<< 【あいまって】 | Home | 【あがる】 >>

【あえて】

1. あえて

（1）私 はあえてみなさんに規則 の見直 しを提案 したいと思 います。／I would dare to suggest we re-examine the regulations.

（2）誰 も助 けてくれないかもしれないが、それでもあえてこの計画 は実行 に移 したいと思 う。／Although nobody might help me, I still want to put this plan into action.

（3）恥 を忍 んであえてお聞 きしますが、今 のお話 のポイントは何 だったのでしょうか。／It’s embarrassing to ask you this, but what was the point of your speech just now?

（4）反感 を買 うのを承知 であえて言 いたいのは、彼 らにこの仕事 を任 せるのはリスクが大 きいということだ。／I know I will offend them, but I dare say that it is too risky to leave this work to them.

（5）これができるのはあなたしかいないから、負担 をかけることはわかっていても、あえてお願 いしているのです。／I know it is a burden for you, but I dare to ask because only you can do this job.

When あえて is followed by a verb of utterance, like 言う, 提案する, お願いする, or verbs like やる, 実行する, it expresses “doing it would offend others or involve risks and difficulties, but I still want to do it, or must do it.” It is used to state a strong opinion or bring up an idea.

2. あえてV-ば

（1）反対 されるのを承知 であえて言 えば、こんな計画 は百害 あって一利 なしだ。／I know there may be objections, but if I dare say so, such a plan is harmful and really no good.

（2）少々 言 いにくいことなのですが、あえて言 わせていただければ、お宅 のお子 さんは他 の学校 に変 わられた方 がいいのではないかと思 うのですが。／It is slightly hard to say, but if I’m allowed to say so, I think your child had better move to another school.

（3）この映画 はあまりストーリー性 がないのだが、あえて説明 すれば、二組 のカップルがあちらこちらを旅 して回 り、行 く先々 で事件 が起 こるというものだ。／This movie doesn’t have much of a story line, but if I had to explain it, I’d say it’s a story about two couples traveling here and there and troubles happen at every place they visit.

（4）まだこのプロジェクトの方針 は漠然 としているのだが、あえて言 うとすれば、環境破壊 が進 んでいる地域 に対 して、民間 の援助 によってそれを食 い止 めようというものだ。／The policy of this project is still vague, but if I try to explain it, it is to stop environmental destruction in areas that destruction is taking place, with the support of the private sector.

In these cases, when あえて is followed by a verb of utterance such as 言う, お話しする, or 説明する, it is used as a prefatory expression when one wants to say something in spite an objection or criticism being raised, or when one cannot find an appropriate way to say something.

3. あえて...ない

（1）そのやり方 にあえて反対 はしないが、不満 は残 っている。／I don’t dare to object to that way of doing things, but I’m not satisfied with it.

（2）相手 が偉 い先生 だからといって、あえてへりくだる必要 もない。／It is not necessary to be overly modest, even if he is a great teacher.

（3）親 に反対 されてまで、あえて彼 と結婚 しようとは思 わない。／I won’t dare to marry him, if it’s against my parents’ wishes.

（4）みんなに嫌 がられてまで、あえて自分 の方針 を押 し通 すこともないじゃないか。／Why do you have to push your policy through while putting people off?

When expressions like する必要もない, することもない, しようとは思わない follow, あえて expresses the meaning “others would object or be antagonized, so one doesn’t, or shouldn’t, do such a risky thing.”

<< 【あと1】 | Home | 【あとから】 >>

【あと2】

1. あと

（1）料理 はこのくらいあれば十分 ですね。あと、飲 み物 はこれで足 りますか。／This much food will be enough, right? And will these be enough drinks?

（2）以上 でだいたい分 かったと思 いますが、あと、何 か質問 はありませんか。／I think you have understood more or less everything, but do you have any questions?

（3）A:メンバーはこれだけですね。／These are all the members, right?

B:あ、あと、もしかしたら田中 さんも来 るかもしれないと言 っていました。／Well, Tanaka-san said he might come, too.

あとis placed at the beginning of a sentence or clause. It is used when the speaker remembers something relevant to the matter at hand and adds a piece of information or an after thought.

2. あと+数 量 詞

（1）その仕事 を片 づけるにはあと3日 で十分 です。／Three more days will be enough to finish that job.

（2）あと二人 そろえば野球 チームが作 れる。／We can make a baseball team with two more members.

（3）あと10メートルでゴールインというところで、その選手 は倒 れてしまった。／The runner fell down ten meters before the finish line.

（4）あと少 しで終 わりますので、待 っていただけますか。／I will finish it in a moment, so could you please wait?

In these cases, あとindicates that a certain amount is added to the present number or quantity. It means that, by increasing the quantity by the amount indicated after あと, the conditions would be met for a certain event to take place. In other words, あと indicates the quantity that is needed to fulfill a certain condition, as shown in the following examples.

（例）卒業式まであと1週間だ。←あと1週間で卒業式だ。／It’s one week until the graduation ceremony. ←The graduation ceremony will be in one week.

（例）ビールはもうあと2本しかない。←あと2本でビールはなくなる。／There are only two bottles of beer left. ←The beer will be gone after just two more bottles.

（例）サラダがあと少し残っていますが、誰か食べませんか。←あと少しでサラダも終わりです。／There is a little more salad left—would anyone like to have it? ←The salad is nearly gone.

<< 【あらためる】 | Home | 【あるまじき...だ】 >>

【あるいは】

Typical of written language. Also used in formal spoken language.

1. あるいは

a. N（か）あるいはN

（1）黒 あるいは青 のペンで記入 してください。／Please fill it in using a black or blue pen.

（2）欠席 する場合 には、口頭 かあるいは書面 で届 け出 ること。／If you are going to be absent, oral or written notification is required.

（3）このクラブの施設 は、会員 あるいはその家族 に限 り、使用 することができます。／Only members and/or their families can use the facilities of this club.

（4）応募 は、25 歳以上 、あるいは 20 歳以上 で、職業 をお持 ちの方 に限 ります。／Applications are limited to those over 25 years of age or those in full-time employment aged 20 or more.

（5）被害者 は、包丁 あるいは登山 ナイフのようなもので殺害 されたらしい。／I heard that the victim was killed with something like a kitchen cleaver or a mountaineering knife.

Indicates “either X or Y.” It is often used when giving instructions to indicate “you can choose either X or Y, but choose only one of these,” as in (1) and (2). It is also used for indicating a condition that implies “it’s all right if it conforms to either X or Y,” as in (3) and (4). In the case of (4), suitable answers include X, Y, or both. As shown in (5), it is often used when “there are two possibilities (X or Y), so I don’t know which one to choose.”

XかY, XまたはY, XもしくはY are similar expressions. In everyday spoken language, XかY is often used.

b. ...か、あるいは

（1）申 し込 み書類 は、郵送 するかあるいは事務所 まで持参 してください。／Please bring or send your application form to our office.

（2）A:福岡 へは、どうやって行 ったらいいですかね。／How do I get to Fukuoka?

B:そうですね。新幹線 で行 くか、あるいは飛行機 で行 くか、でしょうね。／Well, either by shinkansen (bullet train), or by air.

（3）社会人 大学院 に入学 するためには、定職 に就 いているか、あるいは 25 歳以上 であることが条件 である。／In order to enter graduate school for working adults, one must have regular employment or be over 25 years old.

（4）就職 しようか、あるいは進学 しようかと迷 っている。／I am thinking about whether to find a job or continue on in school.

（5）A:被害者 は、犯人 は知 らない男 だと言 っています。／The victim says the culprit was unknown to him.

B:本当 に知 らないか、あるいは知 らないふりをしているか、どちらかだな。／It must be one or the other—either he really doesn’t know who it was, or he’s pretending not to know.

（6）景気 は数年 で回復 するのか、あるいは何十年 もかかるのか、まったく予想 できない。／No one can predict whether business conditions will look up in just a few years, or whether it will take decades.

XかあるいはY indicates “either X or Y.” (1) and (2) are examples in which either X or Y is acceptable (but only one is chosen). In (3), it indicates “if it conforms to condition X or Y, either of them can be chosen,” and it is also acceptable if both are true. (4)-(6), indicate “there are two possibilities (X and Y), but I don’t know which one to choose.”

2. あるいは...かもしれない

（1）このぶんでは、明日 はあるいは雪 かもしれない。／If the weather stays like this, it might snow tomorrow.

（2）彼 の言 うことは、あるいは本当 かもしれない。／What he is saying might be true.

（3）これで、手術 は三度目 だが、今回 はあるいはだめかもしれない。／This is the third time for me to have surgery, but this operation might not succeed.

（4）もう何年 も国 には帰 っていない。両親 でも生 きていれば、あるいは帰 りたいと思 ったかもしれないが、知 った人 もほとんどいない今 は、特 になつかしいとも思 わない。／I haven’t gone home for many years. If my parents were alive, I might want to go, but there’s hardly anyone I know these now, so I really don’t miss it so much.

In these cases, あるいはis used in the pattern あるいは...かもしれない and expresses the speaker’s supposition that something is possible. ひょっとすると andもしかすると are similar to あるいは...かもしれない.

あるいは can also be used with other suppositional expressions, such as あるいは...のだろう and あるいは...かもしれない.

3. あるいは...あるいは

（1）高校 を卒業 した学生 たちは、あるいは進学 し、あるいは就職 し、それぞれの進路 を歩 み始 める。／Students who have graduated from high school go off on their own ways, with some continuing on to college and some getting a job.

（2）美 しかった街路樹 も、あるいは横倒 しになり、あるいは途中 から二 つに折 れて、台風 の威力 のすさまじさを物語 っている。／The beautiful trees lining the street have fallen over or been broken in two, attesting to the tremendous power of the typhoon.

（3）風 の音 は、あるいは泣 くが如 く、あるいは呻 くが如 く、高 く低 く、一晩中 谷間 に響 いた。／The sound of the wind reverberated across the valley all through the night, sounding sometimes like crying and sometimes like groaning, at times high and at times low.

This is used to describe multiple situations.

In these cases, あるいはis used in the pattern あるいは...し、あるいは...し, as in (1) and (2), where more than two actions or states are described in parallel and the meaning is something like “someone is..., and someone is....” In (3), it means “sometimes it is..., and sometimes it is....” These are formal expressions used in written language, not in everyday spoken language.

<< 【あるまじき...だ】 | Home | 【あれでも】 >>

【あれで】

1. あれで〈positive evaluation〉

（1）あの人 はいつもきついことばかり言 っていますが、あれでなかなか優 しいところもあるんですよ。／He always says harsh things, but actually he is quite a kind person.

（2）彼女 、体 は小 さいけど、あれでけっこう体力 はあるのよね。／Although she has a small build, she is quite strong physically.

（3）あのレストランって、一見 汚 くてまずそうに見 えるけど、あれでなかなかいけるんですよ。／At first glance, that restaurant looks dirty and not so appealing, but it actually is quite nice.

Used with words likeなかなか and けっこう, this expresses an evaluation of something in which there is an unexpected difference between its appearance and its true nature. The evaluation is expressed after あれで. This is used when praising the person or thing that is the topic of the sentence.

2. あれで〈surprise〉

（1）あのコート、あれで4万 なら安 いものだ。／Forty thousand yen is very cheap for that coat.

（2）え、彼女 あれでスキー初 めてなんですか。すごくうまいじゃないですか。／Is it really her first time to ski? She is a very good skier.

（3）今日 の食堂 の定食 、あれでよく改善 したって言 えるよね。まるで豚 のえさだよ。／Today’s special at the cafeteria was food fit for pigs! How can they say that they’ve improved things?

（4）あの映画 、あれで（も）アカデミー賞 授賞 してるんですか。ちょっとひどすぎると思 いませんか。／Did a movie like that win an Academy Award? Don’t you think that’s awful?

In these cases, あれで expresses slight surprise that a person or thing is in a certain state, has value, or can do something. This can be used for positive remarks, as in (1) and (2), or for negative remarks, as in (3) and (4).

<< 【いかん】 | Home | 【いけない】 >>

【いくら】

1. いくら

a. いくら〈question〉

（1）この本 はいくらですか。／How much is this book?

（2）東京 まで片道 いくらですか。／How much is a one-way ticket to Tokyo?

（3）この絵 はいくらぐらいかなあ。／I wonder how much this picture is.

いくら expresses that a price is unknown. It is used for asking the price.

b. いくら〈indefinite〉

（1）いくらなら案内 してもらってもいいとこちらから先 に提示 した。／I told them beforehand how much I was prepared to pay for a guided tour.

（2）フリーマーケットに出 す品物 は、それぞれいくらで売 るということを決 めてこの書類 に金額 を書 き込 んでください。／Please decide how much you want to charge for each item that you bring to the flea market, and fill in the amounts on this form.

（3）いくら持 ってきてくれという形 で注文 しないと、後 でまた頼 まなければならなくなったりするから、個数 を確認 してください。／If you don’t specify in your order how many items you want delivered, you may have to order more later on, so please confirm the number.

In these cases, いくら indicates an indefinite price or amount. It is used when one is not able to say or it is not necessary to say an exact amount.

2. いくらでも

（1）ビールならまだいくらでもあるから、安 心 して飲 んでください。／We still have plenty of beer, so please feel free to drink it.

（2）これだけ暇 ならいくらでも好 きなことができる。／If I have this much free time, I can do whatever I’d like.

（3）あの人 の代 わりならいくらでもいるから、やめられても全然 困 らない。／It’s no problem whatsoever for me if that person quits, because I can find any number of people to take his/her place.

（4）いくらでもいたいだけここにいてくれてかまわないよ。／I don’t mind if you stay here as long as you want.

Expresses that something is unlimited and means “as much as one wishes.”

3. いくらも...ない

（1）もうワインはいくらも残 っていない。／There is not much wine left.

（2）バスがでるまで時間 はもういくらもない。／There is not much time left until the bus leaves.

（3）駅 までは歩 いていくらもかからなかった。／It didn’t take very much time to get to the station on foot.

（4）収入 はいくらにもならないが、やることに意味 がある。／Though I don’t get paid much for this, it is a worthwhile thing to do.

Expresses that the amount is very small.

4. いくら...ても

a. いくらV-ても

（1）いくら練習 してもうまくならない。／I don’t get better however hard I practice.

（2）いくら食 べても太 らない。／No matter how much I eat, I don’t put on weight.

（3）彼 はいくら誘 っても一度 もパーティーに顔 を出 してくれない。／He never shows up at a party no matter how many times I invite him.

（4）私 がいくら「お祝 いにはバラの花束 をあげよう」と言 っても、誰 も賛成 してくれなかった。／No matter how many times I said we should give her a bouquet of roses to celebrate the occasion, no one would agree with me.

Means “no matter how many/how many times/how hard one does something.” Used for emphasizing degree or extent.

b. いくら...といっても

［いくらNaだといっても］

［いくらA-いといっても］

（1）いくら給料 がいいと言 っても、残業 がそんなに多 いのでは就職 するのはいやだ。／However high the salary is, I don’t want to take the job if there is that much overtime work.

（2）いくら甘 いものが好 きだと言 っても、一度 におまんじゅうを3つは食 べられない。／However much I like sweets, I can’t eat three manjuu(bean-jam buns) at a sitting.

（3）いくらここの食 べ物 がまずいと言 っても、生協 食堂 よりはましだろう。／However bad the food here is, it would be better than a co-op restaurant.

Means “I acknowledge that..., but still” and is used to emphasize an assertion that follows.

c. いくら...からといって（も）

（1）いくら淋 しいからと言 って、夜中 の3時 に友達 に電話 するなんて非常識 だ。／Even if he feels lonely, calling a friend at three o’clock in the morning shows a lack of common sense.

（2）いくら体 にいいからと言 っても、毎日 そればかり食 べ続 けていては病気 になってしまう。／No matter how good it is for your health, you will get sick eating the same thing every day.

（3）いくら新 しいのを買 うからと言 っても、何 も古 いのをすぐに捨 ててしまうことはないんじゃないか。／Even though you’re buying a new one, there isn’t any need to throw away the old one straight away, is there?

Takes the pattern いくらXからといって（も）Y and means “you might think that X leads to the conclusion Y, but that is strange.” Implies a slight criticism and is followed by an objection against Y. In (1), for example, it is “not common sense” to do Y (calling a friend in the middle of the night) just because of X (being lonely).

d. いくら...からといっても

（1）いくら才能 がないからと言 っても、10 年 もピアノをやっていれば簡単 な伴奏 ぐらいはできるだろう。／Although you say that he has no talent at all, if he has been playing the piano for ten years, he should at least be able to play a simple accompaniment.

（2）いくら不器用 だからと言 っても、それだけきれいにセーターが編 めれば上出来 だ。／However clumsy you may say you are, knitting that beautiful sweater shows you are pretty good after all.

（3）いくら私 が料理 がうまいからと言 っても、プロとは違 うんだからそういうこったものは作 れませんよ。／Even though I may be pretty good at cooking, I am not a professional, so I can’t make something as elaborate as that.

Similar to Usage 4c above, with the difference that Y is not explicit. Means something likes “even if X, what follows is (not Y) but Z” and expresses the speaker’s refutation of Y. In (1), for example, the speaker is saying that even if X (“he has no talent for playing the piano”) is true, it doesn’t follow that “he can’t play the piano” (Y), but that “he should be able to play a simple accompaniment” (Z).

e. いくらなんでも

（1）そういう言 い方 はいくらなんでもひどすぎるよ。／There’s no excuse for such a harsh statement.

（2）いくらなんでも、その服 はお母 さんには派手 すぎないか。／Be that as it may, don’t you think that outfit is too flashy for our mother?

（3）この料理 はいくらなんでも辛 すぎてとても食 べられない。／I don’t care what you think, for me this food is so spicy that there’s no way I can eat it.

An adverbial idiom often used with ...すぎる. Expresses a feeling of criticism, as in “even if I take various circumstances into consideration, it’s still wrong/unusual/beyond common sense.”

5. いくらV-たところで

（1）いくらがんばってみたところで結果的 には同 じことだ。／No matter how hard you try, you’ll get the same result.

（2）いくら隠 してみたところで、もうみんなにはばれているんだから仕方 がないよ。／Even if you try to hide the fact, there’s nothing you can do since everyone already knows about it.

（3）いくらいいドレスを買 ったところで、どうせ着 ていくところがないんだから無駄 になるだけだ。／There’s no point in buying such a great dress, since you have no place to wear it.

（4）いくら話 し合 ったところで、彼 らは自分 の意見 を変 える気 はないんだから、話 し合 うだけ無駄 だ。／No matter how many times we discuss it, it’s a waste of time because they have no intention of changing their opinion.

When いくらV-たところで is followed by phrases like同じだ, 仕方がない, or 無駄だ, it means “no matter how hard one tries to do something, the situation doesn’t change” or “it’s a waste to work so hard.” This is similar to いくら...ても in Usage 4a, but Usage 5 includes a feeling of resignation because the result of the action will be meaningless. This is used to give advice that “you should not do something because....”

<< 【いささか】 | Home | 【いじょう】 >>

【いざしらず】

［Nはいざしらず］

（1）昔 はいざしらず、今 は会社 を 10 も持 つ大 実業家 だ。／I don’t know about his past, but now he is a business magnate who has ten companies.

（2）両親 はいざしらず、我々 は兄弟 として妹 の結婚 を許 すわけにはいかない。／I don’t know what our parents think, but as her brothers we can’t allow our sister’s marriage.

（3）幼稚園 の子供 ならいざしらず、大学生 にもなって洗濯 もできないとは驚 いた。／I understand that a kindergarten child may not know how to do laundry, but I’m surprised that even a college student doesn’t know how.

（4）暇 なときだったらいざしらず、こんなに忙 しいときに客 に長居 されてはたまらない。／When I have lots of time I don’t mind, but I can’t stand to have long-term guests at such a busy time.

（5）国内 旅行 ならいざしらず、海外旅行 に行 くとなると、準備 も大変 だ。／Maybe not on a domestic trip, but if you are going on an overseas trip, there will be lots of preparation.

Following a noun plus は, なら, or だったら, いざしらず means “I don’t know/care about such-and-such, but....” Before and after いざしらず there are contrastive pairs, such as “the past and the present,” “a kindergarten child and a college student,” or “free time and busy time.” It is used to express that the matter in the latter half is superior in degree or importance to, or is a special case of, the matter in the first half. In the latter half, an expression of astonishment or something like “it’s a problem” often follows. The expression in (1) is an idiomatic way to say “different from the past.”

<< 【いじょう】 | Home | 【いずれ2】 >>

【いずれ1】

1. いずれ

（1）進学 と就職 といずれの道 を選 ぶのがいいか、自分 でも決 めかねている。／I can’t decide which choice is better, furthering my education or finding a job.

（2）「はい」「いいえ」「どちらでもない」のいずれかに○をつけてください。／Please circle one: “Yes,” “No,” or “Neither.”

This is a way of saying どちら or どれ using a form more common in written language. It indicates one selection among two or more choices.

2. いずれにしても

（1）山田 は仕事 の都合 で遅 れるとは言 っていたが、いずれにしても来 ることにはなっている。／Yamada told me he would be late because of work, but he is going to be coming, at any rate.

（2）後遺症 が出 る可能性 もあるが、いずれにしても回復 に向 かっていることだけは確 かだ。／There is a chance of lingering complications, but all in all he is definitely recovering.

（3）彼 が辞 めるのがいいのかどうかはわからないが、いずれにしてもこのまま放 っておくわけにはいかない。／I’m not sure whether he should resign, but anyhow we can’t just leave things as they are.

（4）A:ここでついでにお昼 ご飯 食 べましょうか。／Shall we have lunch here, as long as we’re here anyway?

B:そうですね。いずれにしても、どこかで食 べておかなきゃならないんだし。／Yes, let’s. At any rate, we have to have lunch somewhere.

いずれにしても is placed at the beginning of a sentence or clause and expresses “there are many possibilities to choose from, but anyway no matter which one you choose....” It is used to emphasize that the thing following いずれにしてもis something true or definite. It is used in both spoken and written language. いずれにしろ and いずれにせよ are more formal ways to say this. It can also be reworded as 何にしても.

3. いずれにしろ

（1）やりたい仕事 はいろいろあるが、いずれにしろこんな不況 では希望 する職 にはつけそうもない。／There are lots of jobs I want to do, but having said that, I don’t think I will get one that I want in this recession.

（2）ちょっと来客 があったりするかもしれませんが、いずれにしろこの日 なら時間 が取 れるので大丈夫 です。／We might have a visitor or two in for a while, but even so I can make time for you on that day.

（3）もっといい機種 が出 るまで待 ってもいいけれど、いずれにしろいつかはパソコンを買 わなければならないのなら、この機会 に買 ってしまったらどうか。／It’s OK to wait until a better model comes out, but if you have to buy a computer sooner or later, why don’t you take this opportunity to buy one?

いずれにしろ is a formal way to sayいずれにしても.

4. いずれにせよ

（1）今日 はこの問題 にはもう触 れませんが、いずれにせよ今後 も考 えていかなければならないとは思 っています。／I won’t talk about this problem anymore today, but at any rate, I am thinking that it has to be considered in the future, too.

（2）今後 誰 にこのプロジェクトを任 せるかは未定 だが、いずれにせよ彼 には降 りてもらうことに決 めた。／It hasn’t been decided who will be entrusted with this project, but at any rate, I’ve made up my mind to have him step down.

This is a formal way to sayいずれにしても.

5. いずれも

（1）ここにございます宝石類 は、いずれも最高級品 でございます。／The jewelry here is all of the highest quality.

（2）今日 の講演会 のお話 はいずれも大変 興味深 いものでした。／The lectures today were all very interesting.

This is a formal and polite way to sayどちらも or どれも.

<< 【いわば】 | Home | 【うえ】 >>

【いわゆる】

［いわゆるN］

（1）これがいわゆるエスニック料理 というものですか。／Is this what’s called ethnic cuisine?

（2）彼女 はいわゆる普通 のOLで、役職 に就 きたいなどとは考 えたこともなかった。／She is a so-called “office lady,” an ordinary working woman, and she had never thought that she wanted to be promoted to a managerial position.

（3）彼 も、いわゆるワールドミュージックのブームに乗 って、世界的 に売 れるようになった歌手 の一人 だ。／He is one of the singers who became popular all over the world by getting on the so-called world music bandwagon.

（4）A:うちの大学 、最近 またアメリカの大学 と姉妹校 になったんです。これで8校 目 ですよ。／Recently, my university became a sister school with another university in America. This is our eighth partner school.

B:ああ、いわゆる「大学 の国際化 」というやつですね。そういうのが国際化 だと思 っている人 が、まだたくさんいるんですねえ。／Oh, yes, it’s what they call “the internationalization of universities.” There are still lots of people who regard things like that as internationalization.

Means “it is generally called....” Used to explain something clearly using everyday words. There are cases, as in (4), in which it conveys that the expression or concept in question is unfavorable to the speaker.

<< 【うち】 | Home | 【える】 >>

【うる】

［R-うる］

（1）彼 が失敗 するなんてありえない。／It’s impossible for him to fail.

（2）それは彼女 になしえた最大限 の努力 だったに違 いない。／It must been the best effort that she could put forth.

（3）その絵 のすばらしさは、とても言葉 で表 しうるものではない。／It can’t be described in words how wonderful that picture is.

（4）確 かに外国人 労働者 が増 えればそういう問題 も起 こり得 るだろう。／If the number of foreign workers increases, those kinds of problems might possibly occur, too.

（5）彼 の自殺 は誰 もが予期 し得 なかったことだけに、そのショックは大 きかった。／No one could have expected his suicide, so it was a great shock to us.

（6）彼 の仕事 ぶりには失望 の念 を禁 じ得 ない。／I cannot help being disappointed with his way of working.

うる joins to a verb stem. Both うる and える can be used in the dictionary form, but in the masu-form, negative form, and ta-form, only えます, えない, and えたare used. These expressions mean “one can do a certain action” or “it is possible that a certain situation will be realized.” In the negative, it means “one cannot do an action” or “it is impossible for a situation to be realized.” V-れる indicates potential, as in 書ける and 読める, and is only used with volitional verbs. うる, on the other hand, can also be used with non-volitional verbs, as in (1) and (4). However, unlike V-れる, it cannot be used to express an ability.

（×）彼はフランス語が話しうる。／He is possible to speak French.

（○）彼はフランス語が話せる。／He can speak French.

Generally considered to be written language, but ありえない can also be used in daily conversation.

<< 【お...いたす】 | Home | 【お...ください】 >>

【お...いただく】

［おR-いただく］

［ごNいただく］

（1）今日 は遠 いところをわざわざお集 まりいただきましてありがとうございます。／Thank you very much for coming all the way here today.

（2）ここにお名前 とご住所 をお書 きいただいて、あちらの窓口 へお出 しください。／Please fill in your name and address here, and take it to the teller’s window over there.

（3）お忙 しいのにご連絡 いただき、まことに恐縮 しております。／Thank you so much for contacting me even though you are so busy.

（4）ご住職 にご教示 いただいた禅 の心 を、これからは生活 の中 で実践 していきたいと思 います。／What I have learned from the master about the spirit of Zen, I will put into practice from now on in my daily life.

（5）《案内状 》先生 にはぜひご出席 いただきたく、お知 らせ申 し上 げます。／《in a written invitation to a teacher》This is to let you know about this event, with the sincere hope that you will be able to attend.

お...いただくis used with a verb stem or a noun of Chinese origin that indicates an act. Although it is a humble expression, like ていただく, it is more polite and formal than the latter. In the case of action nouns of Chinese origin, such as 連絡(する), 教示(する), and 出席(する) in (3), (4), and (5), ごNいただくis usually used. However, in the case of 電話(する), お電話いただく is used.

<< 【お...なさい】 | Home | 【お...になる】 >>

【お...なさる】

［おR-なさる］

［ごNなさる］

（1）あの先生 がお話 しなさったことは、多 くの人 たちにとって生 きていく心 の支 えとなるだろう。／What the teacher said will be a real comfort to many people in their lives.

（2）ケニアへはいつご出発 なさるんですか。／When are you going to depart for Kenya?

（3）今度 あなたがその方 達 とお食事 なさるときにでも、一度 ご一緒 させていただけるとうれしいのですが。／I would be delighted if I could accompany you sometime when you have dinner with them again.

（4）どうぞ、お食 べなさい。／Please go ahead and eat. (Please help yourself.)

（5）明子 、自己紹介 なさい。／Akiko, introduce yourself.

Takes either verb stems or nouns of Chinese origin that express an action. An honorific expression, like おR-になる. When used with a verb stem in expressions like お話しなさる ((someone of higher status) speaks) or お食べなさる ((someone of higher status) eats), it sounds a little old-fashioned. When used with a Chinese-origin noun, as in (2), it usually takes the form ごNなさる. When used with なさい (do something, imperative), as in (4) and (5), it is a polite imperative. However, in this case it is not used when talking to a person of higher status.

<< 【お...ねがう】 | Home | 【おいて】 >>

【おいそれと（は）...ない】

［おいそれと（は）V-れない］

（1）子供 を産 んだばかりの母 ネコにはおいそれとは近 づけない。／We can’t easily get close to a mother cat that has just had kittens.

（2）君 ならできるとおだてられても、あんな大役 は責任 も重 いし、おいそれとは引 き受 けられない。／Even though you flatter me that I can do it, I can’t easily undertake such an important task with so much responsibility.

（3）当時 は大変 な不景気 で、大学 を出 たからといっておいそれと就職 できるような時代 ではなかった。／Those were really hard times, so even if someone had graduated from a university, it was not easy to get a job.

（4）お礼 にと言 ってお金 を差 し出 されたが、何 か下心 がありそうなので、おいそれと受 け取 るわけにはいかなかった。／They offered me money to show their gratitude, but I couldn’t easily accept it, because they seemed to have some kind of ulterior motive.

Means that, for some reason, an action can’t be easily done. Used with sentence-final expressions such as the negative form of the potential V-れる and indicates that the action expressed by a verb is impossible. Sometimes おいそれと...する modifies nouns, such as 時代 in (3). In that case, too, the noun is followed by a negative expression. V-るわけにはいかない, as in (4), expresses impossibility.

<< 【おかげで】 | Home | 【おそらく】 >>

【おきに】

［数量詞+おきに］

（1）大学 行 きのバスは 10 分 おきに出 ている。／The buses to the university run every ten minutes.

（2）この薬 は2時間 おきに飲 んでください。／Please take this medicine every two hours.

（3）この道路 には 10 mおきにポプラが植 えられている。／On this street, poplars have been planted at intervals of ten meters.

（4）このあたりは高級 住宅 街 で、2軒 おきぐらいに外車 を持 っている家 がある。／This area is an upscale residential district, and every third house or so has an imported car.

（5）映画館 に入 ると、座席 は一 つおきにしかあいていなかったので、友達 とは離 れて座 ることになった。／When we got into the theater, every other seat was taken, so my friend and I ended up sitting separately.

Usually follows a word expressing time or distance and means “with that amount of time or space in between.” The words used with おき in (4) and (5) don’t express distance, but they do refer to things arranged in a line (houses (4), seats (5)) and are interpreted to express distance. When おきに refers to a point in time or space, as in (1)-(3), it can be replaced with ごとに. However, when おきに and ごとに are used to refer to the number one, they differ in meaning, as shown in the examples below.

（例）1年おきに大会が開かれる。（2年に1回）／The meeting is held every other year. (= once every two years)

（例）1年ごとに大会が開かれる。（1年に1回）／The meeting is held every year. (= once a year)

<< 【おまけに】 | Home | 【おもえば】 >>

【おもう】

1. ...とおもう

a. ...とおもう

（1）今日 は雨 が降 ると思 います。／I think it’ll rain today.

（2）山田 先生 は来 ないと思 う。／I think Yamada-sensei won’t come.

（3）あの人 のやり方 はひどいと思 います。／I think the way he does things is awful.

（4）彼 の言 ったことはうそだと思 う。／I feel what he said was a lie.

（5）確 か、机 の上 に置 いたと思 う。／I’m sure I put it on the desk.

（6）あなたには幸 せになってほしいと思 うから、あえてこういうきつい忠告 をするのです。／I want you to be happy, so that is why I am giving you such stern advice.

（7）こんな忙 しい会社 にいつまでもいては過労死 しかねないと思 って、思 いきって転職 することにした。／I thought there was a real chance of dying from overwork if I stayed at such a busy company, so I took the plunge and changed jobs.

Follows a clause and indicates that the content of the clause is the speaker’s subjective judgment or personal opinion. When used in an interrogative sentence, its function is to ask for the listener’s personal judgment or opinion . When used in the dictionary form (と思う) or masu-form (と思います) as a declarative statement, the subject is always the speaker and never another person. For example, in (2) the person doing the thinking is 私 (I), not 山田先生 (Yamada-sensei). If the speaker wishes to say that the person doing the thinking is 山田さん, then use of the form 思っている is required, as in 山田さんは（田中さんが来ない）と思っている (Yamada-san thinks that (Tanaka-san will not come)). However, 思う can refer to a third person’s judgment when it is used in ta-form, as in the example below.

（例）山田さんは来ないと思った。／I thought Yamada-san wouldn’t come./Yamada-san thought (someone else) wouldn’t come.

In this case, the original sentence can be interpreted as either “I thought Yamada-san wouldn’t come” or “Yamada-san thought (someone else) wouldn’t come.”

b. ...とおもっている

（1）私 は自分 のしたことが正 しいと思 っている。／I think what I did was right.

（2）イギリスに留学 してよかったと思 っている。／I feel that studying in the U.K. was very good for me.

（3）警察 はあの男 が犯人 だと思 っている。／The police think that man is the culprit.

（4）その実力 で合格 できると思 っているの。／Do you really think your ability can get you a passing grade?

Follows a clause and expresses an opinion, judgment, or belief on the part of the speaker or another person. The difference between 思っている and 思う (see Usage 1a above) is that 思う is interpreted to mean that the speaker’s judgment has been made on the spot, while 思っている implies that someone has held a certain opinion or belief from some point in the past until the present. Also, 思っている can express the opinion or judgment of another person, as in (3) and (4), while 思うcannot.

c. ...とおもわれる

（1）このままの状態 では環境 汚染 は進 む一方 だと思 われる。／There is reason to believe that if things are left as they are, environmental pollution will only get worse.

（2）私 にはこのことが正 しいとは思 われません。／This doesn’t seem right to me.

Means “a certain judgment is formed spontaneously.” Used when stating an opinion objectively rather than arbitrarily, or for softening the impact of an assertion. Often used in academic papers, lectures, and other kinds of written language. と can be replaced by ように to form the expression ように思われる.

2. ...とはおもわなかった

（1）まさか今日 あの人 が来 るとは思 わなかった。／I never thought that person would come today!

（2）こんな街中 にこんな静 かな公園 があるとは思 わなかった。／I didn’t expect there to be such a quiet park like this right in the middle of downtown.

（3）独身寮 の部屋 は狭 いとは聞 いていたが、こんなに狭 いとは思 わなかった。／I’d heard that the rooms in the singles dormitory were small, but I never imagined they would be this small.

（4）いつも反抗的 なお前 がそんなに素直 に謝 るとは思 わなかったな。／I never thought that someone as contrary as you would apologize so sincerely.

（5）A:引 っ越 し先 のおとなりが田中 さんだなんて思 ってもみませんでしたよ。奇遇 ですね。／I never imagined that I was moving in next to you, Tanaka-san. What a coincidence!

B:いや、ぼくも隣 に越 してくるのが君 だとは思 わなかったよ。／Well, I never thought you were the person moving in next door either!

Means that the speaker views a situation or event as completely unexpected. Usually implies a feeling of surprise.

3. R-たいとおもう

（1）アメリカに留学 したいと思 います。／I want to go to the U.S. to study.

（2）結婚式 には是非 参加 したいと思 っております。／I’d very much like to attend your wedding ceremony.

（3）一流 会社 に就職 したいと思 っている。／I’d like to work for a top-ranked company.

（4）では、ご一緒 に乾杯 をしたいと存 じます。／I would now like to ask you all to join me in a toast.

思う is combined with ...たい, which expresses a wish or desire on the part of the speaker, to soften the directness of the ...たい expression and make the statement more polite. 存じます can be used instead of 思う／思います, as in (4), to create an even politer expression. Sentence-final use of ...たい（です） gives an impression of childishness and is not appropriate in formal conversation among adults, in which case たい is usually followed by 思う or のだ.

4. ...おもう

［Na におもう］

［A-くおもう］

（1）先生 に指導 していただけることになって、本当 に幸 せに思 います。／I am very happy to have the opportunity to be instructed by you.

（2）バスが全然 来 ないので、不思議 に思 って聞 いてみたら、昨日 からダイヤが変 わったとのことだった。／I wondered why there were no buses coming, so I asked, and they said that the bus schedule had changed starting yesterday.

（3）この度 の突然 のご逝去 をまことに辛 く悲 しく思 います。／I am deeply grieved to hear of his sudden death.

（4）お会 いできてうれしく思 います。／It was very nice to have the chance to see you.

（5）このような賞 をいただくことができ、まことに光栄 に存 じます。／It is truly an honor to receive a prize such as this.

When 思うfollows the conjunctive form of i-adjectives and na-adjectives that express feelings or emotions, it expresses how the speaker feels. The pattern XをYに（Yく）おもう is also used, as in (2) and (3). To ask about the listener’s impression, どう思う／思いますか are used, as in the example below.

（例）あの人についてどう思いますか。／What do you think of that person?

5. V-ようとおもう

（1）今日 はゆっくり休 もうと思 う。／I’m going to take it easy and rest today.

（2）この仕事 をやめようと思 っている。／I’m thinking of quitting this job.

（3）A:夏休 みはどうするつもりですか。／What are you planning to do this summer vacation?

B:ヨーロッパを旅行 しようと思 っています。／I’m going to tour Europe.

（4）将来 、どんな仕事 をしようと思 っているんですか。／So what sort of work are you going to do in the future?

When combined with the intentional form of a verb, と思う expresses the speaker’s plans or intentions. In interrogative sentences, the function of this combination is to ask about the listener’s intentions. When と思う is used with the dictionary form, as in the following example, it indicates that the speaker’s plans are uncertain; this form cannot be used to express intention.

（例）私は来年アメリカに行くと思う。／I think I’ll go to the U.S. next year.

6. ...ようにおもう

［N／Na　であるようにおもう］

［A／V　ようにおもう］

（1）太田 くんは内気 なので、ウェイターの仕事 は向 いていないように思 う。／Because Ota-kun is shy, I don’t think he is suited to be a waiter.

（2）住民 の多 くが反対 していることを考 えると、マンションの建築 は見合 わせた方 がいいように思 う。／Considering the fact that many local residents are opposed to it, I think it would be better to postpone construction of the condominiums.

（3）この社員 旅行 のプランはちょっとゆとりがなさすぎるように思 うのですが。こんなに短期間 であちこち動 き回 っても疲 れるだけではないでしょうか。／I think the plan for this company trip doesn’t include enough free time. Moving from one place to another in such a short time will only tire everyone out.

（4）《上司 に》パソコンは一人 に一台 あった方 が仕事 の能率 も上 がるように思 うのですが、購入 するわけにはいきませんか。／《to one’s boss》I think we would be able to work more efficiently if each person had his/her own computer. Couldn’t we buy more computers?

（5）国民 一人一人 の幸 せを考 えることは首相 としての当然 の義務 であるように思 われますが、首相 はいかがお考 えでしょうか。／It seems to me that considering the happiness of each and every citizen is a given duty of the prime minister. What do you, as prime minister, think about this?

Expresses a mild assertion of opinion. Often used when the speaker thinks there is a possibility that the listener has a different opinion, or when the speaker offers an opinion with which it is difficult for the listener to agree. When an even more euphemistic expression is desired, ように思われる is used.

7. N（のこと）をおもう

（1）親 が子供 を思 う気持 ちは何 にも変 えられない。／Nothing can replace the love parents have for their children.

（2）いつもあなたのことを思 っている。／I’m always thinking about you.

（3）試験 のことを思 うと心配 で眠 れない。／When I think about the exam, I get so worried that I can’t sleep.

（4）母 の優 しさを思 うと気持 ちが安 らぐ。／My mind is at peace when I remember my mother’s gentleness.

When combined with a noun or a noun followed by のこと, 思う means that the speaker thinks or feels strongly about something. Depending on the meaning of the preceding noun, it can express a variety of cognitive processes, including imagination, retrospection, anxiety, reserve, and love.

8. Nを...とおもう

［Nを　N／Na　だとおもう］

［Nを　A／V　とおもう］

（1）最初 は保子 さんを男 の子 だと思 った。／At first, I thought Yasuko-san was a boy.

（2）人々 は私 の考 えを奇想天外 だと思 ったようだ。／People seemed to consider my idea to be bizarre.

（3）みんな、彼 の提案 を実現 不可能 だと思 って相手 にしなかった。／Everyone thought his suggestion was unfeasible and wouldn’t go along with him.

（4）彼女 の横顔 を美 しいと思 った。／I thought her profile was beautiful.

（5）みんなが彼 のことを死 んだと思 っていた。／Everyone thought he had died.

（6）彼 は自分 のことを天才 だと思 っている。／He considers himself a genius.

Used to express one’s feeling, impression, or judgment concerning something. Sometimes Nが is used instead of Nを, as below:

（例）人々は私の考えが奇想天外だと思ったようだ。／People seemed to think my idea was bizarre.

Can also be used to indicate that someone has mistaken something or someone for something or someone else, as in (1).

<< 【おもう】 | Home | 【おもったら】 >>

【おもえば】

1. おもえば

（1）思 えば、学生 時代 はみんな純粋 だった。／When I think about it now, back in our student days everyone was pure and innocent.

（2）思 えば、あのころはよくあなたと徹夜 で議論 しましたねえ。／I remember how we used to stay up all night and argue in those days.

（3）A:中島 さん、あのころは毎日 朝 から晩 までお酒 飲 んでましたよね。／Nakajima-san, back then you used to drink every day from morning till night, didn’t you?

B:ええ、思 えば、よくもあのときアル中 で死 ななかったものですよね。もう体 じゅうぼろぼろでしたからね。／Yeah, now that I think about it, it’s a miracle I didn’t die of alcoholism back then. I was a physical wreck.

（4）思 えば、あのとき彼女 に引 き止 められなければ、私 はあの墜落 した飛行機 に乗 って死 んでいたのだ。彼女 は命 の恩人 だ。／When I think back on it, if she hadn’t held me up, I would have gotten on that plane and died when it crashed. I owe her my life.

Used at the beginning of a sentence to describe, with a feeling of yearning or nostalgia, a recollection of the past.

2. いまからおもえば

（1）母 は、私 が下宿 するのに猛反対 したが、今 から思 えばその気持 ちもわからなくもない。／My mother was dead set against my moving into a boarding house. Now that I think about it, I can understand something of what she felt.

（2）あのときは彼 の運営 方針 に反発 したが、今 から思 えば彼 がああいう方針 をとったことも理解 できる。／At the time I opposed his management policy, but now when I think about it, I can understand why he took that kind of approach.

（3）今 から思 えば、あのとき転職 しておけばよかったとつくづく思 います。当時 は転職 してもいい仕事 ができるとは限 らないと思 ってしりごみしたのですけどね。／Now that I think about it, I really believe I should have changed jobs back then. At the time, though, I thought that even if I changed jobs there would be no guarantee of a good career, so I dragged my feet.

（4）今 から思 えば、あのとき結婚 するのをやめてよかったと思 う。婚約 を破棄 したときは、本当 にこれでいいのかと思 って、ものすごく不安 だったが。／Now that I think about it, I’m glad I decided not to get married back then. Although when I broke off my engagement, I was really worried about whether or not I was doing the right thing.

Means that the speaker is reconsidering a past situation or event. Used when one’s knowledge or opinion has changed and one can now look at things differently. Expresses the notion that one can now understand someone else’s actions, even though it wasn’t possible in the past, or that one now thinks his/her own past behavior was a mistake, even though s/he used to think it was appropriate, or vice versa. Example (1) means “At the time, I couldn’t understand the reason why my mother was against it, but now I can,” and (3) means “At the time, I thought I shouldn’t change jobs, but now I think if I had, I could have gotten a better one.” This expression often describes a contrast between the past and the present. 今から思うと can also be used.

<< 【おもえば】 | Home | 【および】 >>

【おもったら】

［N／Na　だとおもったら］

［A／V　とおもったら］

（1）息子 の姿 が見 えないと思 ったら、押 し入 れの中 で寝 ていた。／I was wondering where my son could be, and there he was sleeping in the closet.

（2）なんだか寒 いと思 ったら、窓 が開 いていたのか。／I was wondering why it was so chilly, but now I can see it’s because someone left the window open.

（3）めがねがないないと思 ったら、こんなところに置 き忘 れていたよ。／I was wondering why I couldn’t find my glasses, but now I see that I left them here, of all places!

（4）冷蔵庫 においしそうなケーキがあると思 ったら、お客 さん用 だった。／I was thinking that the cake in the refrigerator looked delicious, but it was for our guests.

（5）最近 上田 さんが学校 に来 ないと思 っていたら、交通 事故 で入院 しているらしい。／I was wondering why Ueda-san isn’t coming to school lately, and then I heard that she’s in the hospital because of a traffic accident.

（6）誰 もいないのにうちに電気 がついていると思 ったら、弟 が遊 びに来 て勝手 に上 がり込 んでいたのだった。／I was wondering why the lights were on even though no one was home, but it turned out that my younger brother had dropped by for a visit and let himself in.

Placed after a clause and expresses an unsettled feeling about something for which the cause or reason is unknown. Followed by a statement of the cause, reason, or explanation, which also indicates that the matter has been satisfactorily resolved for the speaker. Example (1) means “I thought it was strange that my son wasn’t here, but I found him sleeping in the closet, so then I understood,” and (2) means “I was wondering why it was chilly, but then I noticed that the window had been left open, so I could understand the reason.” When an inexplicable situation continues over a period of time, と思っていたら can be used, as in (5).

<< 【か】 | Home | 【が2】 >>

【が1】

1. Nが

（1）あの人 が山本 さんです。／That person is Yamamoto-san.

（2）隣 のうちには猫 が3匹 いる。／There are three cats in the house next door.

（3）あ、財布 が落 ちている。／Look, there’s a wallet on the floor.

（4）この本 は表紙 がきれいですね。／This book has a beautiful cover, doesn’t it.

（5）私 はジャズが好 きです。／I like jazz.

（6）外交官 になるには語学力 が必要 だ。／You need to be good at languages to be a diplomat.

（7）彼 は 10 ヶ国語 ができるらしい。／I heard that he can speak ten different languages.

Attaches to a noun and indicates that the noun is the subject of an action or state, as in (1), (2), (3), and (4), or that the noun is the object of a state, as in (5), (6), and (7). When used in proverbs or idioms, it sometimes attaches to words other than nouns, as in 負けるが勝ち (Sometimes you have to lose to win).

2. NがNだから

（1）親 が親 だから、子供 があんなふうに生意気 になるのだ。／With such parents, it’s no wonder the child is so bratty.

（2）もう時間 が時間 だし、今 から行 ってもあのレストランは閉 まってるかもしれないよ。／Considering what time it is now, the restaurant might be closed by the time we get there.

（3）デパートをぶらぶら歩 いていて、かわいいネックレスを見 つけた。とても気 に入 ったのだが、なにしろ値段 が値段 だったので買 うのはあきらめた。／I was wandering around the department store and found a pretty necklace. I really liked it, but with the price being what it was, I decided not to buy it.

（4）A:再就職 しようと思 ったけど、なかなかむずかしいわ。／I thought I’d try to go back to work, but it’s really quite difficult to find a job.

B:そりゃ、年 が年 だもの。70すぎた人間 なんか今 どきどこも雇 ってくれないわよ。／Well, it’s your age. These days no one wants to hire someone in his seventies.

The same noun is repeated and then followed by a word expressing a reason, such as だから, ので, し, だもの, or もので. In many cases, this pattern expresses a negative evaluation of the noun and is used to describe an inevitable result that arises from it. For example, (1) means the parents are too indulgent of their children, (2) means it is too late to go to the restaurant, (3) means the price is far too expensive, and (4) means that, in B’s opinion, A is too old to get another job.

3. NがNだけに

（1）ここの料理 は、素材 が素材 だけに味 も格別 だ。／The food here is exceptionally tasty because of the ingredients.

（2）この店 は味 は大 したことはないが、場所 が場所 だけにたいていいつも満員 だ。／The food at this restaurant isn’t particularly good, but its location means it’s almost always full.

（3）この店 はとても気 に入 っているのだが、場所 が場所 だけにそうしょっちゅうは来 られないのが残念 だ。／I really like this shop, but because it’s located where it is, unfortunately I can’t come very often.

（4）その映画 は戦時中 の日本軍 の侵略 を扱 ったもので、多 くの評論家 が絶賛 している優 れた作品 だが、内容 が内容 だけに、一般的 な娯楽 映画 と比 べると興行 成績 は格段 に悪 かった。／The movie deals with the aggression of the Japanese army during the war. It is an excellent work that many critics have praised highly, but because of the subject matter, box office returns were markedly worse than those of ordinary movies made for entertainment.

（5）学長 が収賄 容疑 で逮捕 された。今 までも小 さな不祥事 はあったが、マスコミには騒 がれないよう注意 してきた。しかし、今回 はことがことだけに、マスコミの取材 からは逃 れられないだろう。／The president of the university was arrested on suspicion of bribery. There have been minor scandals before, but care was always taken to keep the media from making anything of them. However, this time, with the situation being what it is, there will be no stopping the mass media from covering the story.

Repetition of the same noun indicates that a certain outcome is natural or inevitable, considering the characteristics of that noun. NがNだけに is followed by a description of the natural or inevitable outcome. The listener/reader does not know the exact nature of the noun’s characteristics until s/he reaches the description in the latter part of the sentence. For example, in (1), the description 味も格別だ (exceptionally tasty) tells us the ingredients are good. However, in the sentence 素材が素材だけに大した料理はできやしない (Because the ingredients are what they are, the food can’t be very good), the interpretation is that the ingredients are bad. (2) means a place that is conveniently located and easy to get to. On the other hand, (3) means a place that is inconveniently located and hard to get to. ことがことだけに in (5) is an idiomatic expression. In this example, it means “because this situation is serious.”

4. NがNなら...（が）

（1）時代 が時代 なら、この本 も売 れたかもしれないが、今 の時代 では人間 の生 き方 を問 うような本 は若 い人 には読 まれない。／If times were different, this book might have sold well, but in this day and age, young people don’t read books that raise questions about how to live.

（2）世 が世 ならあいつも出世 できただろうに。／In another time and place, she probably would have been successful.

（3）俺 も大学 が大学 ならもう少 しましな仕事 にもつけたのだろうが、この大学 ではせいぜいこの会社 ぐらいがいいところだ。／I suppose if I had graduated from a better university, I could have found a better job, but this is the best company anyone from a university like mine could hope to work for.

Repetition of the same noun indicates that the speaker is making the supposition “if the conditions were suitable....” NがNなら is accompanied by expressions such asだろうが, だろうに or かもしれないが, and a statement or description of the actual state of affairs then follows. (1) means “if it were a time when many people thought seriously about how to live,” (2) means “if people in society evaluated him correctly,” and (3) means “if I had graduated from a better university.” This pattern is used to hypothesize a situation that is better than reality; it means “if the situation were X, a good result like Y would follow.” Because the situation hypothesized is one that is actually impossible, a sense of pity, regret, or resignation is implied.

5. NがNならNもNだ

（1）この生徒 はいつも教師 に口答 えばかりして困 る。親 もすぐ学校 にどなりこんでくるし、まったく、親 が親 なら子 も子 だ。／This student always causes trouble to his teachers by answering back. His parents often come storming into the school with complaints, too. With such parents, it’s no wonder the children behave the way they do.

（2）まったく、おじさんがおじさんなら、おばさんもおばさんだよ。おじさんが頑固 なのはわかっているんだから、嘘 でも「ごめんなさい」って言 えば喧嘩 なんかすぐにおさまるのに。／(to an aunt and uncle) Honestly, you two are both just as bad as each other. (to the aunt) You know he’s obstinate, so if you say “I’m sorry,” even if you don’t mean it, the quarrel will quickly be resolved.

The first noun (repeated in NがNなら) is different from the second noun (repeated in NもNだ), but the two nouns are related. The expression as a whole conveys a negative evaluation: both N’s are equally bad. (1) means that the parents and child are equally problematic, and (2) means that both the uncle and aunt are bad, because they are equally stubborn. Used to criticize both parties or elements.

6. V-たがさいご→【がさいご】

7. V-るがはやいか→【はやいか】

<< 【が2】 | Home | 【かえって】 >>

【かい】

1. かいが　ある／ない

［Nのかいが　ある／ない］

［V-たかいが　ある／ない］

（1）努力 したかい（が）あって、無事 合格 することができた。／As a result of all the effort I put in, I was able to pass the exam.

（2）コンクールで優勝 できるなんて、一日 も休 まず練習 したかいがあったね。／The fact that we won the competition shows that practicing every single day was worth it.

（3）警官 の懸命 の説得 のかいもなく、その男性 は警官 の顔 をしばらくじっと見 つめた後 、屋上 から飛 び降 りてしまったという。／All the policeman’s earnest persuasion was to no avail. They say the man stared at him for a while and then jumped off the roof.

（4）今 になってまったく違 う意見 を主張 されたのでは、せっかくみんなが歩 み寄 って意見 を調整 したかいがなくなるじゃないか。／If you’re going to assert a completely different opinion now, it will mean the trouble everyone took to make concessions and coordinate their opinions was really all for nothing.

Follows a verb or noun expressing an action and indicates that the action has been rewarded or the anticipated effect of the action has been achieved. When the negative form is used, it means that there was no reward despite the effort, or no result from the action.

2. R-がい

（1）やりがいのある仕事 を求 めて転職 する。／I want to find some work with a purpose, so I am changing jobs.

（2）仕事 のほかに生 きがいを見出 せないような人生 ではあまりにも寂 しいではないか。／If you can’t find a reason to live other than your work, it is so sad, isn’t it.

（3）もっと働 きがいのある職場 に移 りたいと思 うが、この不況 では転職 もなかなかむずかしそうだ。／I’d like to move to a workplace with a more rewarding job, but it seems pretty difficult to change jobs in this recession.

（4）こんなに喜 んでもらえるのだったら、料理 のしがいがある。／If it makes you this happy, then cooking is worth it.

（5）一度 失 われた森林 を元 に戻 すのは大 変 なことではあるが、そこに住 む人 たちの暮 らしもかかっているだけに、苦労 のしがいもあるというものだ。／It is hard to restore forestland once lost, but the people living there depend on it for their livelihoods, so it is well worth the trouble.

Attaches to a verb stem and means that an action has value or is effective or rewarding. It is used with only a limited range of verbs. When the action is difficult to accomplish or requires great effort, as in (4) and (5), it indicates that the effort is worthwhile and meaningful.

<< 【かい】 | Home | 【かえる】 >>

【かえって】

（1）親切 で言 ったつもりなのだが、かえって怒 らせてしまったようだ。／I meant to say it out of kindness, but it made her angry instead.

（2）間 に合 うようにと思 ってタクシーに乗 ったのに、渋滞 のせいでかえって遅 くなってしまった。／Even though I took a cab so I would arrive in time, I ended up being late because of a traffic jam.

（3）昨日 買 ったカーテンは少 し派手 すぎたかなと思 っていたが、かえって部屋 が明 るくなってよかった。／I was afraid that the curtains I bought yesterday were too loud, but I’m happy to say that they’ve made the room brighter.

（4）A:お見舞 いに来 てくれたお礼 に、川井 さんにはお菓子 でも持 って行 こうか。／Shall I bring a box of cookies or something to thank Kawai-san for visiting me when I was ill?

B:いや、そんなことをしたら、かえって向 こうが気 を遣 うよ。／No, if you did that, it would just make her feel beholden.

（5）A:この間 はひどいことを言 ってしまって、悪 かった。／I’m sorry I said such an awful thing the other day.

B:いや、かえって良 かったよ。あれから君 の言葉 を思 い出 してぼくもいろいろ反省 したんだ。／No, it was actually good. After that, I thought over many things that you had said.

Used when a result is the opposite of one’s intention or expectation. Example (1) means “contrary to expectation, something said out of kindness to another person made him angry,” and (4) means “one would expect that bringing a box of cookies would make someone happy, but instead it would make her feel beholden.” Example (5) means “I thought I hurt the other person because I said such an awful thing, but it was actually a good chance for him to reflect on his conduct.” Indicates an outcome that is contrary to what one might expect in normal circumstances. It is therefore not likely to be used for unpredictable events.

（×）今日は雨が降ると思っていたが、かえっていい天気になった。／I thought it would rain today, but instead it was a beautiful day.

（○）今日は雨が降ると思っていたが、いい天気になった。／I thought it would rain today, but it turned out to be a beautiful day.

<< 【かえる】 | Home | 【がかる】 >>

【がかり】

がかり is a word derived from the verb かかる. かかる may mean “take,” as in時間／お金がかかる (take time/money), “see/receive treatment,” as in 医者にかかる (see a doctor), “be affected,” as in 雨がかかる (get wet in the rain), “start,” as in仕事にかかる (get started with work), and so on.

1. 数 量 詞 +がかり

（1）グランドピアノを5人 がかりでやっと運 んだ。／It took five people to move the grand piano.

（2）3日 がかりで作 り上 げた巨大 な雪 だるまは、翌日 のポカポカ陽気 ですぐに溶 けてしまった。／The enormous snowman it had taken us three days to build melted away quickly in the warm sunshine of the following day.

（3）5年 がかりの調査 の結果 、その湖 の生態系 は壊 れかかっているということがわかった。／As a result of five long years of research, we found that the ecosystem of the lake was breaking down.

（4）さすが横綱 は体 が大 きくて力 も強 いので、高校生 力士 が3人 がかりで向 かっていってもまるで勝 ち目 はなかった。／The yokozuna (grand champion) was as big and strong as you might expect, so there was no chance for a win by any of the three high school wrestlers who faced off against him.

Attaches to words like 人, 日, or 時間 and expresses an action that requires many people or a lengthy time to be accomplished. Followed by an expression of the action that was difficult and required such effort.

2. Nがかり

（1）彼女 は 30 才 にもなって、親 がかりで留学 した。／She studied abroad totally financed by her parents, even though she was already thirty years old.

（2）男 は「君 はバラのように美 しいね」などと、芝居 がかりのせりふを吐 いた。／The man melodramatically spewed out lines like “You are as beautiful as a rose.”

Means something like “depending on/being served by (one’s parents),” as in (1), or “has the quality of (a theatrical performance),” as in (2). There are no other examples but 親がかり for the first type of usage. For the second type, 神がかり (possessed; fanatic) is also used, but there are very few other nouns to which がかり can be attached. The second type is also used in the forms Nがかっている and Nがかった; in such cases, a wider range of words is used, like 青みがかった (with blue overtones) and 左がかった (left-leaning).

3. R-がかり

（1）広場 でトランペットの練習 をしていると、通 りがかりの人 が何人 も足 を止 めて聞 いていった。／When I was practicing my trumpet in a public square, a number of passersby stopped to listen.

（2）それは他 の部署 の企画 だったが、担当者 にいくらかアドバイスもしたので、行 きがかり上 しかたなく私 も関 わることになってしまった。／Though it was another department’s project, since I had given some advice to the person in charge, I ended up getting involved with it myself.

Example (1) means “happened to pass by.” 行きがかり上 in (2) means “because of the sequence of events or situation up to this time.” (1) and (2) are idiomatic expressions, and がかり cannot be attached to any other verbs.

<< 【がさいご】 | Home | 【かたがた】 >>

【がたい】

［R-がたい］

（1）信 じがたいことだが本当 なのだ。／It’s hard to believe, but it’s true.

（2）あいつの言 うことは何 の根拠 もないし常識 はずれで、とうてい理解 しがたい。／What he says is groundless, absurd, and hardly comprehensible.

（3）日本 が戦時中 にアジア諸国 で名 もない人 たちを理由 もなく殺 したことは、動 かしがたい事実 である。／It is an indisputable fact that, during the war, the Japanese Army killed ordinary people in Asian countries for no reason.

（4）彼 は部下 の女性 に対 するセクシャル・ハラスメントで告発 されたにもかかわらず、まるで反省 の色 が見 えないばかりか、あの女 は無能 だなどと言 いふらしており、まったく許 しがたい。／Though he was prosecuted by a female subordinate for sexual harassment, he not only shows no sign of remorse, he’s also spreading reports that she’s incompetent. That’s really unpardonable!

Attaches to a verb stem and means that an action is difficult or impossible to do. Combines with verbs of perception and awareness, as in 想像しがたい (hard to imagine), 認めがたい (hard to admit/accept), (考えを) 受け入れがたい (hard to accept other people’s (opinions/ideas)), 賛成しがたい (difficult to agree with). Also used with verbs of utterance, as in 言いがたい (hard to say) and 表しがたい (difficult to express). 動かしがたい事実 in (3) is an idiomatic expression that means something is undeniably true. Often used in written language.

<< 【かたわら】 | Home | 【かつ】 >>

【がち】

1. Nがち

（1）その作家 は、ここ数 年 病気 がちでなかなかまとまった仕事 ができないと言 っている。／The writer says she has been sickly in recent years and has found it hard to complete any work.

（2）このところ、はっきりしない曇 りがちの天気 が続 いているので、洗濯 ものが干 せなくて困 る。／Because we’ve been having such unsettled, mostly cloudy weather these days, it’s a real problem not to be able to hang the wash out to dry.

（3）どうしてあんなことをしたんだと問 いつめると、彼女 は伏 し目 がちに、どうしてもお金 がほしかったのだと答 えた。／When I demanded to know why she had done such a thing, she answered, with downcast eyes, that she had been desperate for money.

（4）「よかったらうちまで車 で送 ってもらえないでしょうか」と、彼女 は遠慮 がちにたずねた。／“Could you possibly take me home in your car?” she hesitantly asked me.

Attaches to a noun and expresses that something has the characteristics of that noun or tends to be in the state it implies. Used when the state implied by the noun is considered unusual or has a negative connotation. Thus the words with which がち can be combined are limited. Examples (3) and (4) are idiomatic expressions.

2. R-がち

（1）寒 い季節 は家 の中 にこもりがちだが、たまには外 にでて体 を動 かした方 がいい。／We tend to stay inside in the cold season, but it’s better to go outside once in a while and get some exercise.

（2）彼女 に電話 すると、どうしても長話 になりがちで、いつも父親 に文句 を言 われる。／When I phone her, it tends to be a long call and my father complains to me about it.

（3）甘 いものはついつい食 べ過 ぎてしまいがちなので、ダイエット中 は気 をつけましょう。／It’s so easy to end up eating too many sweets, so we have to be careful when we’re on a diet.

（4）惰性 で仕事 を続 けていると、この仕事 に飛 び込 んだ頃 の若々 しい情熱 をつい忘 れがちになる。／When we keep on working from sheer force of habit, we tend to forget the youthful zest we once had when we started the job.

（5）「『役不足 』とは『その役 を務 めるには能力 が不足 している』という意味 だ」という解釈 は、ありがちな間違 いだ。／Interpreting the expression yakubusoku as “lacking the ability to fulfil that role” is a common error.

Attaches to a verb and means that one tends to do something even when one doesn’t mean to. Describes an unfavorable action. Often used withどうしても (can’t help but do something), つい (involuntarily, unwittingly), うっかり(carelessly, without realizing), and てしまう (end up doing something). ありがちな in (5) means “something that happens frequently.”

<< 【がてら】 | Home | 【かといえば】 >>

【かというと】

1. ...かというと

［N／Na　 （なの）かというと］

［A／V　 （の）かというと］

（1）彼女 はその仕事 が気 に入 っているそうだ。しかし自分 の時間 を犠牲 にしてでも打 ち込 んでいるかというと、そこまでは行 かないらしい。／I hear she likes her job very much. Having said that, she doesn’t seem to like it enough to sacrifice her own free time for it.

（2）私 はこの国 に失望 させられた。しかし、まったく見捨 ててしまったのかというと、そうでもない。／I have been disappointed by this country. However, if you asked me whether or not I’ve abandoned it completely, I would say no.

（3）彼女 はケーキ作 りがとても上手 なのだが、甘 いものが好 きなのかといえば、そうでもない。／She is very good at making cakes, but whether she likes sweet things or not is another matter.

（4）彼 は入社 して3ヶ月 で会社 を辞 めてしまった。仕事 や給料 が不満 だったのかというとそういうわけではなくて、もともと大学院 に行 きたかったので就職 する気 はなかったのだということだった。／He quit his job within three months. It wasn’t that he was dissatisfied with the work or the salary, but rather that he wanted to go to graduate school and really had no intention of starting a career in the first place.

When かというと is used with a negative expression in phrases such as Xかというとそうではない or Xかというとそうとは限らない, X is negated, even though X would have been the obvious outcome judging from the context of the preceding sentence. For example, in (1), because “she likes her job so much,” one might expect that “she would devote herself to her job even at the expense of her personal time,” but in reality, this is not the case. かといえば is also used.

2. 疑 問 詞 +かというと

（1）私 は彼 がきらいだ。どうしてかというと、いつも人 の悪口 ばかり言 っているからだ。／I don’t like him, and if you want to know why, it’s because he’s always badmouthing people.

（2）私 は一度 も海外 に行 ったことがない。どうしてかというと、飛行機 に乗 るのが恐 いからだ。／I have never been abroad. The reason I haven’t is that I’m scared of flying.

（3）祖父 がいつごろこの家 を建 てたかというと、戦争 が終 わってすぐの頃 、食 べるものも満足 に手 に入 らないような苦労 の時代 だ。／To tell you about the time when my grandfather built this house—it was just after the war ended, and things were so bad that people couldn’t even get enough food.

（4）彼 は入社 して3ヶ月 で一流 企業 を退職 してしまった。やめて何 をするかというと、インドへ行 って仏教 の修行 をするらしい。／He’s left a leading company after three months. What he’ll do after quitting his job is to go to India and devote himself to Buddhist training.

（5）機械 の苦手 な私 がどうやってパソコンに慣 れたかというと、友達 とパソコンでゲームをして遊 んでいるうちに、だんだん恐 くなくなってきたのだ。／If you want to know how someone as technically challenged as I am learned how to use a PC, it’s that I gradually got over my fear by playing computer games with friends.

（6）A:なんで引 っ越 すの。今 のアパート、家賃 も安 いし広 いのに。／Why are you moving? The apartment you live in now is reasonable and roomy.

B:なんでかっていうとね、大家 さんがうるさくて、友達 を呼 ぶと文句 を言 われるし、おまけに壊 れたところも直 してくれないのよね。／Well, to tell you the truth, the landlord is in my face all the time, complaining when I invite friends over, and—what’s more—he won’t repair anything that breaks down.

Attaches to a question with a question word in it and is used to indicate the point of the question. The answer to the question follows. When a reason is expressed, as in (1), the sentence often ends with からだ, ためだ, or のだ. どうしてかというと and なぜかというと (both meaning “the reason being”) are idiomatic expressions. Used to explain something by asking oneself to come up with an answer. かといえば can also be used.

<< 【かな】 | Home | 【かなにか】 >>

【がな】

（1）山田 さんはまだ来 ないの？　遅 れずに来 るように言 っておいたんだがな。／Yamada-san hasn’t come yet? I told her not to be late!

（2）今度 の試験 も駄目 だった。一生懸命 勉強 したつもりなんだがなあ。／I did badly on this test, too...and I was sure I had studied so hard for it.

（3）あした運動会 だろう？　雨 が降 らないといいがなあ。／Tomorrow is the sports day, right? I sure hope it doesn’t rain.

（4）彼 らももう少 し本気 で仕事 に取 り組 んでくれるようになるといいんだがなあ。／I wish they would get a little more serious about their work.

（5）田口 君 、今 、暇 ？　ちょっと手伝 ってくれるとありがたいんだがな。／Taguchi-kun, are you free right now? It’d be great if you could give me a hand for a second.

Consists of the contradictory conjunction が combined with the particle な. Used at the end of a sentence and indicates either bewilderment at the gap between one’s intention and the actual outcome, or a wish for something that has yet to occur. As in example (5), it can be used to make a request. It cannot be attached to a sentence in polite form. It is a spoken language expression used by men when they are talking to themselves or to someone close. The final sound な is sometimes lengthened so it is pronounced as ...がなあ. A similar expression, ...けどな, is used by women.

<< 【がはやいか】 | Home | 【かもわからない】 >>

【かもしれない】

［N／Na／A／V　かもしれない］

In spoken language, the form かもわからない can also be used. In informal conversation, かもね and かもよ may be used. かもしれぬ and かもしれず are formal expressions used in written language.

1. ...かもしれない

（1）A:あの偉 そうにしている人 、ひょっとしてここの社長 かもしれないね。／That person acting so high and mighty might just be the president of this company.

B:そうかもね。／That might be.

（2）ここよりもあっちの方 が静 かかもしれない。行 ってみようか。／It might be quieter over there than it is here. Shall we go?

（3）雨 が降 るかもしれないから、かさを持 っていったほうがいいよ。／It might rain today, so you’d better take your umbrella.

（4）A:来週 のパーティー、行 くの？／Are you going to the party next week?

B:まだ決 めてないんだ。行 くかもしれないし、行 かないかもしれない。／I haven’t decided yet. I may go, or I may not go.

（5）ノックをしても返事 がない。彼 はもう寝 てしまったのかもしれない。／There was no response when I knocked on the door. He might have gone to sleep already.

（6）交渉 相手 が依然 として強気 の姿勢 をくずさないということは、もしかすると何 か強力 な材料 をもっているのかもしれない。／The fact that the other party continues to maintain a hard-line stance in negotiations may be because they have something very powerful to back their position....

（7）見合 い話 が壊 れて、さぞがっかりしているだろうと心配 していたが、それほど気 にしている様子 もない。当 の本人 は案外 平気 なのかもしれない。／I was worried about her being disappointed over the breakdown of the marriage negotiations, but she didn’t seem to mind it that much. She might be unexpectedly unconcerned about it.

（8）ちょっと待 って。今山田 君 が言 ったそのアイデア、ちょっとおもしろいかもしれないよ。／Wait a second, the idea that Yamada-kun just mentioned could be interesting.

Expresses a supposition on the part of the speaker at the time of utterance. Means there is a possibility of something being the case. Compared to にちがいない and だろう, the degree of probability indicated by かもしれない is low, and there is a possibility it won’t happen. Sometimes used in the form のかもしれない, which consists of かもしれない combined with のだ.

As in (8), かもしれない may be used when the speaker wants to avoid an absolute declaration and soften his/her manner of expression. It may also be used by the speaker to preface an assertion, in expressions like 御存知かもしれませんが or 私が間違っているかもしれませんが.

In spoken language, かもしれない is used. In written language—including narrative passages in novels, in which different perspectives may be adopted freely—かもしれなかった can be used, as seen in the following example.

（例）このままでは、達彦自身の会社も危なくなるかもしれなかった。／At this rate, there was a possibility that Tatsuhiko’s own company would be in danger.

2. たしかに...かもしれない

なるほど...かもしれない

（1）A:この計画 は危険 すぎますよ。／This plan is too risky.

B:確 かに、危険 かもしれない。しかし、やってみるだけの価値 はあると思 う。／Certainly, it may be risky. However, it’s worth giving it a try.

（2）A:今 の時代 、小 さいころから受験 勉強 を始 めなければ、いい大学 には入 れないんですよ。／In this day and age, it’s impossible to get into a good university unless you start preparing for the entrance exams when you’re very young.

B:なるほど君 の言 うとおりかもしれない。でも、いい大学 に入 れなくったって、いいじゃないか。／I see. That may well be the case, but would it really matter if we didn’t get into a good university?

（3）女性 は強 くなったといわれている。確 かに、昔 に比 べれば女性 も自由 になったかもしれない。しかし、就職 ひとつを例 にとっても、真 の男女 平等 と言 うにはほど遠 いのが日本 の現状 だ。／It is said that women have gotten stronger. It may be true that women have more freedom compared with the olden days, but if you look at employment as an example, the present situation in Japan is a long way from true gender equality.

Used by the speaker to state a differing opinion, after having first acknowledged the possibility that something the other person has said, or a general opinion, may be true.

3. ...ば／...たら　...かもしれない

a. ...ば／...たら　V-るかもしれない

（1）ここで代打 がホームランでも打 てば、形勢 は逆転 するかもしれない。／If the pinch hitter hits a home run here, the momentum of the game could be reversed.

（2）もう少 しがんばれば、志望校 に合格 できるかもしれない。／If I try a little harder, I may be able to pass the exam for the college I want to get into.

Indicates the speaker’s conjecture regarding what might happen next, based on the assumption of a certain condition.

b. ...ば／...たら　V-たかもしれない

（1）あの時 彼女 を引 き留 めていたら、僕 たちは別 れずに済 んだかもしれない。／If I had stopped her from leaving then, we might not have broken up.

（2）もう少 し早 く手術 をしていれば、あるいは助 かったかもしれない。／Had he been operated on sooner, he might have been saved.

（3）もし、あの時 、救急車 の到着 があと5分 遅 かったら、私 は今 こうして生 きていなかったかもしれない。／If the ambulance had arrived five minutes later than it did at that time, I might not be here alive.

This pattern is used to talk about something that has already happened and to express that, if the conditions had been different, the result could have been different. Used to express the speaker’s regret, or a sense of relief that a negative outcome was avoided.

<< 【からある】 | Home | 【からいう】 >>

【からいい】

［N／Na　だからいい］

［A／V　からいい］

1. ...からいいが

（1）まだ時間 はあるからいいが、今度 からはもうちょっと早 く来 るようにしなさい。／It’s all right, because we have time. But you should come a little earlier next time.

（2）ネギ、買 ってくるの忘 れたの？　まあ、少 し残 っているからいいけど。／Did you forget to buy leeks? Well, there are some left, so I guess it’s OK.

（3）え？　今日 も休 むの？　まあ、あまり忙 しくない時期 だからいいけど。／What? You’re taking today off, too? Well, it’s not such busy time, so I guess it’s all right.

Takes the form からいいが or からいいけど and means “it is not a big problem, because of such-and-such.” Used in spoken language.

2. ...からいいようなものの

（1）大 きな事故 にならなかったからいいようなものの、これからはもっと慎重 に運転 しなさい。／It’s all right since it wasn’t a serious accident, but you should drive more carefully from now on.

（2）だれも文句 を言 ってこないからいいようなものの、一 つ間違 えば大事故 になっていたところだ。／Since no one complained about it, it’s all right, but it could have been a terrible accident.

（3）保険 をかけてあるからいいようなものの、そうでなければ大 変 なことになっていたよ。／Thank goodness we took out insurance; otherwise, we could have been in serious trouble.

（4）ちょうどタクシーが通 りかかったからいいようなものの、あやうく遅刻 するところだった。／It’s a good thing a taxi passed by just then—I wouldn’t have made it otherwise.

（5）大事 に至 らなかったからいいようなものの、今回 の事故 によって、政府 の原子力 政策 は見直 しをせまられそうだ。／It was fortunate that it didn’t lead to something serious, but this accident will force the Government to take a hard look at its nuclear energy policies.

Implies that the worst situation was avoided, but the outcome is still not favorable. Similar in meaning to からいいが／けど, but conveys a stronger feeling of criticism or rebuke.

<< 【からいったら】 | Home | 【からしたら】 >>

【からこそ】

［N／Na　だからこそ］

［A／V　からこそ］

（1）これは運 じゃない。努力 したからこそ成功 したんだ。／This wasn’t just luck. It’s because I made an effort that I succeeded.

（2）A:君 はぼくを正当 に評価 していない。／You’re not giving me a fair evaluation.

B:評価 しているからこそ、もっとまじめにやれと言 っているんだ。　／It’s precisely because I think so much of you that I’m telling you to try even harder.

（3）愛 が終 わったから別 れるのではなく、愛 するからこそ別 れるという場合 もあるのだ。／There are times when a couple breaks up not because their love is gone but because they still do love each other.

（4）忙 しくて自分 の時間 がないという人 がいるが、私 は忙 しいからこそ時間 を有効 に使 って自分 のための時間 を作 っているのだ。／Some people say that they’re too busy and don’t have time for themselves, but it’s just because I am so busy that I make the best use of time and also make time for myself.

An expression that focuses on and emphasizes the reason or cause for something. Often used with のだ. Addition of こそ conveys the strong conviction of the speaker with respect to the reason expressed in the preceding phrase, so this pattern cannot be used to express a cause-effect relation objectively. のだis often used to end the sentence.

（×）今、東京は朝の9時だからこそ、ロンドンは夜中の 12 時だ。／Just because it’s nine o’clock in the morning in Tokyo, it’s midnight in London.

（○）今、東京は朝の9時だから、ロンドンは夜中の 12 時だ。／Now it’s nine o’clock in the morning in Tokyo, so it’s midnight in London.

<< 【かりにも】 | Home | 【かれ】 >>

【がる】

［Na がる］

［A-がる］

［V-たがる］

（1）注射 をいやがるこどもは多 い。／Many children hate injections.

（2）その子 は自分 と同 じくらいの大 きさの犬 をかわいがっている。／The girl loves the dog, which is almost her size.

（3）妻 の死 をいつまでもかなしがってばかりはいられない。わたしには残 されたこどもたちをそだてていく義務 がある。／It is not good for me to do nothing but grieve over the death of my wife. I have a duty to bring up the children she left me.

（4）こわがらなくてもいいのよ。この人 はおかあさんのともだちなの。／You don’t need to be scared. She is a friend of my mother’s.

（5）そのラーメン屋 は朝 8時 から夜 の2時 までやっているうえに安 くてうまいので、近所 の学生 たちに重宝 がられていた。／That Chinese noodle soup shop is open from eight in the morning to two in the following morning, and what’s more, they serve cheap and tasty noodles, so it’s really prized by students in the neighborhood.

（6）こどもがおもちゃをほしがって地 べたにすわりこんで泣 いていた。／The child wanted the toy and plopped down on the floor in tears.

（7）人 の話 を最後 まで聞 かずに口 をはさみたがる人 がときどきいる。／There are some people who love to butt in without listening to the end of a story.

Attaches to adjectives or stems of the V-たい form, which expresses desire. Means thinking, feeling, or acting a certain way. This pattern is used with verbs that describe a situation objectively, so it usually isn’t used in the first person, except in the narrative passages of a novel or in cases like (3) where one looks at oneself objectively. が in 本が読みたい and 車がほしい is changed toを, as in 本を読みたがる and 車をほしがる. In addition to the examples above, はずかしがる, さびしがる, なつかしがる, けむたがる, つよがる, いたがる and とくいがる are often used.

Variations such as たがり or あつがり, さむがり, さびしがり, はずかしがり and こわがり are nouns that refer to people who think, feel, or act in such-and-such a way.

<< 【かろう】 | Home | 【かわきりに】 >>

【かろうじて】

A formal, expression with the feel of written language. In everyday spoken language, どうにか and なんとか are often used. やっと and ようやく are similar expressions.

1. かろうじてV-た

（1）試験 の開始 時間 に、かろうじて間 に合 った。／I barely arrived in time for the start of the exam.

（2）試験 のできは良 くなかったが、かろうじて合格 できた。／I did badly on the exam but somehow managed to pass it.

（3）雨 でタイヤがスリップした。危 ないところだったが、かろうじて事故 はまぬがれた。／My car skidded because of rain. It was really dangerous, and I just avoided having an accident.

（4）国連 の介入 で、かろうじて武力 衝突 は避 けられた。／Because of the intervention of the United Nations, the use of arms was narrowly averted.

（5）ひどい怪我 だったが、かろうじて死 なずにすんだ。／It was a terrible injury, and I narrowly escaped death.

Means “barely” or “narrowly managing to do something.” Used when a good result is achieved or the worst situation is avoided. Used in the forms かろうじて...をまぬがれた, かろうじて...せずにすんだ, and かろうじて...は避けられた.

やっと has the implication that a long time or great trouble is needed to achieve a result. On the other hand, with かろうじて a process is not always necessary, and the result is the important point. It is more formal than やっと and used in written language.

2. かろうじてV-ている

（1）毎日 の生活 は苦 しいが、かろうじて借金 はせずに済 んでいる。／Everyday life is hard, and I just manage to get by without borrowing money.

（2）病人 は機械 の力 を借 りて、かろうじて生 きている。／The patient is on life support, barely alive.

（3）現代人 は、毎日 のストレスに耐 えて、かろうじてバランスを保 っているに過 ぎない。／People today are only just managing to endure the stress of everyday life and make ends meet.

（4）彼女 も、かろうじて涙 をこらえているようだった。／She also seemed to be fighting back tears.

Expresses “barely managing” or “accomplishing something with difficulty.” Used when conditions are bad, but the worst outcome is avoided and the present condition can be maintained with difficulty, as in (1)-(3). Also used when the present condition is maintained by great effort or trouble, as in (4). The meaning of (4) is that she is almost crying but refrains from it with effort.

3. かろうじてV-るN

（1）この道 は、車 二台 がかろうじてすれ違 える広 さしかない。／This road is just wide enough to let two cars pass each other.

（2）列車 の寝台 というのは、人 ひとりが、かろうじて横 になれる大 きさだ。／The berth in the train is barely big enough for a person to lie down.

（3）その家 は、僕 にもかろうじて買 えそうな値段 だ。／The price of that house is at the limit of what I can afford.

（4）私 の英語 は、かろうじて日常 会話 ができる程度 だ。／My English ability is barely enough for daily conversation.

With expressions of potentiality, as in (1) to (4), かろうじて means “someone somehow manages to achieve something.” Used when something is difficult to do, but someone just barely can do it, with no margin to spare.

<< 【くさい】 | Home | 【ください】 >>

【くせ】

［Nのくせに］

［Na なくせに］

［A／V　くせに］

1. ...くせに

（1）彼 は、自分 ではできないくせに、いつも人 のやり方 にもんくを言 う。／Though he can’t do it himself, he is always complaining about other people’s methods.

（2）もんく言 うんじゃないの。自分 はできないくせに。／Don’t complain. You can’t even do it yourself!

（3）あの選手 は、体 が大 きいくせに、まったく力 がない。／In spite of his size, that player has no strength at all.

（4）こどものくせにおとなびたものの言 い方 をする子 だな。／For just being a child, she sure talks like some adult!

（5）好 きなくせに、嫌 いだと言 いはっている。／She says she doesn’t like it, even though she really does.

Used in the form XくせにY, where the situation Y, which is contrary to what would be expected from the content of X, continues. Y is often an expression of a negative evaluation. The form Y。Xくせに is also used, as in (2). When the subjects of the two clauses are different, as in the next example, くせに cannot be used.

（×）犬は散歩に行きたがっているくせに、彼はつれて行ってやらなかった。／Despite his dog wanted to go for a walk, he didn’t take it.

（○）犬は散歩に行きたがっているのに、彼はつれて行ってやらなかった。／Though his dog wanted to go for a walk, he didn’t take it.

2. ...くせして

（1）彼 は、自分 ではできないくせして、いつも人 のやり方 についてああだこうだと言 う。／Although he can’t do it himself, he is always telling other people how to do it.

（2）人 のやり方 にけちつけるんじゃないの。自分 ではできないくせして。／Quit criticizing other people. I know you can’t even do it yourself!

（3）この人 、大 きなからだのくせして、ほんとに力 がないんだから。／Even though he’s big, he’s got almost no strength.

（4）こどものくせしておとなびたものの言 い方 をする子 だな。／For being just a child, she sure talks like some adult!

（5）好 きなくせして、嫌 いだと言 いはっている。／He insists he doesn’t like it, even though he really does.

Similar in meaning to くせに, but くせして often gives a more familiar impression.

3. そのくせ

（1）彼女 はもんくばかり言 う。そのくせ自分 ではなにもしない。／She’s always complaining. But she does nothing herself.

（2）彼女 は自分 ではなにもしない。そのくせ、もんくだけは言 う。／She does nothing herself. But she always complains.

（3）彼女 はよく山田 君 はバカだと言 ってるでしょ。そのくせ、私 がそうだ、そうだというと、こんどはおこるのよ。／You know she always says Yamada-kun is a fool. But then, when I say she’s right, she gets angry.

（4）日本人 は他人 には非常 に冷淡 な時 がある、そのくせ身内 に対 しては異常 なくらい仲間 意識 を持 つという側面 がある、とその研究者 は言 っている。／That researcher says that, while Japanese people can be extremely standoffish to strangers, they have a remarkably strong sense of bonds with their relatives.

Connects two separate sentences. Expresses the same meaning as くせに, but そのくせ can’t be used with prohibitive or imperative expressions, such as もんく言うんじゃないの in example (2) of ...くせに.

（×）自分では何もしないじゃない。そのくせもんく言うんじゃないの。／You do nothing. Don’t complain.

<< 【げ】 | Home | 【けっきょく】 >>

【けっか】

［N のけっか］

［V-たけっか］

（1）投票 の結果 、議長 には山田 さんが選出 された。／The result of the vote was that Yamada-san was selected as the chairperson.

（2）調 べた結果 、私 がまちがっていることがわかりました。／My investigations showed that I was in the wrong.

（3）3人 でよく話 し合 った結果 、その問題 についてはもうすこし様子 を見 ようということになった。／After discussing it amongst the three of us, the decision was to let the issue lie for a bit longer and see what happens.

（4）国会 審議 の空転 の結果 、この法案 がこの会期中 に採決 される見通 しはなくなった。／As a result of the stalled Diet deliberations, there is no longer any prospect of this bill being adopted during the current session.

Although 結果 (result) is basically a noun, as in 調べた結果を教えてください(Please tell me the results of your investigation), it can be used as an expression to link cause and effect, as shown in the examples above. Combined with an expression that describes the cause, it means “for that reason” or “because of such-and-such.” Followed by a description of the resulting effect. Used more in written language.

<< 【けっか】 | Home | 【けっして...ない】 >>

【けっきょく】

（1）バーゲンセールに行 ったが、結局 何 も買 わないで帰 ってきた。／I went to a bargain sale, but I ended up coming home without buying anything.

（2）結局 、世 の中 は万事 金 で決 まるということだよ。／In the end, money decides everything in this world.

（3）挑戦者 も善戦 したが、結局 は判定 でチャンピオンが勝利 をおさめた。／The challenger also fought well, but in the end the champion won the decision on points.

（4）結局 のところ、あなたは何 が言 いたいのですか。／So at the end of the day, what do you want to say?

Used at the beginning or in the middle of a sentence when stating the final conclusion or result of something. As in (3) and (4), it is sometimes used in the forms 結局は or 結局のところ. Often used to state a conclusion or result settled beyond the power of a person’s will, in spite of his/her efforts or expectations, and carries the slightly negative connotation of “that’s just the way things are (were).” Consequently, it is unnatural and difficult to use this expression when stating a positive result.

（×）猛勉強を続け、結局、彼は一流大学に合格した。／He kept studying very hard, and he ended up passing the entrance exam for a first-class university.

（○）猛勉強を続けたが、結局、彼は希望した大学に合格できなかった。／He kept studying very hard, but he ended up not passing the entrance exam for the university of his choice.

In (4), 結局 is followed by an interrogative sentence and its function is to press the listener to draw a conclusion.

<< 【けど】 | Home | 【けれども】 >>

【けれど】

1. けれど

（1）2時間 待 った。けれど、彼 は姿 を現 さなかった。／I waited for two hours. However, he did not show up.

（2）パーティーではだれも知 っている人 がいなかった。けれど、みんな親切 でとても楽 しかった。／There was no one I knew at the party. However, everybody was nice and I had a really good time.

（3）この作品 で3等賞 ぐらいとれるかなと期待 していた。けれど、結果 は思 いがけなく1等賞 だった。／I was hoping I might win third prize with this piece. But, to my surprise, the result was first prize.

Placed at the beginning of a sentence, けれど indicates that what comes next will develop in a way that differs from what might be expected from the preceding sentence(s). Compared with しかし, けれど is used more often in spoken language. However, it can be used in informal writing too.

2. ...けれど

（1）2時間 待 ったけれど、彼 は姿 を現 さなかった。／I waited for two hours, but he did not show up.

（2）あの人 はきれいだけれど、意地悪 だ。／That woman is beautiful but ill-natured.

（3）下手 だけれど、ピアノを弾 くのは楽 しい。／I’m not good at it, but playing the piano is fun.

（4）野球 もおもしろいけれどサッカーはもっとおもしろいと思 う若 い人 が増 えている。／More and more young people are starting to think that, although baseball is fun, soccer is even more fun.

（5）係長 はもうすぐ帰 ると思 いますけれど、ここでお待 ちになりますか。／I’m sure the subsection chief will be back soon...would you like to wait here?

Attaches to the end of a clause and signals that what comes next will develop in a way that is different from what might be anticipated from the statement in the preceding clause. It is an adversative expression, but not necessarily limited to adversative use. It can also be used to make a preliminary remark, as in (5). Tends to be used in spoken language, but may also be used in informal writing.

3. ...けれど

（1）いま母 は留守 なんですけれど。／My mother isn’t home right now....

（2）来週 は外国 出張 で、いないんですけれど。／I’m afraid I have an overseas business trip next week, so I won’t be here....

（3）紅茶 は切 らしています。コーヒーならありますけれど。／We’ve run out of tea. We do have coffee, though....

（4）ちょっとコピー機 が動 かないんですけれど。／Excuse me, but the copy machine isn’t working....

（5）書類 が一枚 足 りないんですけれど。／A page of the document seems to be missing....

（6）かあさん、友達 が夏休 みにうちへ泊 まりに来 たいって言 ってるんだけれど。／Mom, a friend of mine says she wants to come and stay at our house during the summer break....

Placed at the end of a sentence, ...けれど creates the impression that the sentence is unfinished. Used to state an excuse, an explanation of circumstances, etc. in a soft and gentle manner. Also used to make indirect requests, as in (4), (5), and (6). Can be attached to both polite and plain forms. When attached to polite forms, it makes the expression more feminine and polite. Spoken language.

<< 【ことができる】 | Home | 【ごとし】 >>

【ことこのうえない】

［Na なことこのうえない］

［A-いことこのうえない］

（1）丁重 なことこの上 ないごあいさつをいただき、恐縮 しております。／We are truly overwhelmed at the warmth of the greeting you have given us.

（2）その風景 は、さびしいことこのうえ（も）ないものであった。／The landscape was lonely beyond description.

（3）有権者 の存在 を無視 したような、その政治家 たちの舞台裏 での争 いは、見 ぐるしいことこの上 ないものであった。／The infighting among those politicians behind the scenes—as if they were totally indifferent to the voting public—was disgraceful beyond description.

Means “there is nothing more than such-and-such.” A formal expression used in written language. The examples above can be paraphrased, respectively, as このうえなく丁重なあいさつ (the most cordial of greetings), このうえなくさびしい (the loneliest possible), and このうえなく見ぐるしいもの (unspeakably disgraceful).

<< 【ことこのうえない】 | Home | 【ことだ】 >>

【ごとし】

A literary expression that is now used only in written language. ごとしis the form that is used at the end of a sentence, and the conjugated forms are ごときN and ごとくV.

1. ごとし

［Nのごとし］

［Nであるがごとし］

（1）光陰 矢 のごとし。／Time flies like an arrow.

（2）時間 というものは、矢 のごとくはやくすぎさっていくものだ。／Time passes by quickly, just as an arrow flies.

（3）山田 ごときに負 けるものか。／I’ll never lose to someone like Yamada.

Used to compare one thing to another, like ...のようだ. The form Nごとき is usually followed by a noun to create the pattern NごときN, but sometimes Nごとき is used by itself as a noun, as in (3). This usage is limited to cases in which the meaning is accompanied by a negative evaluation. With the exception of proverbs and idioms, ようだ is now used more often than ごとし.

2. ...かのごとし

（1）彼女 はそのことを知 っているはずなのに、まったく聞 いたことがないかのごとき態度 だった。／Though she should have known about it, she acted as if she had heard nothing at all.

（2）そのふたりはまずしかったが、世界中 が自分 たちのものであるかのごとくしあわせであった。／Although the two of them were poor, they were as happy as if everything in the world belonged to them.

（3）「盗作 する」とは、他人 の作品 を自分 の作品 であるかのごとく発表 することである。／Toosaku-suru (plagiarize) means to publish or present someone else’s work as if it were your own.

（4）あの政治家 は、いつも優柔不断 であるかのごとくふるまってはいるが、実 はそうかんたんには真意 を見 せないタヌキである。／That politician always acts as if he can’t make a decision, but he is really a sly fox who doesn't readily reveal his true intentions.

This is used after a sentence, but in the case of nouns and na-adjectives, as in (3) and (4), it follows である and not だ. Means that something is not actually so, but looks as if it is. Now かのようだ is used more often. In particular, the dictionary form かのごとし is almost never used nowadays.

<< 【ことだ】 | Home | 【ことだし】 >>

【ことだから】

［Nのことだから］

（1）彼 のことだからどうせ時間 どおりにはこないだろう。／Given the way he is, he probably won’t come on time anyway.

（2）あの人 のことだから、わすれずに持 ってきてくれると思 うけどな。／I would say that, because he’s got it, he’ll probably remember to bring it.

（3）慎重 な山田 さんのことだから、そのへんのところまでちゃんと考 えてあるとは思 うけどね。／Since Yamada-san is so cautious, I would guess that she already has everything all thought out.

（4）あの人 のことだから、この計画 が失敗 しても自分 だけは責任 をのがれられるような手 はうってあるんだろう。／You know how he is—I would guess that he’s already taken measures to ensure he can escape having to take any responsibility in case the plan fails.

Usually attached to a noun that denotes a person. Used when making some sort of judgment about a person that both the speaker and the listener know very well, based on that person’s character or behavioral patterns. In some cases, the characteristic or special feature that forms the basis for the judgment about the person in question is specified in the context, such as 慎重な (cautious) in (3).

<< 【ことだから】 | Home | 【ことだろう】 >>

【ことだし】

［N／Na　であることだし］

［Na なことだし］

［A／V　ことだし］

（1）雨 がふってきそうだから、きょうは散歩 はやめておこうか。こどもたちもかぜをひいていることだし。／Since it looks like it’s going to rain, why don’t we put off going for a walk today? Besides, the children have colds.

（2）おいしそうな料理 もでてきたことですし、私 のへたなごあいさつはこのへんで終 わりにしたいと存 じます。／With all this delicious food ready to eat, I will put an end here to my clumsy remarks.

（3）委員 も大体 そろったことだし、予定 時間 も過 ぎているので、そろそろ委員会 を始 めてはいかがですか。／Since most of the committee members are present, and we are already a little behind schedule, how would it be if we started the meeting?

Attaches to a clause. This construction combines ことだ+し and is used when describing the conditions or circumstances that form the reason or basis for some kind of judgment, decision, or hope. ことですし, as in (2), is a more polite form. Sometimes two reasons are stated, as in (3), sometimes one reason is stated, as in (2), and sometimes the reason is tacked on at the end as additional information, as in (1). Although this is a spoken language expression, it is more formal than using only し.

<< 【ことだし】 | Home | 【ことで】 >>

【ことだろう】

［Na　な／である　ことだろう］

［A／V　ことだろう］

（1）会 っていないが、山田 さんのこどもさんもさぞおおきくなったことだろう。／I haven’t seen them, but I suppose that Yamada-san’s children must have really grown up.

（2）市内 でこんなにふっているのだから、山 のほうではきっとひどい雪 になっていることだろう。／Since it’s falling this hard in the city, there must be a terrible snowstorm in the mountains.

（3）《手紙 》息子 さん、大学 合格 とのこと。さぞかしお喜 びのことでございましょう。／《letter》We heard that your son passed his university entrance examination. You must be so very pleased.

（4）この誘拐 事件 は人質 の安全 を考慮 して今 はふせられているが、公表 されれば、まちがいなく社会 に大 きな衝撃 をあたえることだろう。／This kidnapping case is presently being kept quiet out of consideration for the safety of the hostage, but once it’s made public, there’s no question it will cause a great shock to our society.

Attaches to a clause and indicates a conjecture. It is also possible just to say だろう; however, ことだろう is a more formal expression that is suited to written language and used to make empathetic conjectures about things that are not known in the here and now. When used with the adverb さぞ（かし） (how, surely), as in (1), this expression conveys an even stronger emotional involvement.

<< 【ごとに】 | Home | 【ことにする】 >>

【ことにしている】

［Vことにしている］

（1）私 は毎日 かならず日記 をつけることにしている。／I make it a rule to write in my diary every day without fail.

（2）夜 はコーヒーを飲 まないことにしているんです。／I don’t drink coffee at night.

（3）彼 の家族 は、家事 はすべて分担 してやることにしているそうだ。／I hear that his family makes it a policy to divide up all the household tasks among themselves.

（4）運動 不足 解消 のため、私 はこどもと公園 に行 くとかならず鉄棒 をやることにしている。／To deal with my lack of exercise, I make it a rule to exercise on the horizontal bar every time I go to the park with my children.

（5）ずいぶん前 から、不正 をおこなった場合 は失格 ということにしています。／For a long time now, any case of misconduct has led to disqualification.

Indicates that something has been made into a habit or rule, based on a certain decision. Can be considered to mean that the result of the decision or resolution made in the act of ことにする is now a regular habit. Therefore, the form ことにしている is not used to refer to customs or manners in general.

（×）日本人は、はしを使ってご飯を食べることにしています。／Japanese people have decided to use chopsticks to eat rice.

（○）日本人は、はしを使ってご飯を食べます。／Japanese people use chopsticks to eat rice.

<< 【ことにしている】 | Home | 【ことになっている】 >>

【ことにする】

1. ...ことにする〈decision〉

［Vことにする］

（1）あしたからジョギングすることにしよう。／Starting tomorrow, I am going to jog.

（2）これからはあまりあまい物 は食 べないことにしよう。／From now on, I'm not going to eat so many sweets.

（3）きょうはどこへも行 かないで勉強 することにしたよ。／I decided not to go anywhere and just study today.

Indicates a decision or resolution to perform an action in the future. When the form ことにした is used, as in (3), it conveys the meaning that a decision or resolution has already been made. こととする has the same meaning as ことにする, but こととする is more formal and tends to be used in written language.

2. ...ことにする〈treatment〉

［N（だ）ということにする］

［Na　だということにする］

［V-た（という）ことにする］

（1）その話 は聞 かなかった（という）ことにしましょう。／Let’s just say that we never heard that story.

（2）その件 は検討中 （だ）ということにして、すこしなりゆきを見 まもろう。／Let’s put that matter under consideration and see how things go for a while.

（3）敵 の攻撃 に対 する防御 の時間 をかせぐために、大統領 はすこぶる健康 だということにしておくべきだ。／We’d better pretend that the president is in excellent health, in order to gain time to prepare a defense against attacks from the enemy.

（4）出張 に行 った（という）ことにして出張費 を着服 したり不正 流用 することを、俗 に「カラ出張 」と言 う。／Pretending to have been on a business trip and pocketing or misappropriating the travel expenses is commonly known as a kara-shutchoo (phoney business trip).

Attached to a clause describing an action or state, this expression is used to pretend something is true when it isn’t, or to signal that someone will handle a situation in a certain way. When used with a noun, it takes the form N(だ)ということにする, as in (2). With verbs, it follows the ta-form, as in (1) and (4). In that case, use of という is optional. ...こととする, which has the same meaning, is more formal and used in written language. See Usage 1 of ことになる for a comparison with that expression.

<< 【ことになっている】 | Home | 【ことには】 >>

【ことになる】

1. ...ことになる〈decision〉

［Nということになる］

［V-る　（という）ことになる］

［V-ない　（という）ことになる］

（1）こんど大阪 支社 に行 くことになりました。／It’s been decided that I am to go to the Osaka branch office.

（2）ふたりでよく話 し合 った結果 、やはり離婚 するのが一番 いいということになりました。／After a long discussion between the two of us, we came to the conclusion that, as we had suspected, divorce was the best solution.

（3）よく話 し合 った結果 、やはり離婚 ということになりました。／After a long discussion, the decision, as expected, was to divorce.

（4）亡 くなった山田 さんは形式 ばったことがきらいな人 だったから、葬式 などはしないことになりそうだな。／As the late Yamada-san was a person who disliked ceremony, it looks like that there won’t be a funeral or anything.

（5）この問題 は、細部 については両政府 の次官級 協議 にゆだねられることになった。／Regarding this issue, it was decided that the details were to be left to vice-minister level consultations between the two governments.

Means that some kind of decision or agreement was made concerning a future action, and a certain result will follow. In contrast to ...ことにする, which specifies who made the decision or resolution, ことになるconveys the meaning that the conclusion or result in question will be obtained naturally, unintentionally, and of its own accord. Often used in the ta-form ことになった, as in (1), (2), and (4). こととなる, which has the same meaning, is a more formal expression used in written language.

2. ...ことになる〈restatement〉

［Nということになる］

［V-る　（という）ことになる］

［V-ない　（という）ことになる］

（1）4年 も留学 するの？　じゃあ、あの会社 には就職 しないことになるの？／You’re going to study abroad for four years? So, you’re not going to get a job at that company after all?

（2）りえさんはわたしの母 の妹 のこどもだから、わたしとりえさんはいとこどうしということになる。／Rie-san is the child of my mother’s sister, so that makes Rie-san and me cousins.

（3）これまで 10 年 前 と4年前 に開 いているので、これで日本 での開催 は3回目 ということになる。／It was held here ten years ago and four years ago, so that makes this the third time for it to be held in Japan.

Used to paraphrase, to look at something from a different perspective, or to point out the true nature of something.

<< 【ことになる】 | Home | 【ことは...が】 >>

【ことには】

1. V-ることには

（1）その子供 たちの言 うことには、彼 らの両親 はもう二日 も帰 ってきていないらしい。／From what the children say, it appears that their parents have not been home for two days already.

（2）学生 たちの言 うことには、ことしは就職 が予想 以上 にきびしいらしい。／From what the students say, it sounds like job-hunting this year is much harder than they had imagined.

（3）先生 のおっしゃることには、最近 の学生 は言 われたことしかしないそうだ。／According to the professor, students these days do only what they’re told to do.

（4）たぬきさんの言 うことにゃ、きつねさんがかぜをひいたそうじゃ。／What Mr. Raccoon says is that Mr. Fox has caught a cold.

Often attached to 言う (say) or to the dictionary form of a similar verb. Specifies the person who made the utterance that is quoted or reported. In (1), it means “those children are saying that their parents haven’t been home for a full two days.” A slightly old-fashioned expression that has the tone of written language; in particular, the form ことにゃ (as shown in (4)) is often used in folktales and the like.

2. V-ないことには

（1）先生 が来 ないことにはクラスははじまらない。／The class cannot start if the teacher doesn’t come.

（2）いい辞書 を手 にいれないことには外国語 の勉強 はうまくいかない。／Studying a foreign language will not go well if you don’t get a good dictionary.

（3）あなたがこころよく見 おくってくれないことには、私 としても気持 ちよく出発 できないよ。／I won’t be able to feel good about leaving if you don’t come willingly to see me off.

（4）とにかくこの予算案 が国会 で承認 されないことには、景気回復 のための次 のてだてを講 ずることは不可能 だ。／Anyway, if this budget proposal is not approved by the Diet, it will be impossible to take the next measures to restore the economy.

Used in the pattern XないことにはYない and means that Y cannot be realized without realizing X. X is a necessary condition for the realization of Y. Can be paraphrased with なければ or なくては.

<< 【ことには】 | Home | 【ことはない】 >>

【ことは...が】

［Na なことはNa だが］

［AことはAが］

［VことはVが］

（1）読 んだことは読 んだが、ぜんぜん分 からなかった。／Though I did read it, I didn’t understand it at all.

（2）あの映画 、おもしろいことはおもしろいけど、もう一度 金 をはらって見 たいとは思 わないね。／I do agree that that movie is interesting, but I wouldn’t pay money to see it again.

（3）おいしかったことはおいしかったけどね、でも高 すぎるよ。／Yes, it was delicious, but it’s too expensive!

（4）どうしてもやれと言 うなら、いちおうやってみることは（やって）みるけど、うまく行 かないと思 うよ。／If you insist, I will at least give it a try, but I don’t think it will work.

（5）A:ひさしぶり。元気 だった？／Long time no see. How have you been?

B:元気 なことは元気 なんだけどねえ。なにかもうひとつ満 たされない気分 なんだなあ。／I am doing well, but even so.... I feel like something’s missing.

The same word is repeated. This pattern expresses concession. It is used when the speaker acknowledges something to a certain extent, but not vigorously or completely.

When a verb is used, as in (1) and (4), it means that the speaker will perform (or has performed) the action but thinks that the result will not be (or was not) satisfactory. Often used with てみる. When a noun or an adjective is used with this pattern, as in (2), (3), and (5), it means “although I do not deny such-and-such....” For example, (2) can be paraphrased as おもしろくない(という)わけではないが (it’s not that it isn’t interesting).

When this pattern is used to refer to past events, sometimes both words are changed to the ta-form, as in (1), and sometimes only the second word is changed, as in the example below.

（例）読むことは読んだが、ぜんぜん分からなかった。／I did read it, but I didn’t understand it at all.

<< 【さしつかえない】 | Home | 【させる】 >>

【さすが】

1. さすが

（1）これ、山田 さんがつくったの？　うまいねえ。さすが（は）プロだねえ。／Did Yamada-san make this? Marvelous! Just what you’d expect from a pro.

（2）さすが（は）山田 さんだねえ。うまいねえ。／That’s just what I’d expect from Yamada-san. Marvelous!

（3）これ山田 さんがつくったの？　さすがだねえ。／Did Yamada-san make this? Only she could do it!

（4）さすが（は）世界 チャンピオン、その新人 の対戦 相手 を問題 にせずしりぞけた。／Being the world champion that he is, he defeated the rookie opponent without any difficulty.

Often appears at the beginning of a sentence. Can take the form さすが(は)Nだ, as in (1), (2), and (4), or さすがだ, as in (3). Used when a result is obtained that is consistent with the speaker’s knowledge or conventional wisdom. Similar to やはり, but さすが is only used to convey positive evaluation.

2. さすがに

（1）沖縄 でもさすがに冬 の夜 はさむいね。／It is cold at night in winter, even in Okinawa.

（2）いつもはおちついている山田 さんだが、はじめてテレビに出 たときはさすがに緊張 したそうだ。／I heard that even Yamada-san, who is usually imperturbable, got very nervous the first time he appeared on television.

（3）世界 チャンピオンもさすがにかぜには勝 てず、いいところなくやぶれた。／Even the world champion could not defeat the common cold, and she lost without doing anything remarkable.

（4）最近 調子 を落 としている山田 選手 だが、このレベルの相手 だとさすがにあぶなげなく勝 った。／Even though Yamada-senshu (the athlete) has not been in the best condition lately, she won easily against this level of opponent.

（5）ふだんはそうぞうしいこどもたちも今夜 ばかりはさすがにお通夜 のふんいきにのまれているようだ。／The children, who are usually very boisterous, seem to be overwhelmed tonight by the atmosphere of the wake.

Used when someone (or something) that is usually evaluated in a certain way is put into an extraordinary situation and shows a result or behavior that diverges from that evaluation. For instance, in (1), it means that Okinawa, which in Japan is evaluated as being warm, is actually not so in the situation of winter nights. Used for both positive and negative evaluation.

3. さすが（に）...だけあって

［Nだけあって］

［Na なだけあって］

［A-いだけあって］

［Vだけあって］

（1）さすがプロだけあって、アマチュア選手 を問題 にせず勝 った。／Being the pro that he is, he beat the amateur player without any problem.

（2）さすがに熱心 なだけあって、山田 さんのテニスはたいしたもんだ。／Just as you might expect from her enthusiasm, Yamada-san’s tennis is extraordinary.

（3）さすがからだが大 きいだけあって、山田 さんは力 があるねえ。／As might be expected of a big person like him, Yamada-san has a lot of power, doesn’t he.

（4）山田 さんは、さすがによく勉強 しているだけあって、この前 のテストでもいい成績 だった。／Yamada-san got a good mark on the last test too, as might be expected from the fact that she studies so hard.

（5）彼女 は、さすがに 10 年 も組合 活動 をしているだけあって、なにごとも民主的 に考 えることのできる人 だ。／As you might anticipate from her being an active union member for ten years, she is a person who can think democratically about everything.

Used to say that an outcome is as expected, based on conventional wisdom or the speaker’s knowledge of a person or thing. Although it is similar to やはり in meaning, さすがに...だけあって is used only for positive evaluation.

4. さすがに...だけのことはある

［Nだけのことはある］

［Na なだけのことはある］

［A-いだけのことはある］

［Vだけのことはある］

（1）アマチュア選手 が相手 なら問題 にしないね。さすがにプロだけのことはあるよ。／If the challengers are amateur players, he won’t care about it. They don’t call him a pro for nothing!

（2）山田 さんのテニスはたいしたもんだ。さすがに熱心 なだけのことはあるよ。／Yamada-san’s tennis deserves admiration. It’s just as we might expect from her dedication.

（3）山田 さんはちからがあるねえ。さすがにからだがおおきいだけのことはある。／How powerful Yamada-san is! It’s just as might be expected from his large build.

（4）山田 さんはこの前 のテストでもいい成績 だった。さすがによく勉強 しているだけのことはあるね。／Yamada-san got a good grade on the last test too. It’s just as you might expect from her studying so hard.

（5）彼女 はなにごとも民主的 に考 えることのできる人 だ。さすがに20 年 も組合 のリーダーをやっているだけのことはある。／She is a person who can think democratically about everything. It’s just what you’d expect of someone who has been a union leader for more than twenty years.

Used to look at a certain result or situation and then find the cause or reason for it, using the speaker’s knowledge or conventional wisdom. Similar to やはり, but さすがに...だけのことはある is used only for positive evaluation. Can be combined with さすがに...だけあって to create the form さすがに...だけのことはあって.

5. さすがのNも

（1）さすがの世界 チャンピオンもケガには勝 てなかった。／World champion though she is, she couldn’t beat an injury.

（2）さすがの山田 さんも、はじめてテレビに出 たときは緊張 したそうだ。／I heard that even Yamada-san (who is always very calm) got nervous when he appeared on television for the first time.

（3）さすがの機動隊 も、ひとびとのからだをはった抵抗 にたいしては、それ以上 まえにすすむことができなかった。／Even the riot police (who are used to dealing with situations like this) couldn’t advance any further against the resistance of people who were laying their lives on the line.

（4）私 は小 さいころよくいじめられるこどもだった。しかし、さすがのよわむしもおとうとやいもうとがいじめられているときだけは相手 にとびかかっていったそうだ。／When I was a child, I was frequently bullied. However, people say that, wimp though I was, I would throw myself fiercely at the antagonist whenever my younger brother or sister was being bullied.

Used when someone or something that is usually evaluated in a certain way is put into a particular situation and then shows a result or behavior that diverges from that evaluation. Has basically the same function as さすがに, which is used like an adverb.

<< 【さすが】 | Home | 【さぞ...ことだろう】 >>

【させる】

Expresses causation. When the verb in V-させる is a Group 1 verb, the vowel in the final syllable of the dictionary form changes from -u to -a and then せる is attached, as in 行く→行かせる and 飲む→飲ませる. For Group 2 verbs such as 食べる, させる is attached to the stem 食べ and the conjugation pattern is 食べる→食べさせる. The causative form of する is させる, and 来る becomes こさせる. In spoken language, the forms 行かす, 飲ます, 食べさす, and so on may also be used.

A causative sentence essentially conveys the meaning that one person orders or directs another person to do something. However, in actual usage the causative form expresses a broader range of meaning, including coercion, instruction, non-interference, permission, and so on.

（例1）〈強制〉犯人は銀行員に現金を用意させた。／〈coercion〉The criminal made the bank clerk prepare the cash.

（例2）〈指示〉社長は秘書にタイプを打たせた。 ／〈instruction〉The company president had the secretary do the typing.

（例3）〈放任〉疲れているようだったので、そのまま眠らせておいた。 ／〈non-interference〉Since she seemed to be tired, I let her sleep.

（例4）〈許可〉社長は給料を前借りさせてくれた。 ／〈permission〉The president let me have an advance on my salary.

（例5）〈放置〉風呂の水をあふれさせるな。／〈neglect〉Don’t let the bathwater overflow.

（例6）〈介護〉子供にミルクを飲ませる時間です。 ／〈care〉It’s time to give the child some milk.

（例7）〈自責〉子どもを事故で死なせてしまった。 ／〈self-reproach〉It’s my fault that my child died in the accident.

（例8）〈原因〉フロンガスが地球を温暖化させている。 ／〈cause〉Chlorofluorocarbon is causing global warming.

1. V-させる

a. NがNにNを V-させる

（1）教師 が学生 に本 を読 ませた。／The teacher made the students read the book.

（2）犯人 は銀行員 に現金 を用意 させた。／The criminal made the bank clerk prepare the cash.

（3）A:機械 がまた故障 なんですが...。／The machine is out of order again....

B:申 し訳 ありません。すぐに係 りの者 を伺 わせます。／We apologize for the inconvenience. We will send the person in charge over immediately.

（4）山田 はひどい奴 だ。旅行中 ずっと僕 に運転 させて、自分 は寝 てるんだよ。／Yamada is a horrible person. When we were traveling, he made me drive all the way while he just slept.

Expresses a variety of meanings, such as coercion, instruction, and non-interference. The causative sentence NがNにNをV-させる is derived from a sentence with a transitive verb NがNを(transitive) V. The subject Nが of the transitive sentence becomes Nに.

b. NがN　を／に　V-させる

（1）子 どもを買 い物 に行 かせた。／I had the children go shopping.

（2）社長 は、まず山田 をソファーにかけさせて、しばらく世間話 をしてから退職 の話 を切 りだした。／The company president first had Yamada sit on the sofa and then, after making small talk for a little while, he broached the subject of retirement.

（3）最近 は小学生 を塾 に通 わせる親 が多 い。／Many parents send their elementary school-aged children to juku (cram schools) these days.

（4）大 きな契約 だから、新入社員 に行 かせるのは心配 だ。／Since it’s a big contract, I’m worried about letting a new employee go on her own.

Expresses a variety of meanings, such as coercion, instruction, and non-interference. The causative sentence NがNを／にV-させる is derived from a sentence with an intransitive verb Nが(intransitive) V. The subject Nが of the intransitive sentence often becomes Nを, but may sometimes become Nに.

c. NがNをV-させる〈person〉

（1）彼 は、いつも冗談 を言 ってみんなを笑 わせる。／He is always telling jokes and making everyone laugh.

（2）就職 試験 を受 けなかったために、父 をすっかり怒 らせてしまった。／The fact that I didn’t take the employment test made my father very angry.

（3）私 は子供 の頃 は乱暴 で、近所 の子 をよく泣 かせていた。／When I was a child I was wild and unruly, and often made the children in my neighborhood cry.

（4）二年 も続 けて落第 して母 をがっかりさせた。／I disappointed my mother by flunking a grade two years in a row.

（5）厳 しくしつけすぎて、息子 をすっかりいじけさせてしまった。／I brought my son up so strictly that he became utterly intimidated.

（6）子 どもを交通 事故 で死 なせてからというもの、毎日 が失意 のどん底 であった。／From the time I lost my child in a traffic accident, I have been in the depths of despair every day.

Means “induce someone to do...” or “be the cause of someone doing....” In this pattern, the causative sentences use intransitive verbs that express an action that a person cannot control, such as 泣く (cry), 笑う (laugh), and 怒る (get angry). The subject Nが in Nが (intransitive) V becomes Nを in the causative sentence. Example (5) expresses a sense of self-reproach on the part of the speaker, because even though the incident in question was not intentional and s/he was not the direct cause, the child was under his/her care when the incident took place.

d. NがNを V-させる〈thing〉

（1）シャーベットは、果汁 を凍 らせて作 ります。／Sherbet is made by freezing fruit juice.

（2）打撲 の傷 みには、タオルを水 で湿 らせて冷 やすとよい。／To ease the ache of a bruise, it’s good to cool it with a wet towel.

（3）貿易 の不均衡 が日米 関係 を硬化 させている。／The trade imbalance is putting a strain on Japan-US relations.

（4）金融 不安 が、日本 の経済 状態 を悪化 させる原因 となっている。／Financial instability is causing the economic situation in Japan to deteriorate.

（5）子供達 は目 を輝 かせて話 に聞 き入 っている。／The children are listening intently to the story, their eyes sparkling.

（6）猫 は目 を光 らせて暗闇 に潜 んでいる。／The cat is lurking in the darkness, its eyes sharp.

Means “induce something to do...” or “be the cause of something doing....” In this usage, the causative form of an intransitive verb without a corresponding transitive verb, such as 凍る (freeze) or 湿る (become moist/wet), is used the same way as a transitive verb. 目を輝かせる and 目を光らせる in (5) and (6) are idiomatic expressions.

2. V-させてあげる〈permission〉

（1）そんなにこの仕事 がやりたいのなら、やらせてあげましょう。／If you want to do this job so much, I will let you do it.

（2）従業員 たちもずいぶんよく働 いてくれた。2、3日 休 みをとらせてやってはどうだろう。／The employees have worked extremely hard. Why don’t we let them have a few days off?

（3）きのうの晩 、ずいぶん遅 くまで勉強 をしていたようだから、もう少 し休 ませてあげましょう。／She seems to have been up quite late studying last night, so let’s let her sleep a little while longer.

A causative expression combined with あげる, やる, etc. indicates permission or non-interference.

3. V-させておく〈non-interference〉

（1）甘 えて泣 いているだけだから、そのまま泣 かせておきなさい。／He’s just crying like a spoilt baby, so leave him be and let him cry.

（2）注意 したってどうせ人 の言 うことなんか聞 こうとしないんだ。勝手 に好 きなことをさせておけばいいさ。／It doesn’t matter what advice other people give her, she won’t listen anyway. Just let her do whatever she wants.

（3）夕方 になると急 に冷 え込 みますから、あんまり遅 くまで遊 ばせておいてはいけませんよ。／When evening comes it gets cold all of a sudden, so you shouldn’t let them play outside too late.

A causative expression combined with おく indicates non-interference.

4. V-させてください〈request for permission〉

（1）申 し訳 ありませんが、今日 は少 し早 く帰 らせてください。／I’m very sorry, but please let me go home a little early today.

（2）A:だれか、この仕事 を引 き受 けてくれませんか。／Is there anyone who will take this job on?

B:ぜひ、私 にやらせてください。／Please let me do it!

（3）A:私 が御馳走 しますよ。／This will be my treat.

B:いや、いつも御馳走 になってばかりですので、ここは、私 に払 わせてください。／Thank you, but since you always treat me, please let me pay here.

（4）少 し考 えさせていただけますか。／Could you give me some time to think it over?

（5）期日 については、こちらで決 めさせていただけるとありがたいのですが...。／We would appreciate it if you would let us decide on the deadline....

A causative expression combined with an expression of request, such as ください or いただけますか, indicates a request for permission. As in (3), this pattern is also used to make a polite offer.

5. V-させて　もらう／くれる〈favor〉

（1）両親 が早 く亡 くなったので、姉 が働 いて私 を大学 に行 かせてくれた。／Since both of my parents passed away when I was young, my older sister worked to put me through college.

（2）金婚式 のお祝 いに、子 ども達 にハワイに行 かせてもらった。／To celebrate our golden wedding anniversary, our children gave us a trip to Hawaii.

（3）《結婚式 のスピーチ》新婦 の友人 を代表 して、一言 ご挨拶 させていただきます。／《wedding speech》On behalf of the friends of the bride, I would like to say a few words.

（4）《パーティーで》では、僭越 ではございますが、乾杯 の音頭 をとらせていただきます。／《at a party》Now, if you will allow me, I would like to propose a toast.

A causative expression combined with もらう (receive) or くれる (give), etc. shows that the speaker views being allowed or left to do something as a kind of favor. (3) and (4) are idiomatic expressions used as introductory remarks in speeches, etc. They are humble expressions that imply the speaker’s gratitude or sense of honor at being asked to undertake a certain task.

6. V-させられる〈causative passive〉

［NがNにVさせられる］

（1）きのうは、お母 さんに3時間 も勉強 させられた。／Yesterday, I was forced by my mother to study for three whole hours.

（2）先輩 に無理 に酒 を飲 まされた。／I was forced to drink alcohol by a senior student.

（3）この歳 になって、海外 に転勤 させられるとは思 ってもみなかった。／At my age, I certainly didn’t expect to be transferred overseas.

（4）山下 さんは、毎日 遅 くまで残業 させられているらしい。／Apparently Yamashita-san is being forced to work overtime until late every day.

（5）きのうのサッカーの試合 は、逆転 につぐ逆転 で最後 までハラハラさせられた。／Yesterday’s soccer game kept me on pins and needles right up to the end, with one reversal after another.

A causative sentence with the form XがYにV-させる is rephrased from Y’s point of view to create the form YがXにV-させられる, which is a passive sentence. It means that Y is forced by X to do something against his/her will, and that Y thinks this action is bothersome or objectionable. With Group I verbs such as 行く and 読む, the causative passive form tends to become 行かされる and 読まされる (instead of 行かせられる and 読ませされる).

<< 【さっぱり】 | Home | 【さほど】 >>

【さて】

1. さて

（1）さて、そろそろいこうか。／All right, shall we get going?

（2）さて、つぎはどこへいこうかな。／So, I wonder where we should go next.

（3）A:あの人 、だれ？／That person (there), who is she?

B:さて、だれだろう。／Well, I’m not sure.

（4）さて、話 はかわりますが...。／Well, not to change the topic, but....

さて is a word that people use when they want to move on to the next topic or action. Used to invite someone to do something, as in (1), to let the listener know that you are thinking, as in (2) and (3), or to change the topic, as in (4). A slightly formal expression.

2. さてV-てみると

（1）漢字 がおもしろそうだったので日本語 を勉強 することにしたのだが、さてはじめてみると、これがけっこうむずかしい。／I decided to study Japanese because kanji looked interesting, but after I got started, I found out that it’s pretty difficult.

（2）頂上 までいけば水 ぐらいあるだろうと、むりをしてのぼっていった。ところが、さてついてみると何 もないのである。／I pushed myself to climb to the top of the mountain, thinking that at least there would be some water there. However, when I got to the top there was nothing.

（3）頂上 までいけば水 ぐらいあるだろうと、むりをしてのぼっていった。さてついてみると、あった、あった、そこには神社 もあり水 もあった。／I pushed myself to climb to the top of the mountain, thinking that at least there would be some water there. And when I got to the top, yes, yes, there was a shrine and also some water.

さてV-てみると is followed by an expression that indicates a result, and it means that an action based on some kind of expectation has led to a certain outcome. Tends to be used when the result is unexpected, as in (1) and (2), rather than when the result was expected, as in (3). A slightly formal expression.

<< 【さも】 | Home | 【さることながら】 >>

【さらに】

［さらにNa／A／V］

［さらに+数量詞］

（1）一日一回 では効 かないので、さらに薬 の量 を増 やした。／Since one dose per day had no effect, the amount of medicine was further increased.

（2）このままでも十分 おいしいのだが、クリームを入 れるとさらにおいしくなる。／It’s tasty enough as is, but adding cream will make it even more delicious.

（3）さらに多 くの方 に利用 していただけますように今月 は入会金 を半額 にいたしております。またご家族 でご入会 いただきますと、さらにお得 なファミリー割引 がございます。／With the hope that even more people will use (our facilities), we have reduced membership fees by half this month. Also, if you join as a family, there is the further advantage of a family discount.

（4）途中 の小屋 まで5時間 、それから頂上 まではさらに2時間 かかった。／It took five hours to get to the hut along the way, and after that an additional two hours to the top of the mountain.

（5）さらに二人 のメンバーが入 って、団員 は全部 で 18 人 になった。／With two more people joining, the total number of members reached eighteen.

（6）事故 の全貌 が明 らかになるにしたがって、更 に犠牲者 が増 える見込 みである。／As the full extent of the accident becomes clear, the number of victims is expected to increase further.

Used to say that the degree of something will increase further. Has the tone of a written language expression. Also used in polite spoken language. When used with a quantity or amount, it has the meaning of “in addition, on top of.” Can be replaced by もっと, but もっと is used more in spoken language. Cannot be replaced by もっと in cases like (4) or (5), when it is combined with expressions of quantity.

<< 【しかも】 | Home | 【したがって】 >>

【しだい】

1. Nしだいだ

（1）するかしないかは、あなたしだいだ。／Whether you do it or not is up to you.

（2）世 の中 は金 しだいでどうにでもなる。／Money makes the world go round.

（3）作物 の出来 具合 いはこの夏 の天気 次第 です。／The quality of the crops will depend on the weather this summer.

（4）結婚 した相手次第 で人生 が決 ってしまうこともある。／Your life can be determined by the person you marry.

Means “things vary according to N or are influenced by N.” Example (1) means “it is for you to decide.”

2. R-しだい

（1）落 し物 が見 つかりしだい、お知 らせします。／We will let you know as soon as the lost item is found.

（2）事件 のくわしい経過 がわかりしだい、番組 のなかでお伝 えします。／We will bring you further reports on this program, as the details of the incident become known.

（3）資料 が手 に入 り次第 、すぐに公表 するつもりだ。／As soon as we obtain the materials, we intend to make them public.

（4）天候 が回復 し次第 、出航 します。／We will set sail as soon as the weather clears.

Means “immediately after doing....” Expresses that as soon as one action or event is realized, the next action will be carried out. The first half of the sentence often describes an event that takes place as part of a natural progression. On the other hand, the second half of the sentence indicates an intentional action on the part of the speaker. It cannot refer to a spontaneously-occurring event or action.

（×）そのニュースが伝わり次第、暴動が起こるだろう。／As soon as the news spreads, a riot will probably happen.

In addition, R-しだい cannot be used to refer to past events.

（×）休みになりしだい、旅行に行った。／As soon as the vacation starts, they went on a trip.

Often used in TV news and the like, as in (2).

3. V-る／V-た　しだいだ

（1）とりあえずお知 らせした次第 です。／The facts of the matter are as I have just told you.

（2）《挨拶状 》今後 ともよろしくご指導 くださいますようお願 い申 し上 げる次第 でございます。／《letter of greeting》Therefore I humbly request your continued guidance in the future.

Used to describe the course of events that has led to the present state of affairs, the reason(s) behind it, etc. In idiomatic expressions, adjectives are sometimes used.

（例）こんなことになってしまい、まったくお恥ずかしい次第です。／I feel thoroughly embarrassed that it should have come to this.

4. こととしだいによって

（1）ことと次第 によって、計画 を大幅 に変更 しなければならなくなるかもれない。／It all depends, but we may have to make drastic changes to the plan.

（2）ことと次第 によっては、事件 の当事者 だけでなく責任者 も罰 することになる。／Depending on what happens, not only the person involved in the incident but also the one in charge may be penalized.

Used to preface a statement when the outcome of a course of events is uncertain or when something of importance is to be decided. An idiomatic expression.

<< 【しはする】 | Home | 【じゃあ】 >>

【しまつだ】

［V-るしまつだ］

（1）彼女 は夫 の欠点 を延々 と並 べ上 げ、あげくの果 てには離婚 すると言 って泣 き出 す始末 だった。／She went on and on listing her husband’s shortcomings, and in the end she finally said she was going to divorce him and burst into tears.

（2）息子 は大学 の勉強 は何 の役 にも立 たないと言 ってアルバイトに精 を出 し、この頃 は中退 して働 きたいなどと言 い出 す始末 だ。／Saying that college studies serve no purpose whatsoever, my son has put all his energy into his part-time job, and now he says he wants to drop out and get a job.

（3）一度 相談 にのってあげただけなのに、彼 はあなただけが頼 りだと言 って、真夜中 にでも電話 をかけてくる始末 だった。／I only listened to his troubles once, but now he ends up calling me in the middle of the night and telling me I’m the only one he can depend on.

Attached to the dictionary form of a verb, しまつだ expresses that a troublesome situation or annoyance has arisen due to another person’s actions. The first half of the sentence describes all the things that have led up to the situation, and the second half states the situation that has arisen as a result.

The expression この始末だ in the example below is idiomatic and implies criticism when indicating something that has occurred.

（例）山田はどうもこの頃学校に来ないと思ったらこの始末だ。バイクで人身事故を起こすような学生には、もう退学してもらうしかない。／I’ve been wondering why Yamada hasn’t come to school lately, and now this! A student like that who causes a fatal accident with his motorcycle—the only thing we can do is have him quit school.

<< 【しょうがない】 | Home | 【すえに】 >>

【ず】

Comes from the auxiliary verb ず, which is used in literary language. Expresses negation. Can be used only in written language and idiomatic expressions. In spoken language, なくて and ないで are used. Created by changing the ない in V-ない to ず. する becomes せず.

1. V-ず

（1）途中 であきらめず、最後 までがんばってください。／Don’t give up in the middle—please keep going until the end.

（2）1時間 待 っても雨 は止 まず、ぬれて帰 った。／The rain wouldn’t stop even after I waited for an hour, so I went home drenched.

（3）出発 前日 まで予約 が取 れず、心配 させられた。／I couldn’t get a reservation until the day before my departure, so I was really worried.

（4）だれにきいても住所 がわからず、困 った。／No matter who I asked, no one knew the address, so I was in a real fix.

Means the same as V-ないで or V-なくて. (1) is an example of simply putting two clauses side by side to mean “don’t give up.” In many cases, as in (3) and (4), the cause-and-effect relation between the first and second clauses is clear, and V-ず is used as an expression to indicate a reason. Although V-ず is used in spoken language, it is somewhat formal and has the tone of written language.

2. ...ず、...ず

［A-からず、A-からず］

［V-ず、V-ず］

（1）飲 まず食 わずで三日 間 も山中 を歩 きつづけた。／I continued to walk all over the mountains without eating or drinking for three whole days.

（2）その時 、彼 はあわてず騒 がず一言 「失礼 しました」と言 って部屋 を出 ていった。／At the time, he didn’t get flustered or make a scene, he just left the room with a single remark: “Excuse me.”

（3）展覧会 に出品 されている作品 はいずれも負 けず劣 らずすばらしい。／All the works presented at the exhibition are equally wonderful.

（4）独立 した子供達 とは、つかず離 れずのいい関係 だ。／I have a good relationship with my children, who are now on their own—not too close, but not too far.

（5）日本 の5月 は暑 からず、寒 からずちょうどいい気候 です。／The climate in Japan in May is just right—not too hot but not too cold.

（6）客 は多 からず、少 なからずほどほどだ。／The number of clients is just right—not too many and not too few.

Means “neither X nor Y.” In some cases words with similar meaning are listed, as in (1), (2), and (3), and in other cases words with contrasting meaning are listed, as in (4), (5), and (6). (3) means that after comparing several items it is found that “all of them are equally wonderful.” (4) means “keeping a suitable distance,” and (5) means “neither hot nor cold.” Idiomatic expressions. Other examples include 鳴かず飛ばず (fall into obscurity), etc.

<< 【せずに】 | Home | 【せつな】 >>

【せっかく】

1. せっかく...からには

（1）せっかく留学 するからには、できる限 り多 くの知識 を身 につけて帰 りたい。／Since I’m going abroad to study, I’d like to return having gained as much knowledge as I can.

（2）せっかく代表 として選 ばれたからには、全力 を尽 くさなければならない。／I must do my very best, since I was chosen to be the representative.

（3）せっかく休暇 をとるからには、2日 や3日 でなく、10日 ぐらいは休 みたい。／If I’m taking a vacation, I’d like to take at least ten days or so off, not just two or three.

Used in the pattern せっかくXからにはY. X is an action that involves effort, hardship, or a rare opportunity, and Y indicates the speaker’s desire to use such an effort or opportunity effectively. Expressions of intention, hope, advice, etc. are used in Y.

2. せっかく...けれども

（1）せっかくここまできたけれども、雨 がひどくなってきたから引 き返 そう。／I know we’ve come all this way, but it’s starting to rain harder, so let’s head back.

（2）せっかく皆 さんに骨折 っていただきましたが、実 はこの計画 は取 りやめになりました。／Although you have all worked so hard, I’m afraid this plan has been canceled.

（3）せっかく作 ったのですが、喜 んではもらえなかったようです。／Despite all the effort I put into making this, it doesn’t seem to have been appreciated.

Used in patterns like せっかくXけれどもY and せっかくXがY. X is an action that involves effort, hardship, or a rare opportunity. Y indicates that such an action has been wasted and expresses the speaker’s feeling of sorrow or regret for the waste.

3. せっかく...のだから

（1）せっかく来 たのだから夕飯 を食 べて行 きなさい。／Since you’ve come all this way, have supper before you go.

（2）せっかくここまで努力 したのだから、最後 までやり通 しましょう。／We’ve worked so hard to get this far, so let’s see it through to the end.

（3）せっかくおしゃれをしたのだから、どこかいいレストランへ行 きましょうよ。／I went to the trouble of getting all dressed up, so let’s go to a nice restaurant somewhere.

When せっかく is used in the pattern せっかくX（の）だからY, X is an action that involves effort, hardship, or a rare opportunity, and Y indicates the speaker’s desire to use such an effort or opportunity effectively. Expressions of intention, hope, request, invitation, advice, etc. are used in Y.

4. せっかく...のだったら

（1）せっかくピアノを習 うのだったら、少 しくらい高 くてもいい先生 についた方 がいい。／If I’m going to learn to play the piano, I may as well find a good teacher, even if it costs a little more.

（2）せっかく京都 まで行 くのなら、奈良 にも行 ってみたらどうですか。／If you’re going all the way to Kyoto, why not go to Nara as well?

（3）せっかく音楽 を楽 しむのだったら、もうすこし音 のいいステレオを買 いたい。／If I’m going to amuse myself by listening to music, I’d like to buy a stereo with better sound quality.

Used in patterns like せっかくXのだったらY or せっかくX（の）ならY. Indicates the speaker’s expectation that, if someone gets a rare opportunity or makes an effort to do something, it would be best to make the most of that opportunity or effort. Expressions that indicate intention, hope, advice, etc. are used in Y.

5. せっかく　...のに／...ても

（1）せっかく招待 していただいたのに、伺 えなくてすみません。／I was glad to receive your kind invitation, but I’m sorry I won’t be able to visit.

（2）せっかくいい天気 なのに、かぜをひいてどこにも行 けない。／Despite the nice weather, I can’t go anywhere because I’ve caught a cold.

（3）せっかくセーターを編 んであげたのに、どうも気 にいらないようだ。／Even though I went to the effort of knitting a sweater for him, he doesn’t seem to like it.

（4）せっかく来 ていただいても何 もお話 しすることはありません。／I don’t have anything to say to you, even if you make the effort to come all the way here.

（5）今回 のクイズには多数 のおはがきをお寄 せいただきました。ただせっかくお送 りいただきましても、締切日 をすぎておりますものは抽選 できませんのでご了承 ください。／Thank you for the many postcards we’ve received for this quiz. However, please understand that those sent after the deadline cannot be used in the draw.

The patterns せっかくXのにY and せっかくXてもY have the same meaning as せっかく...けれども. ...のに shows that X refers to a situation that has been realized, and ...ても shows that X refers to a hypothetical situation.

6. せっかくのN

（1）せっかくの日曜日 なのに、一日中 、雨 が降 っている。／Here it is Sunday, and wouldn’t you know it, it’s raining all day.

（2）せっかくのチャンスを逃 してしまった。／I let a rare opportunity slip away.

（3）せっかくの努力 が水 の泡 になってしまった。／All my efforts came to nothing.

（4）せっかくのごちそうなのだから、残 さないで全部 食 べましょう。／Since it’s such a feast, let’s eat it all up and not leave a crumb.

Used with nouns that describe an action involving a fortunate opportunity or an effort. Expresses a feeling of regret for not being able to utilize the opportunity/effort, or a feeling of hope or expectation that it should be utilized.

7. せっかく+連 体 修 飾 句 +N

（1）せっかく書 いた原稿 をなくしてしまった。／I’ve lost the draft that I worked so hard to write.

（2）せっかく覚 えた英語 も今 は使 う機会 がない。／Despite the effort I put into learning English, I have no opportunity to use it now.

（3）せっかくきれいに咲 いた花 をだれかが取 っていった。／Someone plucked the flower that was blooming so beautifully.

（4）せっかく作 った料理 を誰 も食 べてくれない。／Despite the effort I put into cooking this meal, no one’s eating it.

Indicates an action made possible by good fortune or one’s own efforts. Expresses a feeling of regret for not being able to utilize the opportunity/effort, or a feeling of hope or expectation that it should be utilized.

8. せっかくですが

（1）A:もう遅 いですから、泊 まっていらしたらいかがですか。／It’s already late, so why don’t you stay overnight?

B:せっかくですが、あしたは朝 から用事 がありますので。／Thank you, but tomorrow I have things to do starting in the morning.

（2）A:今晩 一緒 に食事 しない？／Shall we have dinner together tonight?

B:せっかくだけど、今晩 はちょっと都合 が悪 いんだ。／Thanks, but tonight’s just not convenient.

せっかくですが and せっかくだけど are used to preface the refusal of an offer or proposal made by someone else.

9. せっかくですから

（1）A:食事 の準備 がしてありますので、うちで召 し上 がってくださいよ。／Dinner is ready, so by all means, please stay and eat with us.

B:せっかくですから、お言葉 に甘 えて、そうさせていただきます。／That’s very kind of you. I will take you up on your generous offer.

（2）せっかくだから、あなたの作 ったケーキご馳走 になって行 くわ。／Since you went to all the trouble of baking a cake, I won’t leave without trying it.

Used to preface the acceptance of an offer or proposal made by someone else.

<< 【せつな】 | Home | 【せめて】 >>

【ぜひ】

（1）ぜひ一度 遊 びにきてください。／Please be sure to come and visit me sometime.

（2）《引越 しのあいさつ状 》お近 くにおいでの節 は是非 ともお立 ち寄 りください。／《on a postcard giving notice of a change of address》Please be sure to visit us when you are in the area.

（3）この大学 を卒業 する皆 さんは、ぜひ世 の中 の役 に立 つような人間 になってもらいたいものだと思 います。／I sincerely hope that all of you who are graduating from this university will become useful members of society.

（4）友人 から、引 っ越 したからぜひ遊 びに来 るようにという電話 がかかってきた。／A friend phoned to say please visit because they’ve moved to a new house.

（5）彼女 は有能 だから結婚 してもぜひ仕事 を続 けてほしい。／She’s very capable, so I really hope she keeps working even after she gets married.

Means “by all means” or “definitely.” Combines with expressions of request using てください, or expressions of hope/desire using てほしい, in order to express a strong wish. Not usually used with forms expressing a negative wish.

（×）ぜひ話さないでください。／By all means, please don’t tell anyone.

（○）ぜったいに話さないで下さい。／Don’t tell anyone, no matter what.

Also, it can only be used with respect to the activities of human beings.

（×）あしたはぜひ晴れてほしい。／I hope tomorrow will by all means be sunny.

（○）あしたは何としても晴れてほしい。／I really hope it will be sunny tomorrow.

To emphasize expressions of intention, adverbs such as かならず are used.

（×）ぜひそこに参ります。／I’ll go there by all means.

（○）かならずそこに参ります。／I’ll definitely go there.

However, ぜひ can be used to reply to a request, as for example in ぜひ行かせていただきます (I would very much like to go). This is a formal expression.

<< 【そういえば】 | Home | 【そうして】 >>

【そうしたら】

Used to connect two sentences in chronological sequence. そしたら is a more informal equivalent.

1. そうしたら〈future〉

（1）娘 は大学 に入 ったら下宿 すると言 っている。そうしたら、家 の中 が静 かになるだろう。／My daughter says she’s going to rent a room in a boarding house when she goes to college. Then our house will be quiet, I suppose.

（2）ここには木 を植 えて、ベンチを置 こう。そうしたら、いい憩 いの場所 ができるだろう。／Let’s plant a tree here and put a bench by it. If we do that, it’ll make a nice place to take a rest.

（3）彼 の店 はもうすぐ開店 するらしい。そうしたら、わたしも行 ってみよう。／Apparently his shop will be opening soon. When it does, I think I’ll go and see it too.

（4）毎日 30分 だけ練習 しなさい。そうしたら見違 えるほど上達 するでしょう。／Practice for just thirty minutes every day. If you do that, you’ll improve so much that people will think you’re a different person.

Follows a sentence describing some kind of plan, etc. and indicates the future result of such a plan.

2. そうしたら〈past〉

（1）暑 いので窓 を開 けた。そうしたら大 きなガが飛 び込 んで来 た。／It was hot, so I opened the window. When I did, a big moth flew in.

（2）忘 れ物 をとりに夕方 学校 へ行 った。そうしたらもう正門 が閉 まっていた。／I went back to the school in the evening to pick up something I’d forgotten. When I got there, the front gate was already shut.

（3）ふらっとデパートに入 ってみた。そうしたらちょうどバーゲンセールをしていた。／I happened to pop into a department store and found it was having a sale.

（4）前 にはだぶだぶだったズボンをはいてみた。そうしたらちょうどいい大 きさになっていた。／I tried on some pants that used to be very baggy and found that they were now just the right size.

（5）試験 のあと、参考書 を開 いてみた。そうしたら、全 く同 じ問題 がのっていた。／After the exam, I opened my reference book, just to find that it had exactly the same question in it.

Used to describe a past event that took place as the result of another event or act. Often used to describe a new discovery. Unlike そして, そうしたらlinks what happened in the previous sentence with a situation or event that is unrelated to the speaker’s own actions or intentions, or with a new occurrence, or with the discovery of a fact. そうしたら cannot be followed by expressions indicating an intentional act. Used in casual spoken language.

（×）デパートへ行った。そうしたら買物をした。／I went to the department store and found that I did some shopping.

（○）デパートへ行った。そして買物をした。／I went to the department store and did some shopping.

→【たら1】3

<< 【だい】 | Home | 【たいした】 >>

【たいがい】

（1）あの人 は、たいがい9時 ごろ来 ます。8時 ごろの時 もありますが。／That person usually arrives at around nine o’clock... but sometimes at eight or so.

（2）私 は、朝食 は、たいがいパンですね。／I usually have bread for breakfast.

（3）そんなに遠 くない所 なら、たいがいは自転車 を使 うことにしています。／If I’m going somewhere that’s not so far away, I generally try to use my bicycle.

（4）試験 の成績 が悪 かった人 は、たいがいの場合 、追試 を受 けることになっています。／In most cases, students who get a bad score are expected to take a make-up exam.

Used with respect to habitual activities, to express that their frequency or likelihood is high. May also be used in the forms たいがいは and たいがいの場合（は）. Cannot be used to make a conjecture about the future.

（×）今晩はたいがい7時には帰るでしょう。／He’ll usually be back at seven o’clock tonight.

（○）今晩はおそらく7時には帰るでしょう。／He’ll probably be back at seven o’clock tonight.

When used in the form たいがいのN, as in たいがいの人 (most people) or たいがいの町 (most towns), it means that the proportion of something is high, and it can be replaced by 大部分のN (the majority of N). たいてい (most) can also be used.

<< 【だいたい】 | Home | 【たいへん】 >>

【たいてい】

（1）あの人 は、たいてい9時 ごろ来 ます。8時 ごろの時 もありますが。／That person generally arrives at around nine o’clock... but sometimes at eight or so.

（2）私 は、朝食 は、たいていパンですね。／I usually have bread for breakfast.

（3）そんなに遠 くない所 なら、たいていは自転車 を使 うことにしています。／If I’m going somewhere that’s not very far, I usually try to use my bicycle.

（4）試験 の成績 が悪 かった人 は、たいていの場合 、追試 を受 けることになっています。／In most cases, students who get a bad score are expected to take a make-up exam.

Used with respect to habitual activities and expresses that their frequency or probability is high. Cannot be used to make a conjecture about the future.

（×）今晩はたいてい7時には帰るでしょう。／He’ll generally be back by seven o’clock tonight.

（○）今晩はおそらく7時には帰るでしょう。／He’ll probably be back by seven o’clock tonight.

May be used in the forms たいていは and たいていの場合 (は). When used in the form たいていのN, as in たいていの人 (most people) or たいていの町 (most towns), it means that there is a high proportion of something and it can be replaced by 大部分のN (the majority of N). たいがい (most) can also be used.

<< 【たかが】 | Home | 【だから】 >>

【たかだか】

（1）あれはそんなに高 くないと思 うよ。たかだか 3000 円 ぐらいのもんだろう。／I don’t think that (item) is so expensive. Probably only about 3,000 yen, at most.

（2）今度 の出張 はそんなに長 くならないでしょう。のびたとしても、たかだか一週間 程度 のものだと思 います。／I don’t think this business trip will be very long. Even if it’s extended, I think it’ll only be about a week at most.

（3）ちょっとぐらい遅刻 してもしかられないよ。あの先生 なら、たかだか「これから気 をつけてください」と言 う程度 だと思 うよ。／You won’t get scolded for being a little late. I think the most that teacher will say is just “be careful from now on.”

（4）長生 きしたとしてもたかだか90 年 の人生 だ。私 は、一瞬 一瞬 が生 の充実感 で満 たされているような、そんな人生 を送 りたいと思 っている。／Even a long life is not more than ninety years. I want to live a life in which every moment is filled with a sense of accomplishment.

Used to make a conjecture that the quantity or extent of something probably won’t be very great, even based on a generous estimate. Often used with ぐらい or 程度. Cannot be used if the speaker is stating something as a fact rather than an assumption.

（×）これは安かったですよ。たかだか 2000 円でした。／This was cheap. It was at most 2,000 yen.

（○）たった 2000 円でした。／This was only 2,000 yen.

<< 【だからといって】 | Home | 【だけ1】 >>

【たがる】

［R-たがる］

（1）子供 というものはなんでも知 りたがる。／Children want to know everything.

（2）子供 は歯医者 に行 きたがらない。／Children don’t like going to the dentist.

（3）父 は海外旅行 に行 きたがっているが、母 は行 きたくないようだ。／My father wants to travel abroad, but my mother doesn’t seem to want to go.

（4）夏 になると、みんな冷 たくてさっぱりしたものばかり食 べたがるが、それでは夏 バテしてしまう。／When summer comes, all everybody wants to eat is cold, mildly-flavored food, but that leads to summer fatigue.

（5）避難 している住民 は一刻 も早 く家 に帰 りたがっている。／The evacuated residents want to go home as soon as possible.

（6）リーさんは留学 してまだ半年 だが、家族 のことが心配 で国 に帰 りたがっている。／Lee-san has only been studying abroad for six months, but he wants to go home because he’s worried about his family.

（7）教授 はこの実験 を大学院 の学生 にさせたがっているが、今 のような研究 態勢 では無理 なのではないだろうか。／The professor wants to have graduate students do this experiment, but that may not be possible, given current trends in research.

Used to express the wishes or desires of a third person. Takes the form V-たがっている when a current situation is being expressed.

When たがる is not used, indirect expressions such as たいと言っている, たいらしい, and たいそうだ are used instead. たがる is not used when the speaker says something from the perspective of a third person, as in the example below.

（例）A:山本さん、どうしてパーティーに来なかったんでしょう。／I wonder why Yamamoto-san didn’t come to the party.

B:佐野に会いたくないからだよ。／Because she doesn’t want to see Sano.

On the other hand, たがる is used when the speaker is repeating what a third person thinks of him/her or has said about him/her.

（例）彼は僕が社長になりたがっていると思っているらしいが、僕はそんなつもりはまったくない。／He seems to think I want to become company president, but I have no such intention at all.

→【がる】

<< 【ためし】 | Home | 【たら2】 >>

【たら1】

［N／Na　だったら］

［A-かったら］

［V-たら］

One of the conjugations of predicates. Expresses a condition or opportunity. Has the same meaning as と, ば and なら (and expresses a general truth or law.) Tends to be used to describe a particular isolated matter rather than a general condition. In comparison to the other three, there are fewer restrictions on clause-final forms. Often used in spoken language. Polite forms are N/Na でしたら and V-ましたら. There is no polite form for たら clauses with i-adjectives. There is also a slightly old-fashioned expression たらば, in which ば is appended.

1. ...たら〈not-yet-realized condition〉

Expresses the relation of two isolated matters, such as “if X comes about, then Y will, too” or “if X comes about, then it will make Y come about, too.” X expresses both matters that have and have not come about, while Y always expresses something that has not yet come about. Y is used in declaratory sentences stating an unrealized matter or supposition, sentences expressing intention or hope, and indicative sentences which express imperatives, prohibitions, or invitations.

a. ...たら+未 実 現 のことがら

（1）雨 だったら道 が混雑 するだろう。／If it rains, the road will probably get crowded with traffic.

（2）もしも、あまり高 かったら誰 も買 わないでしょう。／If it should be too expensive, probably no one will buy it.

（3）万一 雨 が降 ったら試合 は中止 です。／In the event that it rains, the match will be canceled.

（4）この薬 を飲 んだらすぐにせきはとまりますが、3時間 たったら効 き目 がなくなります。／If you take this medicine, your cough will stop immediately, but the effect will wear off after three hours.

（5）あんなに美人 だったら、男性 がほうっておかないだろう。／Such a beauty like that will probably not be left alone by any man.

（6）ここまで来 たら、一人 でも帰 れます。／Once I’ve come this far, I can make my way home alone.

（7）そんなにたくさん食 べたらおなかをこわしますよ。／You’ll upset your stomach if you eat so much.

Usage for when Y expresses a statement about matters which have not yet come about. The dictionary form of the predicate, or such a predicate combined with the supposition だろう, are used at the end of sentences.

In (1)-(4), both X and Y are matters which have not yet come about, and when X comes about, then Y will follow. もし or 万一 are sometimes used when making suppositions about uncertain matters which have not yet come about or matters which are unlikely to come about. (4) is a usage which simply describes future matters that will come about in sequence, and has less of a suppositional meaning.

In (5)-(7), X has already come about, and based on this a supposition Y is made. X often includes こ／そ／あwords (e.g. ここ, そんな) to indicate a current status.

たら tends to be used for isolated matters, and is unlikely to be used for general conditions expressing a universal truth or law. However, in spoken language, it is sometimes used for expressing repetition of one’s habit or a certain matter, as the following examples show:

（8）いつも、5時 になったらすぐ仕事 をやめて、テニスをします。／I always stop working right away and play tennis when it is five o’clock.

（9）ここは冬 になったら雪 が1メートルぐらいつもる。／We get about three meters of snow here when it’s winter.

（10）ふだんは昼 ご飯 を食 べたら昼寝 をしますが、今日 は買物 に行 かなければなりません。／I usually take a nap after lunch, but I have to go shopping today.

（11）古 くなったらすぐに新 しいのに買 いかえるというような生活 では、お金 は貯 まらない。／You can’t save money if you have the kind of lifestyle where you always buy new things when something gets old.

(8)-(11) express the meaning “after X is accomplished, Y will be done.” X expresses a time frame in which Y will come about or that the action will be repeated within that time frame. In this case, たらcan be replaced byと.

b. ...たら+表 出 ・働 きかけ

（1）この仕事 が完成 したら、長 い休 みをとるつもりだ。／Once this job is completed, I intend to take a long vacation.

（2）もしも1千万 円 の宝 くじに当 たったら、何 でも買 ってあげますよ。／I’ll buy you anything you want if I win 10 million yen in the lottery.

（3）教師 になったら子 どもたちにものをつくる楽 しさを教 えたい。／If I become a teacher, I want to teach children the joy of making things.

（4）お風呂 に入 ったらすぐ寝 なさい。／Go to sleep immediately after your bath.

（5）この予防 注射 をしたら、風呂 に入 ってはいけません。／You should not take a bath after you have this vaccination.

（6）お酒 を飲 んだら絶対 に運転 はするな。／Never drink and drive.

（7）宿題 が済 んだら遊 びに行 ってもいいよ。／You may go play once you have finished your homework.

（8）A:あちらで野田 さんに会 われますか。／Will you meet Noda-san there?

B:ええ、その予定 ですが。／Yes, that’s the plan.

A:じゃ、お会 いになったらよろしくお伝 えください。／Well, in that case please give her my regards.

（9）もしも遅 れたら、連絡 してください。／Please let me know if you’ll be late.

（10）会議 が終 わったら食事 をしに行 きましょう。／Let’s go and have dinner after the meeting is finished.

Expresses meanings such as “When X comes about, let’s do/I want to do Y” and “When X comes about, do Y/don’t do Y/I can do Y/please do Y.” Y contains “expressive” expressions which indicate the speaker’s will/hope or “indicative” expressions, such as commands, prohibitions, permissions, requests, or invitations.

Usually used to express a specific actual outcome about Y, which will come about when X has occurred. X expresses matters that precede Y, and can be replaced by expressions such as “when this happens,” “when you do...,” or “after this.” As shown below, when たら is preceded by a situational predicate such as ある, an i-adjective, or a noun, it means “if that’s the situation”; moreover, if such a situation obtains, the expression shows the will or hope of the speaker or a demand or recommendation to the listener.

When the sentence concerns the listener’s schedule or wish, it is closer to Usage 6 of たら (<introductory utterance>).

（11）暇 があったら海外旅行 をしたい。／I’d like to travel abroad if I have time.

（12）暑 かったら、窓 を開 けてください。／Please open the window if you’re hot.

（13）お暇 でしたら、いらっしゃいませんか。／Would you like to visit me if you are free?

（14）そんなに勉強 が嫌 だったら大学 なんかやめてしまえ。／If you dislike studying that much, then quit college.

（15）熱 があったら休 んでもいいよ。／You may take time off if you have a fever.

When compared to たら, とand ばhave more restriction on their usage. とcannot be used with “expressive” or “indicative” expressions and when X is a verb indicating action or change, it is odd to use ば for “expressive” or “indicative” meaning.

（×）結婚すれば仕事をやめたい。／I want to quit my job if I marry.

（○）結婚したら仕事をやめたい。／I want to quit my job when I get married.

（×）お風呂に入ればすぐ寝なさい。／Go to sleep as soon as if you have a bath.

（○）お風呂に入ったらすぐ寝なさい。／Go to sleep as soon as you have taken a bath.

c. ...たら+問 いかけ

（1）雨 だったら試合 は中止 になりますか。／If it rains, will the match be canceled?

（2）A:結婚 したら仕事 はやめるの？／You’re going to quit work when you get married?

B:ううん、しばらく続 けるつもりよ。／No, I plan to continue for a while.

（3）万一 雨 が降 ったらどうしましょうか。／What shall we do in case it rains?

（4）A:もし宝 くじに当 たったら、何 に使 いますか。／If you win the lottery, what will you use it for?

B:すぐに使 わないで貯金 しておきます。／I won’t use it right away, I’ll save it.

（5）A:大学 を卒業 したらどうするつもりですか。／What are you going to do after you graduate?

B:オーストラリアに留学 したいと思 っています。／I am thinking of studying abroad in Australia.

（6）A:社長 はただ今 出 かけておりますが。／The company president is currently out of the office.

B:何時 ごろでしたらお帰 りでしょうか。／What time will he be returning?

（7）どのぐらい勉強 したら日本語 の新聞 が読 めるようになりますか。／How long do you have to study to be able to read a Japanese newspaper?

Used in interrogative sentences which require an answer from the listener, in the form X たら Y か.

(1) and (2) are interrogatives, seeking “yes” or “no” answers; (3)-(7) are cases of interrogatives with question words such as “what” and “how”; (3)-(5) are cases where the Y in “is it Y, if X?” is unknown; and (6)-(7) are cases where X is unknown.

In interrogative sentences where the method or means X for getting a good result is asked about, as in (6) and (7), たらcan be replaced byば, but in interrogatives where it is asked what action Y will take when X comes about, as in (2)-(5), たら is mostly used, and the use of ば is unnatural.

（×）結婚すれば仕事をやめるつもりですか。／Do you intend to quit your job if you marry?

（○）結婚したら仕事をやめるつもりですか。／Do you intend to quit your job when you get married?

（×）大学を卒業すればどうしますか。／What are you going to do if you graduate from university?

（○）大学を卒業したらどうしますか。／What are you going to do after graduating from university?

d. 疑 問 詞 +V-たら...のか

（1）何度 言 ったら分 かるんだ？／How many times do I have to tell you so you understand?

（2）人間 は戦争 という愚行 を何度 繰 り返 したら気 がすむのであろうか？／How many times do humans have to repeat the foolish action we call war before they have had enough?

（3）何年 たったら一人前 になれるのだろうか？／How many years will it take before I am a full-fledged member of society?

（4）何回 繰 り返 したら覚 えられるのか？／How many times do you have to repeat it before you remember it?

（5）どれだけ待 ったら平和 な世界 になるのだろうか？／How long do we have to wait to see a world at peace?

（6）一体 どうしたら今 の思 いを伝 えることができるのか？／Just how can I best convey my thoughts now?

This is an ironic expression where the たら form of the verb is attached to question words such as 何/どれだけ/どんなに. Means “no matter how ..., things won’t happen the way one wants them to,” and expresses irritation or despair regarding the situation. These sentences end with のか or のだ/のだろう（か）. V-たらcan be replaced by V-ば.

e. ...たらどんなに...か

（1）宝 くじに当 たったらどんなにうれしいだろう。／How happy I would be if I won the lottery!

（2）合格 したら両親 はどんなに喜 んでくれるだろうか。／How happy my parents would be if I passed the examination!

（3）子供 たちがもどってきたらどんなににぎやかになることか。／How lively it will be when the children return!

Means “how good it will be if X comes about.” Used when expressing a strong wish that X will be realized or expressing the feeling that if it comes about, then one would be really happy. だろう（か） or ことかare used at the end of the sentence.

2. ...たら〈counter-factual〉

a. ...たら　...だろう／...はずだ

（1）あのとき精密 検査 を受 けていたら、手遅 れにならなかっただろう。／Had there been a detailed check-up at that time, it wouldn’t have been too late.

（2）隕石 が地球 に衝突 していなかったら恐竜 は絶滅 していなかったかもしれない。／Dinosaurs might not have died out had a meteorite not hit the earth.

（3）ひどい話 を聞 かなかったら、こんなに酔 うまで飲 んだりしなかったにちがいない。／If I hadn’t heard the horrible story, I’m sure I wouldn’t have drunk myself to this point.

（4）あの時 彼 と結婚 していたら、私 の人生 はもっと幸 せだったはずだ。／Had I married him at the time, my life would have been happier.

（5）あの当時 この「薬 の害 」という本 を読 んでいたら今 ごろ苦 しまなくてもよかったのに残念 だ。／What a pity. Had I read the book The Harm of Medicine in those days, I might not have had to suffer as I do now.

（6）A:面接 試験 、うまくいった？／Did the interview test go all right?

B:うまくいっていたら、こんな顔 していないよ。／I wouldn’t look like this if it had gone well.

（7）点数 があと 10 点 高 かったらこの大学 に合格 できるんだけど。／I would be able to pass the entrance exam to this university if only my score were ten points higher.

Used to make a supposition different from what has actually happened or the opposite of what has actually happened, and expresses what something would have been like if such were the case. In most cases, the verb is put into the stative form V-ていたら.

When making a supposition which is contrary to the facts in the past, the ta-form of predicates, such as ただろう/はずだ/のに, is used at the end of the sentence. On the other hand, when making a supposition which is contrary to the current situation, the dictionary form, such as ...するのに/のだが, is used, as in (6) and (7).

In this usage, たら can be replaced by ば, but たら is more colloquial. Refer to ば (Usage 4) for a more detailed explanation of conditional sentence patterns expressing counter-factual matters.

b. ...たらどんなに...か

（1）背 があと 10 センチ高 かったらどんなによかっただろうか。／How nice it would be if only I were ten centimeters taller.

（2）10 年 前 に彼女 に会 っていたらどんなによかっただろう。／How nice it would have been had I met her ten years ago.

（3）祖母 が生 きていたら、どんなに喜 んだことか。／If my grandmother were alive, how pleased she would have been.

（4）今 すぐあなたに会 えたらどんなにうれしいだろうか。／How happy I would be if I could meet you right now!

Used when X is impossible or contrary to reality, and means “how good it would have been if X were the case.” Expresses the feeling that one has the strong wish that X will come about, but regrets that such a thing cannot ever happen.

When making a supposition contrary to what has already come about, ただろうか is used, as in (1)-(3), and when something has not come about yet, and it seems impossible that it will ever happen, るだろうか is used, as in (4).

3. ...たら...た〈already-realized condition〉

（1）空港 に着 いたら友達 が迎 えに来 ていた。／When I arrived at the airport, my friend was waiting to meet me.

（2）トンネルを出 たら一面 の銀世界 だった。／Coming out of the tunnel brought us into a winter wonderland.

（3）変 な音 がするので隣 の部屋 に行 ってみたらねずみがいた。／I went to the room next door because I heard a strange sound, and there was a mouse.

（4）山田 さんは無口 でおとなしい人 だと思 っていたが、よく話 をしたらとても面白 い人 だということが分 かった。／I thought Yamada-san was a quiet, timid person, but when I spoke to him, I realized that he was a very amusing person.

（5）お風呂 に入 っていたら、電話 がかかってきた。／The phone rang when I was in the bath.

（6）デパートで買 い物 していたら、隣 の奥 さんにばったり会 った。／I ran into the lady from next door when I was shopping at the supermarket.

（7）5月 に入 ったら急 に暑 くなった。／The weather suddenly turned hot right at the beginning of May.

（8）薬 を飲 んだら熱 が下 がった。／My temperature went down when I took the medicine.

（9）会社 をやめたらストレスがなくなって元気 になった。／After I quit the company, my stress went away and I recovered.

（10）落 ちてもともとと思 って試験 を受 けたら、思 いがけず合格 した。／I took the examination thinking I would fail, but I unexpectedly passed it.

（11）部屋 の様子 が変 だと思 ったら、案 の定 、空 き巣 に入 られていた。／I thought something about the room seemed strange and, just as I feared, someone had broken in.

The XたらYた pattern is used to indicate that both the former and the latter have already come about. It is used when the speaker realizes Y at the point when X has already come about, or when a new situation happens as a result of it. Following Y are expressions stating that something has occurred beyond the speaker’s control, or some fact has been newly discovered or realized.

(1)-(4) are usages in which the speaker discovers situation Y at the scene where action X has already been done. The discoverer, 私, is not mentioned in Y as in ...たら、私は...した, but instead the speaker uses expressions to portray the situation, such as ...たら...ということが分かった, ...たら...がいた or ...たら...があった.

（×）隣の部屋に行ったら、私はねずみを見た。／If I go to the room next door, I saw a mouse.

（○）隣の部屋に行ったら、ねずみがいた。／When I went to the room next door, there was a mouse.

Expressions of state, such as V-ていた or Nだった, are used for Y where newly-realized discoveries are expressed, as in (1) and (2).

On the other hand, if V-たis used instead of V-ていた, the meaning changes as follows.

（例）空港に着いたら友達が迎えに来た。／After I arrived at the airport, my friend came to meet me.

In the example above, the active expression来たis used instead of 来ていた. This is used to indicate that after the speaker arrived at the airport, the friend arrived to meet him, rather than that the speaker found the friend upon arrival, as in (1) above.

As in (10) and (11), when what follows the supposition in the second clause is the expected outcome, 案の定 or やっぱりare used; when the result is unexpected, then 案外、意外なことに or 思いがけず are frequently used.

たら in this usage is often replaced by と. However, if X and Y both indicate the same person’s consecutive action of which that person has control, only と can be used, and not たら.

（×）男は部屋に入ったら友達に電話した。／If the man entered the room, he phoned his friend.

（○）男は部屋に入ると友達に電話した。／The man called his friend when he entered the room.

While と is used in novels or stories, たら is used to describe things which the speaker has directly experienced.

4. ...たらさいご

（1）彼 は寝 たら最後 、まわりでどんなに騒 いでも絶対 に目 をさまさない。／Once he falls asleep, he won’t wake up no matter how noisy it is around him.

（2）賭事 は一度 手 を出 したら最後 ずるずると抜 けられなくなる人 が多 い。／With gambling, many people cannot break free from it once they have given it a try.

（3）すっぽんは一度 かみついたら最後 どんなことがあっても離 れない。／Once a snapping turtle bites something, it won’t let go no matter what happens.

Means that once something has happened, because of its characteristics or a strong determination, the situation will not change subsequently. Often used in the form 一度...たらさいご絶対に....

5. ...たら...で

［A-かったらA-いで］

［A-かったらA-かったで］

［V-たらV-たで］

（1）金 というのはあったらあったで使 うし、なかったらないで何 とかなるものだ。／Money is something that you’ll spend if you have it, and somehow get by if you don’t.

（2）自動車 はあれば便利 だが、なかったらなかったで何 とかなるものだ。／A car is convenient if you have one, but you can manage to get by if you don’t.

（3）母 は寒 がりで冬 が苦手 だが、それでは夏 が好 きかというとそうではない。暑 かったら暑 かったで文句 を言 っている。／My mother hates being cold and dislikes winter, but if you think that she likes summer, that’s not the case. If it's hot, she'll complain about that, too.

（4）息子 には大学 に受 かってほしいが、受 かったら受 かったでお金 が要 って大変 だ。／I want my son to pass the university entrance examination, but if he does pass, then it’ll be hard because he’ll need money.

（5）平社員 のときは給料 が少 なくて困 ったけど、昇進 したらしたでつきあいも増 えるしやっぱり金 はたまらない。／My low salary was a problem when I was a junior employee, but since being promoted I have more socializing and whatnot to do so I still can’t save any money after all.

Repeats the same adjectives or verbs twice, before and after. Describes a contrasting circumstance that, despite what happens, will ultimately not differ from the present one.

Some sentences express the meaning “there are problems but they are not too bad/they can be managed somehow,” as in (1) and (2), while other sentences see the situation as undesirable, indicating that “either way it is troublesome/a problem,” as in (3)-(5).

i-adjectives are normally used in the form A-かったらA-かったで, but sometimes the なかったらないでform is also used, as in (1).

...ば...で is a synonymous expression.

6. ...たら〈introductory utterance〉

Used to indicate under what condition the action in the second part of the sentence may be carried out, by restricting the scope or giving a warning or explanation in advance. It is, to a certain extent, a fixed idiomatic expression. It can be replaced by ば.

a. ...たら+依 頼 ・勧 め〈introductory utterance〉

（1）もし差 し支 えなかったら事情 を聞 かせてください。／Please tell me the circumstances, if you don’t mind.

（2）よろしかったら、もう一度 お電話 くださいませんか。／Would you call me again, if you don’t mind?

（3）よかったら、週末 、家 にいらっしゃいませんか。／Would you like to visit our home this weekend?

Idiomatic expression used for politely asking the convenience of the other person when making a request or recommendation.

b. ...たら〈introductory utterance〉

（1）私 から見 たら、こんなことはたいした問題 ではない。／From where I stand, it doesn’t seem like a serious problem.

（2）私 に言 わせたら、責任 はあなたの方 にあるんじゃないかと思 う。／If you ask me, I’d say the responsibility lies with you.

（3）一時代 前 と比 べたら、家事 は格段 に楽 になったと言 える。／It can be said that housework has become far easier in comparison with a generation ago.

This is one way of warning in advance from what viewpoint the utterance or judgment in the latter part of the sentence is made. It follows verbs that express a statement, an idea, or a comparison, such as 見る(see), 思う(think) and 比べる(compare), in the first part of the sentence. It is to a certain degree an idiomatic expression.

からしたら or から言ったらare synonymous expressions.

7. V-たら〈suggestion, recommendation〉

（1）立 って見 てないで、ちょっと手伝 ってあげたら。／Why don’t you lend a hand instead of just standing and watching?

（2）危 ないからやめといたら。／It’s dangerous, so don’t do it.

（3）そんなに疲 れているなら、すこし休 んだら？／How about resting a little, if you’re so tired?

This is an expression to recommend that the listener take a certain action. The latter half of V-たらどうか is omitted. It is usually used when speaking to someone with whom the speaker is on familiar terms. When it is necessary to speak politely, たらどうですか or いかがですか are used without abbreviating the latter half.

Can be replaced by V-ば; however, たら has the nuance that the speaker is seriously recommending something, while the use of ば can contain the nuance that the speaker in fact is merely stating an option without any particular preference.

8. ...からいったら→【からいう】1

9. ...からしたら→【からする】1

10. ...からみたら→【からみる】1

11. ...といったら→【といったらありはしない】、【といったらありゃしない】、【といったらない】

12. ...ときたら→【ときたら】

13. ...としたら→【としたら】

14. ...となったら→【となったら】

15. V-てみたら→【てみる】4

16. ...にかかったら→【にかかっては】

17. ...にかけたら→【にかけたら】、【にかけて】2

18. ...にしたら→【にしたら】

19. ...にしてみたら→【にしてみれば】

20. ...によったら／ことによったら→【によると】1b

21. だったら→【だったら】

<< 【たらどうか】 | Home | 【たりとも】 >>

【たり】

［N／Na　だったり］

［A-かったり］

［V-たり］

1. ...たり...たりする

（1）休 みの日 には、ビデオを見 たり音楽 を聞 いたりしてのんびり過 ごすのが好 きです。／On my day off I like to relax―watching videos or listening to music.

（2）コピーをとったり、ワープロを打 ったり、今日 は一日中 いそがしかった。／I was busy all day today with photocopying and typing.

（3）子供 が大 きくなって家族 がそろうことはめったにないのですが、年 に数回 はいっしょに食事 したりします。／My children have grown up so we seldom have the opportunity for the family to get together, but we do things like get together for dinner a couple times a year.

（4）給料日 前 には昼食 を抜 いたりすることもある。／I sometimes skip lunch on the day before payday.

（5）アルバイトで来 ている学生 は曜日 によって男子 学生 だったり女子 学生 だったりしますが、みなよく働 いてくれます。／Depending on the day, we can have men or women students working part-time, but they all work hard for us.

（6）彼女 の絵 のモチーフは鳥 だったり人 だったりするが一貫 して現代人 の不安 が描 かれている。／Her paintings’ motifs may be persons or birds or whatever, but there’s always a common depiction of present-day anxiety.

Points out two or three representative acts among several. There are also cases where only one example is pointed out, but it implies that other examples exist too, as in (3) and (4). The verb at the end of the sentence has たりするattached when the sentence ends with this pattern, as in ...たり...たりします／しました.

（×）きのうの休みにはビデオを見たり、散歩したり、手紙を書きました。／On the holiday yesterday I did things like watching videos, walking, and I wrote a letter.

（○）きのうの休みにはビデオを見たり、散歩したり、手紙を書いたりしました。／On the holiday yesterday I did things like watching videos, walking, and writing a letter.

2. ...たり...たり

（1）何 か心配 なことでもあるのか彼 は腕組 をして廊下 を行 ったり来 たりしている。／I don’t know if he’s worried about something, but he’s pacing up and down the corridor with his arms folded.

（2）去年 の秋 は暑 かったり寒 かったりして秋 らしい日 は少 なかった。／Last fall was sometimes hot and sometimes cold, without any real fall-like days.

（3）父 は近頃 あまり具合 いがよくなく、寝 たり起 きたりだ。／Father has not been very well lately, lying down and getting up again and again.

（4）薬 はきちんと飲 まなければいけない。飲 んだり飲 まなかったりでは効果 がない。／Medicine has to be taken properly; it has no effect if just taken sporadically.

（5）くつを買 おうと思 うが、いいと思 うと高 すぎたり、サイズがあわなかったりで、なかなか気 に入 ったのが見 つからない。／I want to buy a pair of shoes, but when I find a pair that I like they’re too expensive or the size doesn’t fit, so I just haven’t been able to get a pair that I like.

（6）あすは山間部 は晴 れたり曇 ったりの天気 でしょう。／Tomorrow the mountains will be occasionally sunny and occasionally cloudy.

Expresses a situation where a state or an act alternates repeatedly or there are two contrasting situations. Other expressions frequently used for contrasting situations include あったりなかったり (sometimes exists, and sometimes does not), 上がったり下がったり (going up and down), 泣いたり笑ったり (crying and laughing), 乗ったり降りたり (getting on and off), and 出たり入ったり (coming/going in and out).

3. ...たり　したら／しては

（1）英語 の生活 にもずいぶん慣 れたが、早口 で話 しかけられたりしたらわからなくて困 ることも多 い。／I’ve gotten pretty well used to living with English, but when people speak to me very quickly, I can often have problems.

（2）その人 のいないところで悪口 を言 ったりしてはいけない。／One mustn’t say bad things about a person when he is not around.

Implies that there are other instances as well. Example (2) has almost the same meaning as 悪口を言ったらいけない, but the expression is softened by not saying the complete form.

4. ...たりして

（1）A:変 だね、まだだれも来 てないよ。／That’s strange—no one’s come yet.

B:約束 、あしただったりして。／Maybe the appointment is tomorrow?

（2）A:佐野 さん、遅 いわね。／Sano-san is late.

B:ひとりだけ先 に行 ってたりして。／Could she have already gone ahead by herself?

This is a way of focusing on one example. Implies that there are other possibilities, and is used when avoiding saying something directly. An indirect, bantering expression. Often used in colloquial speech by young people.

<< 【たりとも】 | Home | 【たろう】 >>

【たる】

Derived from the literary expression てあり. Gives a solemn impression. Has an exaggerated tone, and is used for extremely polite written language or formal spoken language such as in public speeches.

1. NたるN

（1）国家 の指導者 たる者 は緊急 の際 にすばやい判断 ができなければならない。／The leader of a nation has to have the ability to make a quick decision in an emergency situation.

（2）国会議員 たる者 は身辺 潔白 でなければならないはずである。／Someone who is a member of the Diet should be completely beyond reproach (lit. squeaky clean).

（3）教師 たる者 は、すべてにおいて生徒 の模範 とならねばならないとここに書 いてある。／It says here that a person who is a teacher must be a model for students in every respect.

（4）百獣 の王 たるライオンをカメラにおさめたいとサファリに参加 した。／He participated in a safari, saying he wanted to take pictures of a lion, the so-called king of beasts.

Means “something that has the (distinguished) qualification mentioned.”

2. NたるとNたるとをとわず

（1）救出 にあたっては軍人 たると民間人 たるとを問 わず、総力 を結集 せよ。／In rescue work, put all your effort into saving lives, regardless of whether you’re a soldier or a civilian.

（2）医療 活動 は民間人 たると、政府 関係者 たるとを問 わず、全員 を平等 に扱 う。／Medical work treats everyone equally, regardless of whether they are ordinary citizens or government officials.

（3）この法律 は市民 たると外国人 たるとを問 わず等 しく適用 される。／This law applies equally to all, regardless of whether they are a citizen or a foreigner.

Means “regardless of whether it’s X or Y, both are....”

3. Nたるべきもの

（1）それは、指導者 たるべき者 のとる行動 ではない。／That’s not how a leader should behave.

（2）後継者 たるべき者 は以下 の資格 を備 えていなければならない。／A successor should have the following qualifications.

（3）王 たるべき者 はそのようなことを恐 れてはならない。／A king must not fear such a thing.

Means “a person who ought to have such qualification as...” or “someone who should have the position of....” The latter half of the sentence usually states “must naturally be...,” to describe the desired form of the person with the qualification or position described in the first half.

4. Nたるや

（1）そのショーの意外性 たるや、すべての人 の注目 を集 めるに十分 であった。／The novelty of the show was enough to get the attention of everyone.

（2）その姿 たるや、さながら鬼 のようであった。／The figure was almost like a devil.

（3）その歌声 たるや、聞 き入 る聴衆 のすべてを感動 させるすばらしいものであった。／That voice was so wonderful that it impressed every audience.

（4）救出 に際 しての彼 らの活動 たるや、長 く記憶 にとどめるに十分 値 するものであった。／Their activities in doing rescue work were certainly worth keeping in memory for a long time.

Uses a noun which possesses a certain characteristic to emphasize what it expresses. Describes what property it has or what state it is in. Personal names are not used.

（×）山田先生たるや、すべての人を感動させた。／The way of Yamada-sensei impressed everyone.

（○）山田先生の話し振りたるや、すべての人を感動させた。／The way Yamada-sensei spoke impressed everyone.

This is a type of expression for emphasis when introducing the subject of the sentence. In (1), for example, it is an exaggerated expression in comparison to only その意外性は....

<< 【ちっとも...ない】 | Home | 【ちゃんと】 >>

【ちなみに】

（1）この遊園地 を訪 れた人 は、今年 五十 万人 に上 りました。これは去年 の三十 万人 を大 きく上回 っています。ちなみに迷子 の数 も千人 と去年 の倍 近 くありました。／The number of visitors to this amusement park reached 500,000 this year, far surpassing last year’s 300,000. Incidentally, the number of lost children was about 1,000, nearly double that of last year.

（2）この人形 はフランスで三百 年前 に作 られたもので、同種 のものは世界 に五体 しかないといいます。ちなみにお値段 は一体 500万 円 。／This doll was made in France three hundred years ago, and it’s said that there are only five in the world. For your information, the price for each doll is five million yen.

（3）山田 議員 の発言 は政局 に大 きな混乱 をもたらした。ちなみに山田 議員 は一昨年 も議会 で爆弾 発言 をしている。／Congressman Yamada’s remark has caused much confusion in the political world. For your information, Yamada also made a bombshell speech in the legislature the year before last.

Used when adding something related to the principal matter, and means “for your reference....” Used in written language or formal spoken language (e.g. news reports or meetings). This expression cannot be used for expressing an additional action.

（×）買い物に出かけた。ちなみに、友達のところに寄った。／I went shopping. For your reference, I went to my friend’s place.

（○）買い物に出かけた。ついでに、友達のところに寄った。／I went shopping. I also stopped by a friend’s house while I was out.

<< 【ってば】 | Home | 【つまり】 >>

【っぽい】

［Nっぽい］

［Rっぽい］

（1）男 は白 っぽい服 を着 ていた。／The man was wearing whitish clothes.

（2）あの人 は忘 れっぽくて困 る。／It’s a problem because he can be forgetful.

（3）30にもなって、そんなことで怒 るなんて子供 っぽいね。／To be already thirty years old and get angry over something like that is really childish, isn’t it?

（4）この牛乳 水 っぽくてまずいよ。／This milk is watery and tastes awful.

（5）死 ぬだとか葬式 だとか、湿 っぽい話 はもうやめよう。／Let’s quit talking about such depressing things like death and funerals.

Used with a noun or verb stem to form i-adjectives to express the meaning “feels that way” or “has the tendency to.”

Used with nouns that express colors, such as 赤(red), 白(white), 黒(black), 黄色(yellow), 茶色(brown), to express the meaning “has that color/characteristic” or “close to that color/characteristic,” as in (1). Also used with verb stems such as 怒る(get angry)／ひがむ(have an inferiority complex) ／ぐちる(grumble) ／忘れる(forget) to express the characteristics of someone who “always does ...” or “often does ...,” as in (2). Also used with 子供(child) ／女(woman) ／男(man) ／やくざ(the Japanese mafia) and so on, to express the meaning “like a child/yakuza” or “very manly (man-like)/womanly (woman-like),” as in (3).

In addition, there are usages like 水っぽい (too watery and thin), 湿っぽい (seems damp, gloomy), and 熱っぽい (seems to have a temperature/feverish). 子供っぽい／水っぽいhave negative connotations. When expressing a positive feeling, 子供らしい／みずみずしい are used.

<< 【つれて】 | Home | 【て...て】 >>

【て】

［N／Na　で］

［A-くて］

［V-て］

で is attached to nouns and na-adjectives. In the case of i-adjectives, it takes the form くて. ない has two forms: なくて and ないで. In the case of verbs, で is used for those whose dictionary form ends in グ, ヌ, ブ and ム, while all others take て.

（1）朝 ご飯 を作 って、子供 を起 こした。／I cooked breakfast and then woke my children up.

（2）しっかり安全 を点検 して、それからかぎをかけた。／I checked that everything was safe and then locked up.

（3）まず、買 い物 をして、それから、映画 を見 て、帰 って来 た。／I went shopping first, then watched a film, and then came home.

（4）電話 をかけて、面会 の約束 をとりつけて、会 いに行 った。／I called them, made an appointment for an interview, and then went to see them.

（5）山田 さんがやめて、高田 さんが入 った。／Yamada-san quit, and then Takada-san joined.

（6）びっくりして、口 もきけなかった。／I was so surprised that I couldn’t speak.

（7）着物 を着 て、出掛 けた。／I put on a kimono and went out.

（8）地下鉄 ははやくて安全 だ。／The subway is fast and safe.

（9）外 が真 っ暗 でこわかった。／Outside was dark and scary.

（10）めずらしい人 から手紙 をもらってうれしかった。／I was happy to receive a letter from someone who rarely writes me.

Used for loosely linking two clauses. ...て can be used twice, as in (3) and (4).

By linking sentences which express actions, this describes matters that take place in sequence, as in (1) and (2). Also used to express contrast, a possible reason, a means of action, or circumstances related to such, depending on the context.

In sentences expressing an attribute or state by the use of adjectives, this is sometimes used to list two attributes or to mention a possible reason. When an adjectival clause or description of a characteristic follows an expression of activity, as in (10), it often expresses a possible reason for something.

When several actions or situations alternate, or when one is describing something unrelated to a time sequence, たりis used instead of て.

<< 【ていけない】 | Home | 【ていはしまいか】 >>

【ていただく】

This is a form in which いただく is attached to the verb te-form. おR-いただく and ごNいただく are similar but more polite expressions.

1. V-ていただく〈benefit〉

（1）友達 のお父 さんに、駅 まで車 で送 っていただきました。／My friend’s father kindly drove me to the station.

（2）高野 さんに教 えていただいたんですが、この近 くにいいマッサージ師 がいるそうですね。／I was told by Takano-san that there is a good masseur in this area.

（3）会議 の日程 は、もう、山下 さんから教 えていただきました。／Yamashita-san has already explained to me the agenda for the meeting.

（4）《手紙 》珍 しいものをたくさんお送 りいただき本当 にありがとうございました。／《in a letter》 Thank you so very much for sending many unusual things.

The humble form of ...てもらう. Expresses the meaning that someone does an action for the speaker or someone on the listener’s side. Usually implies that the recipient is aware of receiving a favor or benefit. に is normally used for the person who does the favor, but から may also be used if a transfer of information or things is being expressed.

2. V-ていただく〈instructions〉

（1）まず、1階 で受 け付 けをすませていただきます。それから3階 の方 にいらして下 さい。／First of all, please complete the registration on the first floor, and then continue up to the third floor.

（2）この書類 に名前 を書 いていただきます。そして、ここに印鑑 を押 していただきます。／We will first ask you to write your name here. Then please stamp your seal here.

Used when giving polite instructions. Can only be used by the person giving instructions. Instead of V-ていただく, it often takes the form お／ご...いただく, as follows.

（例）3才以下のお子様はコンサート会場への入場をご遠慮いただきます。／We ask that children under three refrain from entering the concert venue.

（例）クレジットカードはご利用いただけません。／I’m afraid credit cards cannot be used.

3. V-ていただきたい

（1）A:この次 からは、間違 えないでいただきたいですね。／After this, I should hope there won’t be any more mistakes.

B:はい、申 し訳 ございませんでした。／Yes, I’m terribly sorry.

（2）この忙 しいときにすみません、あした休 ませていただきたいんですが...。／I’m sorry to ask at this busy time, but I’d like to have tomorrow off if I could.

（3）すみません、もう少 し席 をつめていただきたいんですが。／Excuse me, could you put the chairs a little closer to each other?

A humble expression corresponding to ...てもらいたい. Used when describing something that one wants the listener to do. If used in the ...ていただきたい form, often expresses a strong demand, although the form itself is polite. The form ...ていただきたいのですが, where the sentence is not finished, is used when making a hesitant request.

4. V-ていただける〈request〉

（1）A:ご注文 のお品 ですが、取 り寄 せますので、3日 ほど待 っていただけますか。／The goods you ordered need to be sent for, so could you wait for three days or so?

B:ええ、かまいません。／Yes, that’s no problem.

（2）これ、贈 り物 にしたいんですが、包 んでいただけますか。／I want to make this a gift—could you wrap it for me?

（3）A:わたしも手伝 いに来 ますよ。／I’ll come and help, too.

B:そうですか。じゃあ、日曜日 のお昼頃 来 ていただけますか。／Is that so? Well, could you come around lunchtime on Sunday?

（4）タクシーがまだ来 ませんので、あと5分 ぐらい待 っていただけませんか。／The taxi hasn’t arrived yet, so could you wait for five more minutes?

（5）先生 、論文 ができたんですが、ちょっと見 ていただけませんか。／Sensei (Professor), my paper is finished, so may I ask you to look at it for me?

（6）そのことはぜひ知 りたいんです。もし何 か詳 しいことがわかったら、連絡 していただけませんか。／I would really like to know about this. May I ask you to contact me if you learn of any details?

（7）5分 ほど待 っていただける？／Could you wait for five minutes or so?

（8）こちらにいらしていただけない？／Would you come this way?

Expresses a polite request by using いただける, the potential form of いただく. いただけませんか is a somewhat more hesitant expression than いただけますか, and it is often used when you don’t think the listener would necessarily agree to the request. Examples (7) and (8) are used when a woman makes a friendly request in a refined manner of someone of the same status or below. お／ご...いただける, an even politer form, is also often used.

（例）修理に少し時間がかかっています。すみませんが、もう少々お待ちいただけないでしょうか。／The repairs are taking a little time. I’m sorry, but could you wait a little longer?

5. V-ていただけるとありがたい

V-ていただけるとうれしい

（1）A:私 がやりましょう。／I’ll do it.

B:そうですか。そうしていただけると助 かります。／Can you? That would be very helpful.

（2）一人 では心細 いんで、いっしょに行 っていただけるとうれしいんですけれど。／It would be lonely by myself, so I’d be happy if you could go with me.

（3）《手紙 》お返事 がいただければ幸 いです。／《in a letter》 We would appreciate a reply.

Used with suppositional expressions such as ...ば, ...たら, ...と and describes a situation which will be favorable to the speaker if the listener takes the action. The speaker’s reaction is expressed by such phrases as ありがたい (grateful),うれしい (pleased), or 助かる (be saved trouble).

<< 【てください】 | Home | 【てくる】 >>

【てくださる】

くださる is attached to a verb te-form. There are other expressions that are even more polite, such as おR-くださる and ごNくださる.

1. V-てくださる〈benefit〉

（1）先生 が論文 をコピーしてくださった。／My teacher kindly photocopied the thesis for me.

（2）明日 山田 さんがわざわざうちまで来 てくださることになった。／It was decided that Yamada-san would kindly come to my house tomorrow.

（3）どうも今日 はわざわざおいで下 さってありがとうございました。／Thank you for coming all the way to see me today.

（4）せっかくいろいろ計画 して下 さったのに、だめになってしまって申 し訳 ありません。／With all the trouble you took to make all sorts of plans, I am so sorry that they didn’t work out.

This is an expression which makes the person doing an action the subject, and it is used for expressing that the person does something for the benefit of the speaker or someone associated with the speaker. Used when the person doing the action is senior or not close to the speaker. The honorific form of V-てくれる.

2. V-てくださる〈request〉

（1）ちょっとここで待 っていてくださる？／(a woman speaking) Would you wait for me here for a moment?

（2）いっしょに行 ってくださらない？／(a woman speaking) Would you come with me?

（3）ついでにこの手紙 も出 しておいて下 さいますか。／Could you also mail this letter for me?

（4）ちょっとこの書類 、ミスがないかどうかチェックして下 さいませんか。／Could I ask you to check that there is no mistake in this document?

This is an expression used to request someone to do something for the speaker or someone associated with the speaker. ...てくださいますか and ...てくださいませんか are even more polite than ...てください. ...てくださる and ...てくださらない in (1) and (2) are used by women to make a request of someone subordinate or equal in a friendly and refined way.

<< 【てくれ】 | Home | 【てこそ】 >>

【てくれる】

1. V-てくれる〈benefit〉

（1）鈴木 さんが自転車 を修理 してくれた。／Suzuki-san repaired the bicycle for me.

（2）誰 もそのことを（私 に）教 えてくれなかった。／No one told me about it.

（3）母 がイタリアを旅行 したとき案内 してくれたガイドさんは、日本語 がとても上手 だったらしい。／The tour conductor who guided my mother when she traveled around Italy was apparently very fluent in Japanese.

（4）自転車 がパンクして困 っていたら、知 らない人 が手伝 ってくれて、本当 に助 かった。／Just when I was in trouble as my bicycle got a flat tire, a stranger generously lent me a hand. That really helped me!

（5）せっかく迎 えに来 てくれたのに、すれ違 いになってしまってごめんなさい。／You took the trouble to come meet me and then we just missed each other—I’m sorry!

This is an expression which makes the person doing an action the subject, and it is used for expressing that the person does something for the benefit of the speaker or someone associated with the speaker. Used when the person conducts the action voluntarily. V-てもらうis often used if the action is conducted at the request of the speaker.

If only the verb is used instead of V-てくれる, the sentence will mean that the action was done for someone other than the speaker or someone associated with the speaker, so care is needed. For example, 鈴木さんが自転車を修理した means that Suzuki-san fixed a bicycle, and 鈴木さんが自転車を修理してくれた means “Suzuki-san fixed a bicycle for me.” If the speaker does not use the V-てくれる form, despite the fact that the action was done for his/her benefit, the sentence will sound odd.

（×）誰もそのことを私に教えなかった。／No one told me about it.

（○）誰もそのことを私に教えてくれなかった。／No one told me about it.

（×）おいしいリンゴを送って、ありがとう。／Sent delicious apples, thank you.

（○）おいしいリンゴを送ってくれて、ありがとう。／Thank you very much for sending me delicious apples.

This expression may also be used sarcastically, when a certain action causes the speaker an inconvenience or problem, as seen in the following example.

（例）大事な書類をどこかに置き忘れるなんて、まったく困ったことをしてくれたな。／You’ve certainly given me a lot of trouble by misplacing an important document somewhere!

2. V-てくれる〈request〉

（1）この本 、そこの棚 に入 れてくれる？／Can you put these books on the shelf there?

（2）ちょっとこの荷物 運 んでくれないか？／(a man speaking) Hey, can you carry this luggage for me?

（3）すみませんけど、ちょっと静 かにしてくれませんか。今 大事 な用事 で電話 してるんです。／Sorry, could you be quiet? I’m in the middle of an important phone call.

（4）もしよかったら、うちの子 に英語 を教 えてくれないか？／Is there a chance you could teach my child English?

This is an expression to request an action for the speaker or someone associated with the speaker. The plain form is used towards a subordinate or someone equal and close. ...てくれないか is used by men. ...てくれませんか creates a politer impression than ...てくれますか. Used when cautioning someone, as in example (3).

3. V-てやってくれないか

（1）息子 にもう少 し勉強 するように言 ってやってくれ。／Can you tell my son to study a bit more?

（2）山田 君 に何 か食 べるものを作 ってやってくれないか。／Can you maybe make something for Yamada-kun to eat?

Used when requesting the listener to conduct an action for a third person (someone other than the speaker and the listener). Used when the speaker, the listener, and the third person in question are close to one another and all are somehow associated with the speaker.

<< 【てこそ】 | Home | 【てしかたがない】 >>

【てさしあげる】

［V-てさしあげる］

（1）昨日 は社長 を車 で家 まで送 ってさしあげた。／I took the president home by car yesterday.

（2）A:あなた、お客様 を駅 までお見送 りしてさしあげたら？／《wife speaking to husband》Why don’t you take our guests to the station to see them off?

B:うん、そうだな。／OK, I’ll do that.

（3）田中 さんをご存 じないのなら、私 の方 から連絡 してさしあげましょうか。／If you do not know Tanaka-san, shall I contact him for you?

Expresses that the speaker (or someone on the side of the speaker) does an action for other people. Often used when the person receiving the action is superior or equal to, but not close to, the speaker. sed to express, in a humble way, that the speaker does something for someone who is having problems or cannot do the action which the speaker can do. However, it can also give the impression of forcing something upon someone.

Thus, it is strange to use this form when directly addressing a higher-status person. When one does use it, it will sound impolite unless one avoids using the forms V-てさしあげます／ましょう, as in (3), in order to soften the impression of forcing something upon someone. In polite speech, humble forms such as お送りした and ご連絡しましょうか are usually used.

<< 【てさしあげる】 | Home | 【でしかない】 >>

【てしかたがない】

［Na でしかたがない］

［A-くてしかたがない］

［V-てしかたがない］

（1）公園 で出会 って以来 、彼女 のことが気 になってしかたがない。／Ever since I met her in the park, I just can’t get her out of my mind.

（2）この映画 はみるたびに、涙 が出 てしかたがない。／I just can’t help tearing up every time I watch this movie.

（3）何 とか仕事 に集中 しようとしているのだが、気 が散 ってしかたがない。／No matter how much I try to concentrate on my work, I just can’t keep my mind from wandering.

（4）毎日 ひまでしかたがない。／I have too much time on my hands every day.

（5）試験 に合格 したので、うれしくてしかたがない。／I couldn’t contain myself after passing the examination.

（6）台風 のせいで、あの山 に登 れなかったのが、今 でも残念 でしかたがない。／I still regret that I couldn’t climb that mountain because of a typhoon.

（7）わたしが転職 したのは、前 の会社 で働 くのがいやでしかたがなかったからだ。／The reason I changed jobs was that I just couldn’t stand working at my previous company.

（8）田中 さんは孫 が可愛 くて仕方 がないらしい。／Apparently Tanaka-san dotes shamelessly on her grandchild.

Expresses an emotion or feeling arising naturally from a source beyond the control of the speaker. Often used to express an irrepressibly strong emotion. Usually preceded by an expression of emotion, feeling, or desire; use of words denoting an attribute or evaluation leads to awkward constructions.

（×）歌が下手で仕方がない。／Her singing can’t help but be poor.

（○）歌がとても下手だ。／Her singing is really poor.

In addition to directly expressing emotion or feeling, this construction can also be used in cases when a situation lies beyond the control of the speaker and results in problems or annoyance.

（例）最近うちの息子は口答えをしてしかたがないんです。／Recently our son has taken to talking back to us and we don’t know what to do.

（例）年のせいか物忘れをしてしかたがない。／It might just be age, but I’m getting awfully forgetful.

At times が is omitted, resulting in the construction ...てしかたない. In casual conversation, the form ...てしょうがない is also used. For the difference in meaning from てならない, refer to that section.

<< 【てちょうだい】 | Home | 【てでも】 >>

【てっきり...とおもう】

（1）彼女 がいろいろな結婚式 場 のパンフレットを持 っているので、これはてっきり結婚 するんだと思 ってしまったんです。／She had all sorts of brochures of places for wedding receptions, so I was convinced she was going to get married.

（2）人 が倒 れていたので、てっきり事故 だと思 って駅員 に知 らせたんです。／I saw someone lying on the floor and was sure there had been an accident, so I went to tell the station staff.

（3）窓 ガラスが割 れていたので、これはてっきり泥棒 だと思 ったんです。／I saw the broken window and was sure there had been a robber.

（4）てっきり怒 られるものと思 っていたが、反対 にほめられたので、驚 いた。／I expected him to be angry at me, so I was surprised to be praised instead.

Used to explain, after the fact, that the speaker believed something was really true, based on an assumption s/he had made on the grounds of a piece of evidence or reason. てっきり emphasizes the strength of the conviction. Often the assumption is actually mistaken. Can only be used for assumptions made in the past.

（×）てっきり帰ったと思っています。／I feel sure you had gone home.

（○）てっきり帰ったと思いました。／I felt sure you had gone home.

<< 【でなくては】 | Home | 【てのこと】 >>

【てならない】

［Na でならない］

［A-くてならない］

［V-てならない］

（1）卒業 できるかどうか、心配 でならない。／I am beside myself with worry about whether or not I’ll be able to graduate.

（2）将来 がどうなるか、不安 でならない。／Thinking about the future gives me great concern.

（3）子供 のころニンジンを食 べるのがいやでならなかった。／When I was a child, having to eat carrots repulsed me.

（4）あのコンサートに行 き損 ねたのが今 でも残念 でならない。／I will never stop regretting that we missed going to that concert.

（5）住 み慣 れたこの土地 を離 れるのがつらくてならない。／It is really painful for us to leave this place that has been our home for such a long time.

（6）だまされてお金 をとられたのがくやしくてならない。／I am so ticked off at getting cheated out of my money.

（7）青春 時代 を過 ごした北海道 の山々 が思 い出 されてならない。／I can’t help recalling the mountains of Hokkaido, where I spent my youth.

（8）きのうの英語 の試験 の結果 が気 になってならない。／The results of yesterday’s English exam are really bothering me.

（9）大切 な試験 に失敗 してしまった。なぜもっと早 くから勉強 しておかなかったのかと悔 やまれてならない。／I failed an important exam. I am filled with regret that I didn’t start studying sooner.

Expresses a feeling or state of emotion that is the natural outcome of a situation and beyond the control of the speaker. Often used to indicate a state of mind that cannot be suppressed, resulting in a highly emotional condition. てならない is preceded by words denoting emotion or feeling or desire. If words that refer to characteristics or evaluation are used, an awkward construction results.

（×）この本はつまらなくてならない。／This book can’t be anything but boring.

（○）この本はすごくつまらない。／This book is really boring.

Has essentially the same meaning as てしかたがない. One difference is that てならない is difficult to use with words that do not indicate emotion, feeling, or desire.

（×）赤ちゃんが朝から泣いてならない。／The baby has had to be crying since morning.

（○）赤ちゃんが朝から泣いてしかたがない。／The baby has been crying his eyes out since morning.

A somewhat old-fashioned expression that is most often used in written language.

<< 【てはいられない】 | Home | 【てはどうか】 >>

【てはだめだ】

1. V-てはだめだ〈prohibition〉

（1）駐車場 で遊 んではだめだ。出 て行 きなさい。／You can’t play in the parking lot. Please leave.

（2）「その花 をとってはだめよ。」と姉 が弟 に言 った。／“You mustn’t pick that flower,” she told her brother.

（3）文句 ばかり言 っていてはだめだ。自分 でなんとかしろ。／Don’t just complain. Do something on your own.

（4）こんなところでへばってはだめだ。あと1キロだ。しっかりしろ。／You can’t collapse at this point. There’s just one more kilometer to go. Pull yourself together!

（5）「今 、あの人 を叱 ってはだめです。もうすこし様子 を見 ましょう。」と彼女 は部下 をかばった。／“It won’t do to reprimand him now. Let’s wait a little longer and see what happens,” she said, coming to the defense of her subordinate.

（6）そんな浅 いところから、飛 び込 んではだめだ。／You must not dive from such a shallow place.

Expresses prohibition. Often used by people in a supervisory position, such as teachers, parents, and managers, when they are speaking to someone being supervised. Often reduced from では to じゃ, or from ては to ちゃ. Same as V-てはいけない.

2. ...てはだめだ

［N／Na　ではだめだ］

［A-くてはだめだ］

［V-ていてはだめだ］

（1）写真 をとるのに、こんなに暗 くてはだめだ。／It’s too dark here for taking photos.

（2）秘書 になりたいそうだが、言葉 がそんなにぞんざいではだめだ。／She says she wants to be a secretary, but her rough way of speaking is a real problem.

（3）富士山 へ登 りたいのなら、そんな靴 ではだめです。登山靴 をはきなさい。／If you want to climb Fuji-san (Mt. Fuji), those shoes are no good. Wear climbing boots.

（4）今 でもお母 さんに洗濯 してもらっているんですか。それではだめです。自立 したかったら、自分 でやりなさい。／Are you still having your mother do your wash? That’s no good! If you want to be independent, do it yourself.

（5）君 のように遊 んでばかりいてはだめだ。学生 は勉強 しなくてはいけない。／You can’t just fool around and have fun all the time. Students have to study!

Expresses the judgment that under a certain condition, it will be impossible to attain a certain goal. The goal is sometimes expressed in words, and sometimes only alluded to in the context. Often used in conversation. The contracted forms じゃ（あ）だめだ and ちゃ（あ）だめだ are also used.

As in (5), this form may also be combined with verbs to create the construction V-ていてはだめだ, which is used to state that the present situation is unacceptable and to criticize or reprimand someone.

<< 【ではない】 | Home | 【ではないか2】 >>

【ではないか1】

［N／Na／A／V　ではないか］

Attaches to plain forms and expresses surprise on the part of the speaker, or the intention to press the addressee for acknowledgement. With nouns or the dictionary form of na-adjectives, ではないか can be attached directly without using だ. However, for non-dictionary forms, だった／ではない／ではなかった must be inserted.

This is a fixed expression consisting of the negative interrogative form of だ, and it has the tone of written language or a somewhat formal situation. Usually used by men. In casual conversation, men use the form じゃないか and women the forms じゃない or じゃないの. The form じゃん, which is even more casual, is used by both sexes. In polite language, the forms ではないですか and ではありませんか are used. Always appears in the dictionary form and cannot be used in the ta-form; this, as well as the fact that it cannot be combined with だろうか are what distinguish it from ではないか2.

1. ...ではないか〈surprise, discovery〉

（1）やあ、大野 君 ではないか。／Well, if it isn’t Ono-kun!

（2）これはすごい、純金 ではないか。／This is really something—pure gold, right?

（3）なんだ、中身 、空 っぽではないか。／What’s this? There’s nothing inside it, is there?

（4）この店 の料理 、結構 おいしいではありませんか。／Wouldn’t you say that this restaurant has pretty good food?

（5）このレポートなかなかよくできているではありませんか。／This report really is actually rather good, isn’t it.

Expresses surprise at an unanticipated discovery. If the discovery is something desirable, then ではないか conveys a favorable impression, as in (4) and (5). If the discovery is contrary to one’s expectations, then the meaning is disappointment or discouragement, as in (3).

2. ...ではないか〈criticism〉

（1）A:悪 いのは君 のほうではないか。／Aren’t you the one who’s really at fault?

B:僕 はそうは思 いませんが。／I don’t see it that way.

（2）A:病人 を連 れ出 したりしたら、だめじゃないか。／Don’t you think it’s a bad idea to take a sick person out on a jaunt?

B:はい、これから気 をつけます。／Yes, I’ll be more careful from now on.

（3）A:おそかったじゃないか。／You’re late, aren’t you?

B:あの、道 が混 んでいたんです。／Well, the traffic was really bad.

（4）A:まずいじゃありませんか、そんな発言 をしては。／Isn’t there going to be trouble if you say that?

B:そうですか。／You think so?

（5）A:はじめにそう言 ってくれなくては困 るではないか。／We could have avoided a lot of trouble if you had told us that at the beginning.

B:すみません、気 がつかなくて。／I’m sorry, I wasn’t thinking.

Used to reproach or criticize an addressee of the same or lower status. The purpose is to make the addressee acknowledge properly that s/he is responsible for an undesirable state of affairs. Used with falling intonation.

3. ...ではないか〈confirmation〉

（1）A:同級生 に田中 さんという女 の子 がいたじゃないか。／Wasn’t there a girl in your class named Tanaka-san?

B:ああ、髪 が長 くてやせた子 ね。／Oh yes, a thin girl with long hair.

（2）A:あそこに、郵便局 が見 えるじゃないですか。／You can see the post office over there, right?

B:ええ。／Yes.

A:あの手前 の角 を右 に曲 がってください。／At the corner just before it, please turn right.

（3）地下道 などによくいるではありませんか。ああいう男 が。／Aren’t they usually in places like underground passageways— that kind of man?

Used to remind the listener of a person or thing s/he already knows, or to bring attention to something that can be seen or heard at the present location. Since this usage is associated with a desire to confirm that the listener has understood, it is often spoken with rising intonation, and it can be substituted with other expressions of confirmation such as だろう and でしょう.

Because this usage is almost exclusively conversational, the form ではないか is actually not used very often. The forms じゃないか, じゃありませんか, and じゃないですか are used instead.

4. V-ようではないか

（1）このクラスみんなでディベート大会 に申 し込 もうではないか。／Why don’t all of us in this class apply for the debate contest?

（2）とにかく、最後 まで頑張 ってみようではないか。／Anyway, can’t we give it our best right up to the end?

（3）遠 くからはるばる来 たのだから、お金 の心配 などしないで十分 楽 しもうではないか。／Since we’ve come all this way, let’s not worry about money and things, let’s just enjoy ourselves!

（4）売 られた喧嘩 だ。受 けて立 とうじゃないか。／They’re asking for a fight. What’s to stop us from taking the challenge?

Attached to the intentional form of a verb, this is used to suggest joint action or to express strongly one’s personal intention. A slightly formal expression, ordinarily used by males.

<< 【ではないか1】 | Home | 【ではないだろうか】 >>

【ではないか2】

［N／Na　（なの）ではないか］

［A／V　のではないか］

Although this form can be attached directly to nouns or to na-adjectives without inserting の, in the case of i-adjectives and verbs, の must be inserted, resulting in the form のではないか. This point distinguishes ではないか2 from ではないか1. In casual speech, men use （ん）じゃないか and women use forms such as （ん）じゃない and んじゃないの. The polite forms are （の）ではないですか and （の）ではありませんか.

1. ...（の）ではないか

（1）あそこを歩 いているのは、もしかして山下 さんではないか。／Might that be Yamashita-san walking over there?

（2）こんな大 きなアパートは一人 暮 らしにはちょっとぜいたくではないか。／Isn’t such a big apartment a little too luxurious for someone who lives alone?

（3）もしかしたら、和子 は本当 は良雄 が好 きなのではないか。／Isn’t it possible that Kazuko is really in love with Yoshio?

（4）この話 は結局 ハッピーエンドになるのではないか。／It looks like this story might just wind up with a happy ending.

（5）ファーストフード産業 が伸 びれば伸 びるほどごみも増 えるのではないか。／As the fast food industry gets bigger and bigger, won’t that just create more trash?

（6）この品質 でこの値段 は、ちょっと高 いのではないか。／Isn’t this price a little steep for something of this quality?

（7）これからますます環境 問題 は重要 になるのではないか。／Won’t environmental problems become even more and more serious from now on?

Attached to expressions in the plain form, this expresses a conjecture on the part of the speaker, with the sense of “I can’t say for certain, but isn’t it likely that....” The speaker’s degree of conviction is lower than in the case of だろう.

2. ...（の）ではないかとおもう

（1）こんなうまい話 は、うそではないかと思 う。／I have a hard time believing such a good deal to be true.

（2）どちらかというと妹 さんの方 がきれいなのではないかと思 う。／If I had to say, I think the younger sister is probably the prettier of the two.

（3）話 がうますぎるので、山田 さんは、これは詐欺 ではないかと思 ったんだそうです。／The deal was too good to be true, so apparently Yamada-san thought it was most likely a scam.

（4）もしかすると、彼女 はこの秘密 を知 っているのではないかと思 う。／I think that there’s a good chance she might know the secret.

（5）この条件 はわれわれにとって不利 ではないかと思 われる。／This condition might possibly work to our detriment.

This construction is formed by attaching 思う to ではないか. When the dictionary form 思う is used, it always expresses the speaker’s judgment; when 思った is used, as in (3), the judgment of a third-person subject can be expressed. The form 思われる, which is used in (5), has the tone of written language. This form is often used for the purpose of softening what would otherwise sound like a strong or dogmatic opinion; it does not necessarily mean that the speaker is in doubt of something.

<< 【ではないだろうか】 | Home | 【ではなかろうか】 >>

【ではなかったか】

［N／Na　（なの）ではなかったか］

［A／V　のではなかったか］

This is essentially a written language expression used to make conjectures about a past condition or to complain about a difference between the past and present. In spoken language, forms such as （ん）じゃなかったか (men) and （ん）じゃなかったの (women) are used.

1. ...（の）ではなかったか〈conjecture〉

（1）古代人 にとってはこれも貴重 な食物 ではなかったか。／Was this not also an important food for ancient peoples?

（2）昔 はここもずいぶん閑静 だったのではなかったか。／Isn’t it true that a long time ago this place was extremely quiet?

（3）当時 のわが家 の暮 らしは、かなり苦 しかったのではなかったか。／Wasn’t it true that our family was struggling financially at that time?

（4）当時 の人々 は人間 が空 を飛 ぶなどということは考 えもしなかったのではなかったか。／I wouldn’t imagine that the people of that time ever thought humans would fly through the sky.

An expression used to make a conjecture about something in the past. While it is similar to ...た（だ）ろう, the form ではなかったか conveys less conviction on the part of the speaker. With the exception of cases such as the one shown in (1), it usually follows the ta-form of a predicate and takes the form ...たのではなかったか. Essentially synonymous with ではなかっただろうか and ではなかったろうか.

2. ...（の）ではなかったか〈contrary to expectations〉

（1）昔 はとなり近所 の人々 は互 いにもっと協力的 ではなかったか。／In the past, didn’t neighbors used to be much more cooperative with each other?

（2）あなたたちは規律 を守 ると誓 ったのではなかったか。／Didn’t you pledge to obey the regulations?

（3）これまでは平和 に共存 してきたのではなかったのか。／Haven’t they co-existed peacefully until now?

（4）これからは一家 が平和 に暮 らしていくのではなかったか。／Wasn’t it the intent of the family to live a peaceful life from now on?

Expresses to the listener a feeling of criticism, dissatisfaction, or regret regarding an undesirable state of affairs in the present that is different from the past. のではなかったか is used in written language. As in (3), it can also take the form ではなかったのか. When used with the dictionary form of a verb, as in (4), means “though something should have been done, in reality it wasn’t.”

<< 【てみる】 | Home | 【でも1】 >>

【ても】

［N／Na　でも］

［A-くても］

［V-ても］

A combination of the te-form of a predicate and も. For nouns and na-adjectives, it becomes でも. In informal spoken language, the forms たって and だって are also used.

1. ...ても〈converse condition〉

（1）この仕事 は、病気 でも休 めない。／I can’t take time off from this job even if I get sick.

（2）その車 がたとえ 10 万 円 でも、今 の私 には買 えない。／Even if that car cost only 100,000 yen, I’m not in a position to buy it now.

（3）不便 でも、慣 れた機械 の方 が使 いやすい。／It’s easier to use a machine that you’re used to, even if it’s a little inconvenient.

（4）風 が冷 たくても平気 だ。／Even if the wind is cold, it doesn’t bother me.

（5）ほしくなくても、食 べなければいけない。／Even if you don’t want to, you have to eat something.

（6）国 へ帰 っても、ここの人々 の親切 は忘 れないだろう。／Even after I return home, I don’t think I’ll ever forget the kindness of the people here.

（7）今 すぐできなくても、がっかりする必要 はない。／You don’t have to be discouraged if you can’t do it right away.

（8）わたしは、まだ勉強 不足 だから、今 試験 を受 けても受 からないだろう。／I still haven’t studied enough, so if I took the test now, I doubt I’d pass.

（9）たとえ両親 に反対 されても彼 との結婚 はあきらめない。／Even if my parents are against it, I’m not going to give up on marrying him.

Expresses a converse condition that negates the resultative conditional “If X happens, then Y results” (XならばY). For example, the ...ても constructions in (1) and (6), respectively, negate the relationship between the conditions “If I get sick, I can take time off” and “After I return home, I’ll forget the kindness of the people here”; these express that even if condition X arises, condition Y will not result. Example (9) shows how the adverb たとえ is sometimes used with this construction.

2. ...ても〈parallel condition〉

Presents two or more conditions and expresses that no matter which condition is realized, the outcome will be the same.

a. ...ても

（1）2を二乗 すると4になりますが、－2を二乗 しても4になります。／If you square 2 you get 4, and if you square minus 2 you also get 4.

（2）飛行機 で行 くと料金 は片道 2万 円 ぐらいですが、新幹線 で行 っても費用 はだいたい同 じです。／The fare for a one-way plane ticket is about 20,000 yen, but going by shinkansen (bullet train) costs about the same.

（3）A:演奏会 、あと 20 分 で始 まるんですが、タクシーで行 けば間 に合 うでしょうか。／The concert starts in about twenty minutes—can I still make it if I take a taxi?

B:会場 は駅 の近 くですから、歩 いて行 っても間 に合 うと思 いますよ。／The hall is near the station, so I think you can make it in time even if you walk.

When two clauses expressing different conditions that yield the same outcome are presented sequentially, as in XならばZ and YならばZ, the second conditional clause is expressed with ても, in the form Y（であっ）てもZ. Since this construction conveys the meaning that either condition will yield the same result, it can be rephrased as XてもYてもZ.

（例）2を二乗しても、－2を二乗しても4になります。／Either squaring 2 or squaring minus 2 will yield 4.

b. ...ても...ても

（1）うちの子供 はニンジンでもピーマンでも好 き嫌 いを言 わないで食 べます。／Our child isn’t picky—she’ll eat carrots and green peppers and everything.

（2）天気 がよくても悪 くても、雨 が降 っても風 がふいても、新聞 配達 の仕事 は休 めない。／Whether the weather is good or bad, whether the rain falls or the wind blows, delivering newspapers is a job that doesn’t allow for holidays.

（3）道 を歩 いてもデパートへ入 っても人 でいっぱいだ。／Whether I walked on the streets or went into department stores, there were crowds of people everywhere.

（4）辞書 で調 べても先生 に聞 いても、まだこの文 の意味 が理解 できない。／Even after consulting my dictionary and asking my teacher, I still don’t understand what this sentence means.

（5）スポーツをしても映画 を見 ても気 が晴 れない。／Even playing sports or watching movies doesn’t lift my spirits.

The construction XてもYても (...ても) Z juxtaposes two (or more) conditions and conveys the meaning that either (or any) one of them will yield the same result.

c. V-てもV-なくても

（1）今回 のレポートは出 しても出 さなくても、成績 には全 く影響 ありません。／Your grade will not be affected at all, regardless of whether or not you submit this report.

（2）全員 が参加 してもしなくても、一応 人数分 の席 を確保 しておきます。／Whether everyone comes or not, I will at least make sure there are enough seats for all the members.

（3）1日 ぐらいなら食 べても食 べなくても体重 はたいして変化 しない。／Eating or not eating for just one day won’t change your weight that much.

In forms like ...してもしなくても, this juxtaposes an affirmative condition with a negative one to express the idea that, whichever the case, the outcome will not change.

d. V-てもV-ても

（1）このズボンは洗 っても洗 っても汚 れが落 ちない。／I’ve washed and washed these pants but still can’t get them clean.

（2）宿題 が多 すぎて、やってもやっても終 わらない。／I have so much homework that even though I work and work I’m still never finished.

（3）働 いても働 いても、暮 らしは全然 楽 にならない。／No matter how hard I work, it never gets easier to make a living.

The same verb is repeated in order to emphasize that, no matter how much effort one makes, the desired outcome cannot be obtained. Although the final clause is usually a negative expression, there are cases, as shown below, when an affirmative expression may follow. Even in these cases, however, the implication is that the outcome is undesirable.

（例）追い払っても追い払ってもついてくる。／No matter how often I chase it away, it keeps on following me.

（例）雑草は取っても取ってもすぐ生えてくる。／I weed and weed, but they grow back in no time at all.

3. 疑 問 詞 ...ても

When question words such as 何, どこ, だれ, どれ, いつ, and どう are used with a ても conditional, the meaning is that, no matter what the condition is, the resulting situation is inevitable. (When a negative form follows, it means that the situation will fail to occur.)

a. いくら...ても

（1）いくら華 やかな職業 でも、つらいことはたくさんある。／No matter how spectacular the occupation, there will be many difficult challenges.

（2）いくら高 い車 でも、使 わなかったら宝 のもちぐされだ。／However expensive a car may be, if you don’t use it, it’s a waste of a valuable possession.

（3）給料 がいくらよくても、休日 のない職場 には行 きたくない。／No matter how good the salary is, I don’t want to work at a place where there are no days off.

（4）いくら騒 いでも、ここは森 の中 の一軒家 だから大丈夫 だ。／This is the only house in the middle of a forest, so you can make as much noise as you want.

（5）いくらお金 を貰 っても、この絵 は絶対 手放 せない。／No matter how much money I might get for it, I’ll never give up this picture.

（6）このビデオの会話 は、いくら聞 いてもよく分 からない。／I can’t understand the conversation on this video, no matter how many times I listen to it.

いくらXても expresses that the frequency or degree of an action or situation is very great. Used to say that, although this is a powerful condition, it has no effect on the realization of a outcome.

The outcome is usually contrary to anticipation or expectation. For example, in (1), the expectation that “If you have a spectacular occupation, it must always be enjoyable” is contradicted by the second clause “...there will be many difficult challenges.” In (6), the resulting situation is “I still don’t understand,” which runs counter to the expected outcome “If I listen to this video many times, I should be able to understand it.”

b. どんなに...ても

（1）このコンピューターはどんなに複雑 な問題 でも解 いてしまう。／This computer can solve any problem, no matter how complex.

（2）どんなにつらくても頑張 ろう。／I will keep on trying, no matter how hard it gets.

（3）どんなに熱心 に誘 われても、彼女 はプロの歌手 にはなりたくなかった。／No matter how fervently she was scouted, she did not want to become a professional singer.

（4）どんなに大 きい地震 がきても、この建物 なら大丈夫 だ。／No matter how big an earthquake may hit, this building is safe.

（5）妻 はわたしがどんなに怒 っても平気 である。／My wife stays calm, no matter how angry I get.

Usage is the same as いくら...ても (Usage a) above. どんなに can be replaced by いくら, but the latter is more conversational.

c. 疑 問 詞 ...ても

（1）だれが電話 して来 ても、取 りつがないでください。／No matter who calls, please don’t put them through.

（2）どんな仕事 でも、彼 は快 く引 き受 けてくれる。／He readily agrees to do any kind of work.

（3）本 は、どこで買 っても同 じ値段 だ。／Books are the same price wherever you buy them.

（4）あの人 はいつ見 ても美 しい。／She’s beautiful no matter when you see her.

（5）何 をしても、あのショックが忘 れられない。／Whatever I do, I can’t forget the shock I felt.

Means どのような場合でもY (no matter what the situation is, Y holds true). No matter what element is linked to the question word, this expresses that the end result will always be situation Y (or, in the case of a negative form, that it will always fail to be Y).

d. どうV-ても

（1）どう言 ってみても、彼 の決心 を変 えさせることはできなかった。／No matter how I put it, I couldn’t find a way to make him change his mind.

（2）どう計算 してみても、そこへ着 くまで 10 時間 はかかる。／No matter how you calculate, it’s going to take ten hours to get there.

（3）どうがんばっても、前 を走 っている三人 を追 い抜 くのは無理 だと思 った。／I thought that, no matter how hard I tried, it was going to be impossible for me to overtake the three runners in front.

Uses a verb of intentional action to express that, no matter what measures are taken, the outcome will not meet one’s expectations.

e. なん+助 数 詞 +V-ても

（1）何回 聞 いても名前 が覚 えられない。／However many times I hear them, I can’t remember names.

（2）この論文 は何度 読 み返 しても、理解 できない。／No matter how many times I re-read this paper, I can’t make sense of it.

（3）何回 話 し合 っても、この問題 は簡単 には解決 できないだろう。／This is not a problem that will be easily solved, no matter how many times we talk about it.

（4）あの店 の料理 は何度 食 べてもあきない。／I never get tired of the food at that restaurant, no matter how often I eat it.

（5）あの映画 は何回 見 ても面白 い。／That movie is always fun to watch.

Uses an action verb to express the notion that no matter how many times the action is done, the outcome is still the same. The outcome expressed in the last part of the sentence is often contrary to expectation, as in (1)-(3). However, it can sometimes be a desirable situation, as in (4) and (5).

4. ...ても...ただろう

（1）たとえ、努力 しても合格 できなかっただろう。／I don’t think I could have passed even if I’d tried.

（2）彼 は頭 がいいので、努力 しなくても合格 できただろう。／He’s really smart, so he probably could have passed without much effort.

（3）人 をだまして金儲 けをするような商売 では、たとえ成功 しても両親 は喜 んでくれなかっただろう。／In a business where you earn money by deceiving people, I doubt that my parents would have been happy for me even if I’d succeeded.

This is a counter-factual conditional that negates the propositional relation XしていたらYしていただろう (if someone had done X, then s/he probably would have done Y). In the form XしてもYしなかっただろう (even if someone had done X, s/he probably wouldn’t have done Y), it is used to state the assumption that even if X had happened, it would have had no effect on the fact that Y did not happen.

For example, (1) denies the conditional relationship in the resultative counter-factual conditional “If he had worked hard, then he probably would have passed” (which means he didn’t work hard and thus failed). (1) means “He did not actually work hard, but even if he had, the result probably still would have been failure.” (2) negates the resultative counter-factual conditional “If he hadn’t worked hard, then he probably wouldn’t have passed” (which means he actually did work hard and thus passed). (2) means “He did work hard, but even if he hadn’t, the result probably still would have been success.”

5. ...ても...た

（1）雨 でも運動会 は行 われた。／The sports meet was held even though it rained.

（2）頭 が痛 くても学校 を休 まなかった。／He didn’t miss school even when he had headaches.

（3）ドアは強 く押 しても開 かなかった。／The door wouldn’t open, even when I pushed hard on it.

（4）いくら待 っても彼女 は現 れなかった。／No matter how long we waited, she didn’t show up.

（5）この本 は難 しすぎて、辞書 を引 いて読 んでも、ほとんど理解 できなかった。／This book was too difficult—I could hardly understand any of it, even reading it with a dictionary.

The construction XてもYた, which uses the ta-form at the end of the sentence, expresses the fact that both X and Y happened. For example, (1) means “it rained, but the sports meet was held.” While the ても form used here is similar in meaning to が, けれども, or のに, when ても is used after an action verb, it conveys the nuance that the action was repeated, or that although the action was carried out to an extreme degree, the anticipated outcome was not obtained. Thus, in sentences like (4), which include いくら, it is not possible to replace ても with が, けれども, or のに.

（×）いくら待った｛が／けれど／のに｝彼女は現れなかった。／We waited how long, {but/however/even though} she didn’t show up.

6. V-てもR-きれない

（1）彼 の親切 に対 しては、いくら感謝 してもしきれない。／I cannot thank him enough for all of his kindness.

（2）学生 時代 になぜもっと勉強 しておかなかったのかと、悔 やんでも悔 やみきれない。／There is no limit to the regret I feel that I didn’t study harder during my school days.

（3）ここで負 けたら、死 んでも死 にきれない。／I can’t bear to die if we lose now.

The same verb is repeated to emphasize its meaning. For example, (1) shows deep appreciation, and (2) emphasizes a strong sense of regret. This construction is rather idiomatic, and the range of verbs that can be used is limited. 死んでも死にきれない in (3) is a strong expression of being unable to give up on something or feeling deep regret.

7. V-てもどうなるものでもない

（1）いまから抗議 してもどうなるものでもない。／Raising an objection now won’t accomplish anything.

（2）もう一度 彼 に会 ってもどうなるものでもないと彼女 は思 った。／She concluded that even if she met with him one more time, it would still be pointless.

（3）性格 は直 らないのだから、あの人 に説教 してもどうなるものでもない。／His personality can’t be mended, so even giving him a lecture will accomplish nothing.

Means that even if some action is attempted, it will not lead to a solution. Conveys a feeling of resignation.

8. V-たくてもV-れない

（1）急 に仕事 が入 って、飲 みに行 きたくても行 けないのだ。／Some urgent business has come up, so however much I want to go out drinking, I can’t.

（2）きらいな先生 の前 では、泣 きたくても泣 けない。／I couldn’t cry in front of a teacher I hate, even if I wanted to.

（3）医者 に止 められているので、甘 いものは食 べたくても食 べられない。／No matter how much I want to, I can’t eat sweets, since my doctor has told me not to.

An idiomatic expression that combines the ても form of V-たい with the negative form of a V-れる potential verb. Means “even if I want to, I cannot.” Used to emphasize that circumstances do not allow a certain action, or to make an excuse.

9. ...てもいい→【てもいい】

10. ...てもかまわない→【てもかまわない】

11. ...てもさしつかえない→【てもさしつかえない】

12. ...てもしかたがない→【てもしかたがない】

13. ...てもみない→【てみる】5、【てみる】6

14. ...てもよろしい→【てもよろしい】

<< 【てもかまわない】 | Home | 【てもしかたがない】 >>

【てもさしつかえない】

［N／Na　でもさしつかえない］

［A-くてもさしつかえない］

［V-てもさしつかえない］

（1）無理 をしなければ運動 をしてもさしつかえありません。／If you don’t strain yourself, you may do some exercise.

（2）ひとりかふたりのお客 さまなら、人数 を変更 なさってもさしつかえありません。／There is no problem changing the number of guests, if it’s only one or two people.

（3）この書類 ははんこがなくてもさしつかえない。／This document doesn’t need to have your seal.

（4）最終的 に決定 するのに、全員 の意見 が聞 けなくてもさしつかえはないと思 う。／I think it’s still all right to make the final decision, even if we can’t listen to everyone’s opinion.

Used in the forms てもさしつかえない and なくてもさしつかえない. An expression of concession which means that the condition indicated by ても is acceptable or presents no difficulties. さしつかえはない is also used. Close in meaning to てもいい and てもかまわない, but usually used in more formal situations than these two.

<< 【てもさしつかえない】 | Home | 【でもって】 >>

【てもしかたがない】

［N／Na　でもしかたがない］

［A-くてもしかたがない］

［V-てもしかたがない］

（1）このレポートでは、やりなおしを命 じられても仕方 がない。／With this report, it’s no wonder I’ve been ordered to do it over again.

（2）あんないいかげんな練習 では、一回戦 で負 けてもしかたがない。／With such sloppy practice, it’s no wonder they lost the first match.

（3）あんなに雪 が降 っては、時間 通 りに着 けなくてもしかたがない。／With that heavy a snowfall, it can’t be helped if they don’t arrive on time.

（4）これだけたくさんの人 がいては、彼女 がみつけられなくても仕方 がない。／With this many people around, it’s no surprise we can’t find her.

（5）チームの選手 にけが人 が多 かったから、今回 は最下位 でもしかたがない。／There were a lot of injured players on the team, so ending up in last place this time was unavoidable.

（6）買 い物 にいくひまがないから、今夜 のパーティーは古 い服 でもしかたがない。／I don’t have time to go shopping, so I’ll have to wear something old to the party tonight.

（7）このところ雨 ばかりだから、ビアガーデンのお客 が少 なくてもしかたがない。／The small number of customers at the beer gardens is to be expected, with all the rain we’ve had recently.

（8）この辺 は便利 だから、マンションの値段 が高 くても仕方 がない。／This is a convenient location, so it’s no wonder the condominiums are pricey.

Used in both the forms てもしかたがない and なくてもしかたがない. Means that a situation is unfortunate or unsatisfactory, but there is no other choice but to accept it. The cause or reason that brought about the situation at hand is often stated by adding ては to the end of the preceding clause.

<< 【てん】 | Home | 【と2】 >>

【と1】

［N／Na　だと］

［A-いと］

［V-ると］

Attaches to the dictionary form of a predicate. Although it is usually used with plain forms, in polite language it is also used in the form ですと or ますと. Expresses the relation that the second event is realized because of the condition created by the first event.

1. ...と〈generic condition〉

（1）あまり生活 が便利 だと人 は不精 になる。／People become lazy when lifestyles are too convenient.

（2）気温 が低 いと桜 はなかなか咲 かない。／If the temperatures are low, it takes a long time for the cherry blossoms to bloom.

（3）酒 を飲 むと顔 が赤 くなる。／His face turns red if he drinks alcohol.

（4）春 が来 ると花 が咲 く。／When spring comes, flowers bloom.

（5）水 は 100 度 になると沸騰 する。／Water boils when it reaches 100 degrees Celsius.

（6）気温 が急 に下 がると霧 が発生 する。／Fog forms when the temperature drops suddenly.

（7）だれでも年 をとると昔 がなつかしくなるものだ。／All people wax nostalgic over the past as they get older.

（8）生活 が安定 すると退屈 になるし、不安定 すぎるとストレスがたまる。／When life is stable, it gets boring, and if it’s too unstable, it causes stress.

（9）月 にかさがかかると翌日 は雨 になる。／When the moon has a halo, it will rain the next day.

（10）来年 のことを言 うと鬼 が笑 う。／Don’t count your chickens before they’re hatched (lit. If you talk about next year, the devil will laugh).

（11）夜爪 を切 ると親 の死 に目 に会 えない。／If you cut your nails at night, you’ll never say your last goodbyes to your parents (lit. If you cut your nails at night, you won't be able to see your parents at the time of their death).

Expresses a conditional relationship that applies not to a specific person or thing, but to people or things in general. Means “if X happens, then Y is inevitable.” The end of the sentence is always in dictionary form, and ta-forms, conjectural forms, and so on are not possible. As in (7), sometimes と is combined with ものだ, which signifies that a certain characteristic is intrinsic to the thing or situation at hand.

Often used to express a relationship in which the event stated in the second clause occurs automatically or spontaneously after the event in the first clause. Thus, this pattern is often used to state laws of nature. Both (10) and (11) are proverbial expressions.

2. ...と〈repetition, habit〉

Expresses repeated habits or actions of a particular person or thing. Often accompanied by adverbs such as 必ず(invariably), いつも(always), 毎年(every year), or よく(often). Unlike the generic condition expressed in Usage 1, this usage concerns a particular subject, and either the dictionary form or ta-form may be used at the end of the sentence.

a. ...と...る

（1）おじいさんは天気 がいいと裏山 に散歩 にでかける。／Grandfather strolls in the hills behind our house whenever the weather is fine.

（2）兄 は冬 になると毎年 スキーに行 く。／My older brother goes skiing every year when winter comes.

（3）隣 の犬 は私 の顔 を見 るといつもほえる。／The dog next door barks every time she sees my face.

（4）私 は面白 いコマーシャルを見 るとすぐその製品 を買 いたくなるくせがある。／Whenever I see an interesting commercial, I tend to want to buy the product right away.

（5）お酒 を飲 むといつも頭 がいたくなる。／I always get a headache when I drink alcohol.

（6）キーボードを2時間 たたくと肩 がこる。／I get stiff shoulders whenever I type on a keyboard for two hours.

（7）彼女 はストレスがたまるとむやみに食 べたくなるのだそうだ。／I heard that whenever she’s under stress, she wants to eat a lot.

（8）僕 がデートに遅 れると彼女 は必 ず不機嫌 になる。／My girlfriend always gets upset when I’m late for a date.

（9）彼 は給料 が入 ると飲 みに行 く。／He goes out drinking whenever he gets paid.

Indicates the repetition of a present habit or action of a particular person or thing. The dictionary form of a predicate is used at the end of the sentence.

b. ...と...た（ものだ）

（1）子供 のころ天気 がいいと、この辺 を祖母 とよく散歩 をしたものだ。／When I was a child, if the weather was nice, I often used to take walks with my grandmother around here.

（2）日曜日 に一家 で買 い物 に出 ると、必 ずデパートの食堂 でお昼 を食 べた。／When my family went shopping together on Sundays, we always ate lunch in the department store cafeteria.

（3）祖母 のところに行 くと必 ずおこづかいをもらったものだ。／Whenever I went to my grandmother’s, I always got some spending money.

（4）学生 のころは、試験 が始 まると胃 が痛 くなったものだ。／When I was a student, as soon as exams started I would always get a stomach ache.

（5）北海道 のおじさんが遊 びに来 ると娘 たちはいつも大喜 びをした。／My daughters were always overjoyed whenever their uncle from Hokkaido came to visit.

（6）あのころは一日 働 くと、一 ヶ 月 遊 んで暮 らせたものだ。／At that time, I could goof off for a month on just one day’s work.

The ta-form of a predicate is used at the end of the sentence to express the repetition of a past habit or action of a particular person or thing. Often accompanied by the phrase たものだ, which expresses reminiscence.

3. ...と〈yet-to-be-realized condition〉

a. ...と+未 実 現 のことがら

（1）ここをまっすぐ行 くと右手 に大 きな建物 が見 えます。／If you go straight here, you’ll see a large building on your right.

（2）このボタンを押 すとドアは開 きます。／If you push this button, the door will open.

（3）この小説 を読 むと世界観 が変 わるかもしれません。／Your view of the world may change if you read this novel.

（4）雨天 だと明日 の試合 は中止 になります。／If it rains, then tomorrow’s match will be canceled.

（5）これを全部 計算 すると、総費用 はだいたい100万円 になります。／If you calculate all this, the total cost is about a million yen.

（6）動 くと撃 つぞ。／Move and I’ll shoot!

（7）そんなに食 べると太 るよ。／You’ll gain weight if you eat that much.

（8）真面目 に勉強 しないと卒業 できないよ。／If you don’t study hard, you won’t graduate, you know.

（9）生活 がこんなに不安定 だと落 ち着 いて研究 ができない。／When my livelihood is this uncertain, I can’t concentrate on my research.

（10）こんなにおいしいといくらでも食 べてしまいそうだ。／When it’s this delicious, I could eat as much as there is.

Used to say that “if/when X occurs, then Y will occur,” with respect to a particular person or thing. The Y clause always expresses an unrealized situation, but the X clause may express either an unrealized situation or one that has already come about.

(1)-(6) are cases in which X has not been realized, and (7)-(10) are cases in which X has already been realized. (6) is a threat directed at an addressee who is on the verge of moving. In this situation it would also be possible to say 動いたら撃つぞ (If you move, then I’ll shoot), but the use of と implies that both actions will occur virtually simultaneously, giving the threat more impact than when it is expressed with the たら form. (7) and (8) are ways to warn or admonish someone who is overeating and someone who is lax about studying, respectively.

The Y clause may be followed by expressions to emphasize a fact, or expressions of conjecture such as だろう or かもしれない. However, expressions meant to exert an effect on the other party, including commands, requests, and invitations, cannot be used. V-よう intentional forms cannot be used either.

（×）雨天だと明日の試合は中止しよう。／When it’s rainy, let’s cancel tomorrow’s match.

（○）雨天なら明日の試合は中止しよう。／If it rains, let’s cancel tomorrow’s match.

Since と conveys a strong implication that a condition has already been realized or is very likely to be realized in the future, there is a tendency to avoid combining it with the word もし, which signifies a hypothetical situation.

（×）もし雨天だと試合は中止になります。／Supposing when it rains, the match will be canceled.

（○）もし雨天なら試合は中止になります。／If it rains, the match will be canceled.

b. ...と+疑 問 詞 ...か

（1）A:お酒 を飲 むとどうなりますか。／What happens if you drink alcohol?

B:顔 が赤 くなります。／My face turns red.

（2）A:51 を3で割 るといくつになりますか。／What do you get if you divide 51 by 3?

B:17 になります。／It’s 17.

（3）A:この道 をまっすぐ行 くと、どこに出 ますか。／Where does this road lead to, if we follow it straight ahead?

B:国道 1号線 に出 ます。／It leads to National Highway No. 1.

This is like the form するとどうなるか (if such-and-such is done, what is the outcome?). と is followed by an interrogative clause such as どうなるか or 何があるか, which contains a question word and a verb that expresses some kind of unintentional action, such as change or existence. Expressions denoting actions that are consciously controllable, such as どうするか, cannot be used unless they indicate a habitual behavior or characteristic.

（×）水は 100 度になるとどうしますか。／What will you do when water reaches a temperature of 100 degrees Celsius?

（○）水は 100 度になるとどうなりますか。／What happens when water reaches a temperature of 100 degrees Celsius?

The particle と is similar to the pattern するとどうなるか in that the focus of the question is usually on the second half of the sentence. It is difficult to use in patterns like どうするとそうなるか, where the focus of the question is on the first half of the sentence. In these cases, it is more natural to use ば or たら rather than と.

（×）どうするとドアは開きますか。／What do you do then the door opens?

（○）どう｛すれば／したら｝ドアは開きますか。／What should be done so that the door opens?

4. ...と...た〈already-realized condition〉

The situations specified before and after と are previously-realized conditions. Typically, the ta-form appears in sentence-final position, but in novels and other literary works, the dictionary form is sometimes used to express the historical present. In almost all cases, a verb is used both before and after this expression. Often used in stories and novels. In conversation, たら is more commonly used.

a. ...と...た〈trigger〉

（1）教 えられた通 りまっすぐ行 くと、つきあたりに郵便局 があった。／When I went straight down the road I had been shown, there was a post office at the end.

（2）駅 に着 くと、友達 が迎 えに来 ていた。／When I arrived at the station, my friend was already there to meet me.

（3）トンネルを出 ると、そこは銀世界 だった。／Passing through a tunnel brought us into a winter wonderland.

（4）お風呂 に入 っていると、電話 がかかってきた。／It was while I was sitting in the bath that the telephone rang.

（5）街 を歩 いていると、見知 らぬ男 が声 をかけてきた。／When she was walking about the town, a strange man called to her.

（6）夜 になると急 に冷 え込 んできた。／When evening came, it suddenly turned cold.

（7）午後 になるとだいぶ暖 かくなった。／When afternoon came, it became much warmer.

（8）ベルを鳴 らすと、女 の子 が出 て来 た。／When I rang the bell, a young girl came out.

（9）仕事 をやめるとたちまちお金 がなくなった。／When I quit my job, my money ran out in no time.

Expresses a relationship between two situations, such as when the occurrence of the first situation makes the speaker aware of the second, or the first situation is a trigger that brings about the second. (1), (2), and (3) show that as soon as the first action is carried out, the speaker “discovers” the second situation. (4) and (5) are scenarios in which a new situation arises while the first action is taking place. In (6) and (7), the first half of the sentence expresses a time-related condition that leads to the realization of the second situation. (8) and (9) express a relation in which the first action triggers the occurrence of the second one.

In all cases, the second situation must be part of the same overall situation as the first one, and it must also be something the speaker can observe from the outside. The following example describes an internal physical sensation of the speaker. Here the particle と is not possible, and たら must be used instead.

（×）昨夜この薬を飲むと、よく効いた。／On taking this medicine last night, it worked really well.

（○）昨夜この薬を飲んだら、よく効いた。／When I took this medicine last night, it worked really well.

In almost all cases, a verb is used in both clauses. However, when this pattern is used to express the discovery of a situation, a predicate noun or adjective may conclude the second sentence, as shown in (3) above and the example below.

（例）外に出ると、予想以上に寒かった。／On going outside, I found it much colder than I had imagined.

b. ...と...た〈successive events〉

（1）男 はめざまし時計 を止 めると、またベッドへ戻 った。／After shutting off his alarm clock, the man climbed back into bed.

（2）わたしは、東京駅 へ着 くとその足 で会社 へ向 かった。／After reaching Tokyo Station, I continued on to the office.

（3）母 は受話機 を置 くと、ためいきをついた。／After putting down the receiver, Mother let out a sigh.

Expresses a situation in which the same person performs two actions in succession, the first one leading to the second. Both actions are intentional. Although the ta-form is usually used at the end of the sentence, in stage directions for things like screenplays the dictionary form may be used, as below.

（例）《シナリオ》良雄は、手をふくと、ギターを手に取る。／《script》Yoshio wipes his hands, then picks up the guitar.

The <successive events> usage of と is often found in novels or stories. With this usage, たら is unnatural, and it is almost never possible to use たら instead of と. This と can be replaced by the te-form of the verb, but it is not always possible to replace the te-form of the verb with と. For example, the te-form can be used to link three or more successive actions, but と cannot be used to do so.

（×）父は家に帰ると、ご飯を食べると、すぐ布団に入った。／When my father came home, when he ate dinner, he soon got into bed (lit. his futon).

（○）父は家に帰って、ご飯を食べて、すぐ布団に入った。／My father came home, ate dinner, and soon got into bed.

While the te-form expresses successive actions that are part of the same situation, と divides one situation into two parts. It is used to depict, from an external point of view, the change that arises as the first situation switches into the second one.

5. ...とすぐ

（1）彼 はうちへ帰 るとすぐテレビのスイッチを入 れる。／As soon as he gets home, he turns on the TV.

（2）放送局 は、駅 を降 りて右 へ曲 がるとすぐです。／The broadcasting station is just after you take the first right from the station.

（3）うちへ帰 るとすぐテレビのスイッチを入 れた。／I turned on the TV as soon as I got home.

（4）彼 らは土地 の開発 許可 が降 りるとすぐ工事 にとりかかった。／As soon as they got the land development permit, they started construction.

（5）彼女 は大学 を卒業 するとすぐ結婚 した。／She got married right after she graduated from college.

（6）スポーツをやめるとすぐ太 り出 した。／As soon as he stopped playing sports, he started to put on weight.

This is a combination of the conditional expression と and the adverb すぐ. It means that a first event is followed immediately by the occurrence of a second.

6. ...と〈introductory utterance〉

（1）正直 に言 うと、そのことについてはあまりよく分 からないのです。／To be honest, I really don’t know very much about that.

（2）母 に言 わせると、最近 の若者 は行儀 が悪 くなっているようだ。／If you ask my mother, apparently young people these days have worse manners.

（3）本当 のことを申 し上 げますと、手術 で助 かる見込 みは 50 パーセント以下 ではないかと思 います。／If I may speak frankly, I think the chances of success for this operation may be less than fifty percent.

（4）実用的 な点 からみると、あまり使 いやすい部屋 ではない。／Looking at it from the point of view of practicality, it’s not a very easy-to-use room.

（5）今 となって考 えてみると、彼 の言 うことももっともだ。／Looking back on it now, what he said was also on the mark.

（6）昨年 に比 べると、今年 は桜 の開花 がちょっと遅 いようだ。／Compared with last year, this year the cherry blossoms seem to be coming into bloom a little later.

When と is used after verbs of utterance, thought, or comparison, such as 言う (say), 見る (see), 考える (think), or 比べる (compare), it functions as an introductory expression indicating the viewpoint or stance from which the thing that follows will be stated. In this usage, と can often be substituted with the forms たら, ば, and なら.

7. ...からいうと→【からいう】1

8. ...からすると→【からする】1

9. ...からみると→【からみる】1

10. ...てみると→【てみる】3

11. ...というと→【というと】

12. ...となると→【となると】

13. ...ともなると→【ともなると】

14. ...によると→【によると】

15. V-ようとV-まいと→【よう2】4

<< 【とあいまって】 | Home | 【といい】 >>

【とあって】

1. ...とあって

［Nとあって］

［Vとあって］

（1）今日 は三 連休 とあって、全国 の行楽地 は家族 連 れの観光客 で賑 わいました。／Since today is part of a three-day holiday, the nation's leisure spots are bustling with family vacationers.

（2）一年 に一回 のお祭 りとあって、村 の人 はみんな神社 へ集 まっていた。／This being the only festival of the year, the villagers all gathered at the shrine.

（3）めったに聞 けない彼 の生演奏 とあって、狭 いクラブは満員 になった。／As he rarely performed live, the tiny club was filled to capacity.

（4）大型 の台風 が接近 しているとあって、どの家 も対策 におおわらわだ。／With the huge typhoon drawing near, every household was frantic with preparations.

（5）名画 が無料 で見 られるとあって、席 ははやばやと埋 まってしまった。／Since the famous film could be seen for free, every seat was soon filled.

Means “due to such-and-such a situation.” Used to indicate special circumstances and implies that a statement of something that will naturally occur under those circumstances, or a statement of an action that should be taken, will follow. A written language expression used in news broadcasts and so on.

2. ...とあっては

（1）伊藤 さんの頼 みとあっては、断 れない。／Since it's a request from Ito-san, I cannot refuse.

（2）彼 が講演 するとあっては、何 とかして聞 きに行 かねばならない。／He’s the one giving the lecture, so I have to find some way to go hear it.

（3）高価 なじゅうたんが定価 の一割 で買 えるとあっては、店 が混雑 しないはずがありません。／With such an expensive carpet being sold for a tenth of its list price, I wouldn't expect the store not to be packed with people.

（4）最新 のコンピューター機器 がすべて展示 されるとあっては、コンピューターマニアの彼 が行 かないわけがない。／With all the latest computer equipment on display, there's no way a computer geek like him wouldn't go.

Means “because this is the situation.” Used for special circumstances and is followed by a statement of something that will naturally occur under those circumstances, or a statement of an action that should be taken. For example, (1) would be used in a situation where a refusal is unthinkable because Ito-san is a very important person to the speaker. Although this is a somewhat formal expression, it can be used in spoken language.

<< 【とあって】 | Home | 【といい...といい】 >>

【といい】

［N／Na　だといい］

［A-いといい］

［V-るといい］

Formed by combining と1 (Usage 3) with いい. とよい is a slightly more formal form.

1. V-るといい〈suggestion, recommendation〉

（1）この株 は今 買 うといいですよ。／It's good to buy this stock now.

（2）分 からないときは、この辞書 を使 うといい。／When you don’t understand, this dictionary is helpful.

（3）旅行 には、小 さいドライヤーを持 っていくといい。／Taking a small blow-dryer on trips is a good idea.

（4）疲 れたようだね。仕事 は急 がなくてもいいから、ソファで少 し寝 るといい。／You seem tired. Since this work is not urgent, you should lie down on the sofa for a while.

（5）私 を疑 いたければ存分 に疑 うといい。／If you want to doubt me, then go ahead and doubt!

Follows the dictionary form of a verb and expresses the notion of encouraging another person to take an action. Depending on the context, it can also be used to express a hands-off attitude, as in (5), which has the sense of “do as you like.” Cannot be used to dissuade someone from taking an action. In such cases, the form V-ないほうがいい is used.

（×）今買わないといい。／It’s good not to buy it now.

（○）今買わないほうがいい。／You shouldn't buy it now.

Similar expressions include たらいい and ばいい, but といい implies the encouragement that “generally speaking, doing such-and-such is appropriate.” The form といい cannot be used in interrogative expressions inquiring what one ought to do. In that case, たらいい／ばいい are used instead. When answering such questions, however, it is possible to use not only たらいい／ばいい but also といい. Then たらいい／ばいい convey the meaning that “such-and-such would be sufficient” to obtain a particular result. On the other hand, といい means that “such-and-such is generally an appropriate course of action.”

（×）うまくいかない時はどうするといいですか。／What’s good to do when things don't go well?

（◯）A:うまくいかない時はどう｛したら／すれば｝いいですか。／A：When things don't go well, what should I do?

B:山本さんに｛聞いたら／聞ければ／聞くと｝いいですよ。／It would be best to ask Yamamoto-san.

2. ...といい〈wish, desire〉

（1）生 まれてくる子供 が、女 の子 だといいなあ。／It would be nice if the baby on the way is a little girl.

（2）学生 がもっと積極的 だといいのだが。／How I wish the students would take a little more initiative!

（3）勉強 部屋 がもっと広 いといいのになあ。／If only this study room were a little more spacious....

（4）旅行 の間 、晴天 が続 くといい。／Let's hope that the fair weather holds during the trip.

（5）彼 が時間 に間 に合 うといいんだけど。／I hope that he makes it in time, but....

（6）みんながこのことを忘 れていないといいが。／You would all do well never to forget this.

（7）学生 の自発的 な活動 が今後 も継続 されるといい。／It would be nice to see these voluntary activities by the students continue.

Expresses a desire for something to happen. Often used with が, けど, のに, or （のに）なあ at the end of the sentence. When accompanied by が, けど, or のに, the implication is concern that “such-and-such may not be realized,” or that the present state of affairs does not reflect what is hoped for. Has essentially the same meaning as たらいい and ばいい, and can be substituted with these in almost all cases.

3. ...とよかった（のに）

（1）A:とても楽 しい旅行 だったわよ。あなたも来 るとよかったのに。／It was a very enjoyable trip. It would have been nice if you had come along.

B:行 けるとよかったんだけど、急用 ができてしまってね。／It would have been great to be able to go, but something suddenly came up.

（2）本当 のことを言 ってくれるとよかったのに。／If only you had told me the truth.

（3）この部屋 、もう少 し日当 たりがいいとよかったんだが。／I wish this room could have had a little more sunlight.

Expresses a feeling of regret or criticism of the listener, arising from the fact that something did not actually happen or that the present reality is contrary to expectations. This usage takes the forms ばよかった or たらよかった more often than とよかった. The sentence often concludes with expressions such as のに, のだが, or のだけれど. However, のに is not usually used regarding one's own actions.

（×）僕も行けるとよかったのに。／I should have been able to go, too....

（○）僕も行けるとよかったん｛だけど／だが｝。／If only I had been able to go, too....

<< 【という2】 | Home | 【ということ】 >>

【というか】

1. ...というか

（1）そんなことをするなんて、ほんとに馬鹿 というか、困 った人 だ。／That he would do something like that means he’s really a fool, or maybe I should say troublemaker.

（2）この決断 は、勇気 があるというか、とにかく凡人 にはなかなかできないことだ。／This decision is one that shows courage, or at any rate, it would be pretty hard for just an ordinary person.

（3）持 っていたお金 を全部 あげてしまうとは、人 がいいというか、びっくりさせられた。／You could say she’s a wonderful person to give all her money away, or whatever, but it certainly surprised me.

Used to make a parenthetical statement of an impression or judgment about a person, event, etc. Means something like “for example, it’s possible to say something like this.” Often followed by a statement of overall evaluation.

2. ...というか...というか

（1）そんなことを言 うなんて、無神経 というか、馬鹿 というか、あきれてものもいえない。／That he would say something like that makes him either an insensitive clod or an idiot and leaves me utterly speechless.

（2）彼女 の行動 は大胆 というか、無邪気 というか、みんなを困惑 させた。／Her actions were bold or perhaps naive, but everyone was baffled by them.

（3）そのときの彼 の表情 は、悲壮 というか、雄々 しいというか、言葉 にはしがたいものがあった。／His expression at the time was somewhere between tragic and dauntless—a little hard to describe in words.

（4）そのほめ言葉 を聞 いたときのわたしの気持 ちは、うれしいというか、恥 ずかしいというか、何 とも説明 しがたいものだった。／My feelings at hearing such words of praise were somewhere between happy and embarrassed—it’s really hard to explain.

Used for thinking out loud about an impression or opinion of a person or event. Often followed by a statement of overall evaluation.

<< 【というところだ】 | Home | 【というのも】 >>

【というのは】

1. というのは

（1）駅前 の開発 計画 が急 に取 りやめになった。というのは、地域 住民 の強硬 な反対 で、マスコミまでが騒 ぎだしたからだ。／The development plans for the area in front of the station were suddenly canceled. The reason for this was the stubborn opposition of local residents, which led to a furor in the mass media.

（2）申 しわけありませんが、来週 お休 みをいただけないでしょうか。というのは、国 から母 が突然 訪 ねてくることになったんです。／I am really sorry, but could I possibly have some time off next week? I’m asking this because my mother will be making an unexpected trip here from my hometown.

（3）A:あしたのご都合 はいかがですか。／How is your schedule tomorrow?

B:あしたはちょっと都合 が悪 いんです。というのは、東京 に出 かけることになっているものですから。／Tomorrow is not really convenient for me. It’s because I am already scheduled to go to Tokyo.

This expression links to the preceding sentence and is used to explain the cause or reason for the situation described in that sentence, or to add a supplementary statement of the rationale for the speaker’s judgment, etc. The subsequent sentence, which starts with というのは, often ends with expressions such as からだ or のだ.

Although というのは is similar to なぜなら, なぜなら is used in cases of an obvious cause-effect relationship, while というのは does not necessarily require a clear cause-effect relationship when it is used to provide a supplementary explanation about a certain situation. Also, なぜなら is a written language expression, while というのは is most often used in spoken language.

2. ...というのは...ということだ

（1）レイさんが少 し遅 くなるというのは一時間 は遅 れるということだ。／That Ray-san is going to be slightly delayed means he’ll be an hour late.

（2）この地方 全体 で雨 が一時間 に10 センチ降 るというのは、洪水 が起 こるということだ。／A rainfall of ten centimeters in just one hour over this entire region means that there will be floods.

This expression is synonymous with ということは...（ということ）だ.

→【ということ】3

3. ...というのはNのことだ

（1）パソコンというのはパーソナルコンピューターのことだ。／Pasokon means a personal computer.

（2）十五夜 というのは、満月 の出 る夜 のことだ。／The term juugoya refers to a night with a full moon.

Used to present a definition, explanation, or interpretation of the meaning of a word, phrase, or sentence.

<< 【というより】 | Home | 【といえなくもない】 >>

【といえど】

1. ...といえど

（1）この寺院 では、一国 の王 といえど、靴 をはいたまま入 ることは許 されない。／At this temple, even if you’re the king of a country, you’re still not allowed to enter wearing shoes.

（2）暦 の上 では春 といえど、この土地 の人々 はいまだ真冬 の寒 さにふるえている。／While the calendar may say it is spring, the inhabitants of this region are still shivering in midwinter cold.

Same as といえども.

2. ...といえども

（1）冬山 はベテランの登山家 といえども遭難 する危険 がある。／Even for veteran mountaineers, winter climbing still carries the danger of mishaps.

（2）スポーツマンの家田 さんといえども風邪 には勝 てなかったらしい。／Even a sportsman like Ieda-san apparently could not defeat a common cold.

（3）その機密 は厳重 に管理 されており、たとえ、部長 といえども近 づくことは禁 じられている。／That secret information is strictly guarded, and even if you’re a department head, you’re not allowed to get close to it.

（4）弘法大師 といえども字 を間違 えることがあるのだから、少々 の失敗 にくよくよすることはない。／Even the great Kobo Daishi made mistakes with his Chinese characters, so there’s no reason to fret over just a little flub.

This is an expression of concession that highlights someone’s or something’s qualifications or abilities and then presents a situation counter to the expectation that “with those qualifications/abilities, surely X should be possible.” Used in formal spoken language, as well as in novels and other types of written language. Can be substituted with でも.

<< 【といえなくもない】 | Home | 【といけない】 >>

【といえば】

1. Nといえば

（1）川口 さんといえば、どこへ行 ったのか、姿 が見 えませんね。／Now that you mention Kawaguchi-san, where has she gone? I don’t see her here, do you?

（2）高木 さんといえば切手 というぐらい、彼 の収集熱 は有名 だ。／If you say “Takagi-san,” it’s almost the same as saying “stamps”—that’s how well-known his obsession with collecting them is.

（3）森町 といえば、昔 から木材 の産地 だが、最近 は温泉 が吹 き出 して話題 になっている。／Speaking of the town of Mori, it’s been a lumber production area since long ago, but recently people are talking about it because of the new hot spring that’s gushed up.

This expression is used to take a certain topic and describe what it brings to mind, add further explanation about it, etc. It is also possible to say というと.

2. ...といえば...が

（1）おっとりしているといえば、聞 こえがいいが、彼女 は何 をするのものろい。／If you say that she’s easygoing, it sounds good, but really she is slow at everything.

（2）緑 が豊 かだといえば、いい所 だと思 うが、実際 は遠 くて行 くのが大変 だ。／You might think it’s a wonderful place when you hear about the abundant green forests, but the fact is that it’s far away and really hard to get to.

（3）一日 に一回 は部下 をどなりつけるといえば、こわい上司 だと思 われるが、実際 はみんなにしたわれている。／When you hear that she yells at her subordinates at least once a day you might think she’s an intimidating boss, but the truth is that everyone adores her.

Used to state two contrasting evaluations. Means that if you consider things from the viewpoint of statement X, normally evaluation Y would result, but in fact the result is Z, a contrasting evaluation.

3. ...といえば...かもしれない

（1）彼 らはビートルズの再来 だといえば、ほめすぎかもしれない。／To say that they’re the next Beatles might be making too much of them.

（2）この議会 は今 までで最低 だといえば、問題 があるかもしれない。／If they say this is the worst assembly ever, there might be a problem.

（3）この作品 が時代 の流 れを変 えるといえば、あまりにおおげさかもしれないが、実際 に見 ればその素晴 らしさがわかるだろう。／Saying that this work (of art) would change the course of the times might be too much of an exaggeration, but you’ll understand how splendid it is if you actually see it.

This is a roundabout way of expressing an evaluation. The second clause lessens the impact of the evaluation given in the first. The evaluation in the first clause is often what the speaker wants to claim, and a statement that affirms and further develops this evaluation often follows the second clause, as in (3).

4. ...といえば...ぐらいのことだ

（1）わたしの得意 なことといえば、ビールの早 飲 みぐらいのことだ。／If I have to say something I’m good at, the only thing is chugging beer.

（2）町 の名所 といえば、小 さい古墳 が残 っているぐらいのことだ。／The only famous site left in this town is just a small ancient burial mound.

（3）うちの子供 のとりえといえば、動物 をかわいがるぐらいのことだ。／What are our child’s good points? I guess I could say that he’s kind to animals.

Used to say that the topic at hand (a person or thing) does not have many outstanding features. Often used to make self-effacing statements about oneself.

<< 【といったらありゃしない】 | Home | 【といって】 >>

【といったらない】

［Nといったらない］

［A-い（とい）ったらない］

（1）花嫁 衣装 を着 た彼女 の美 しさといったらなかった。／Wearing her bridal costume, she was indescribably beautiful.

（2）みんなが帰 っていったあと、一人 きりで病室 に取 り残 されたときの寂 しさといったらなかった。／Left all by myself in the hospital room after everyone had gone home, my loneliness was beyond description.

（3）彼 は会議中 にまじめな顔 をして冗談 を言 うんだから、おかしいったらないよ。／The way he tells jokes with a straight face during our meetings is too funny for words.

（4）結婚 以来 今 まで 10 年 も別居 せざるをえなかった妻 とやっと一緒 に暮 らせるのだ。うれしいといったらない。／Ever since we got married ten years ago, my wife and I have had to live apart, and now we can finally be together. I can't tell you how happy I am!

Attached to nouns or i-adjectives to emphasize an extreme degree of something. Means “so...that it can’t be expressed in words” or “there is nothing else as...as.” In spoken language, the form ...ったらない may also be used. Although といったらありはしない conveys the same meaning as といったらない, the former is used only when expressing a negative evaluation of something (dissatisfaction, criticism, etc.).

<< 【どうじに】 | Home | 【どうぜん】 >>

【どうせ】

1. どうせ

（1）どうせ私 は馬鹿 ですよ。／After all, I'm a fool.

（2）三日 坊主 の彼 のことだから、どうせ長続 きはしないだろう。／He can never stick to anything, so I don't expect this to last anyway.

Expresses an attitude of resignation or carelessness on the part of the speaker, in the sense that regardless of what s/he does, the conclusion or outcome is foregone and cannot be changed by the will or effort of an individual. Often followed by the description of an undesirable situation.

2. どうせ...（の）なら

（1）どうせやるならもっと大 きいことをやれ。／If you’re going to do it, then do something bigger.

（2）どうせ参加 しないのなら、早 めに知 らせておいたほうがいい。／If you’re not going to attend anyway, you ought to tell them early.

（3）どうせ2か月 余 りの命 なら、本人 のやりたいことをやらせたい。／If she only has about two months left to live, I want to let her do anything she wants.

（4）急 いでもどうせ間 に合 わないのだったら、ゆっくり行 こう。／If we can’t get there on time even if we hurry, let’s take our time.

Means “if such-and-such an outcome will follow in any case” and is used to state an attitude or action that should be taken under such circumstances. The phrase ...のだったら may also be used. Followed by an expression that indicates the speaker’s effort to influence the addressee through his/her will, hope, obligation, command, or invitation.

3. どうせV-るいじょう（は）

どうせV-るからには

（1）やる以上 は必 ず成功 して戻 ってこい。／If you’re going to do it, then make sure you succeed before you return.

（2）どうせ試合 に出 るからには、必 ず優勝 してみせる。／Since I’m going to compete in the match, I’ll show you a victory.

（3）どうせ留学 するからには、博士号 まで取 って帰 ってきたい。／As long as I’m going to study abroad, I'd like to go all the way and bring home a doctorate.

Means “such-and-such an action has been predetermined, so....” Followed by an expression of the speaker's will, hope, obligation, command, or invitation with respect to the addressee.

4. どうせ...のだから

（1）どうせ間 に合 わないのだから、いまさらあわてても仕方 がない。／Since we aren’t going to make it in time anyway, there’s no point in scrambling now.

（2）どうせ合格 するはずがないのだから、気楽 にいこう。／Since there isn’t any chance that I’ll pass the exam anyway, I’m just going to take it easy.

（3）どうせやらなければならないのだから、早 めにやってしまいましょう。／Since we have to do it anyway, let’s get it out of the way early.

Used to express the speaker’s intention or judgment regarding a situation with a foregone conclusion or outcome. Often followed by an expression that indicates the speaker’s attitude of resignation or carelessness regarding the situation.

5. どうせ（のこと）だから

（1）どうせのことだから、飛 び切 り高級 なホテルに泊 まろう。／Since we have to stay somewhere, let’s stay at a really posh hotel.

（2）どうせのことだから、駅 までお送 りします。／Since I’m going that way anyway, I’ll drive you to the station.

（3）当分 バスも来 ないみたいだし、どうせだからお茶 でも飲 まない？／It looks like there won’t be a bus for awhile, so as long as we’re here, would you like to get something to drink?

An idiomatic expression that means “in any case, doing...is a foregone conclusion, so....” Often followed by expressions of intention or invitation, such as 思い切って...しよう (I’m going to/let’s take the plunge and do such-and-such) or ついでに...しよう (I’m going to/let’s do such-and-such along with something else). In spoken language, the form どうせだから is often used.

<< 【とうてい...ない】 | Home | 【どうにか】 >>

【とうとう】

1. とうとうV-た

（1）夏休 みもとうとう終 わってしまった。／Summer vacation has finally come to an end.

（2）長 い間 入院 していた祖父 も、とうとう亡 くなった。／After a long period of hospitalization, my grandfather finally passed away.

（3）卒業式 も無事 に終 わって、とうとう国 に帰 る日 になった。／His graduation successfully behind him, the day to return to his home country had come at last.

（4）20 年 の歳月 をかけて、研究 はとうとう完成 した。／After some twenty years of effort, the research was at last completed.

（5）相手 があまりにしつこいので、温厚 な彼 もとうとう怒 ってしまった。／The other person’s extreme persistence finally drove him to anger, though he was usually so easy-going.

（6）朝 から曇 っていたが、夕方 にはとうとう雨 になった。／It had been cloudy since morning, and when evening came, it finally began to rain.

Expresses that something has been realized ultimately or after spending a lot of time on it. (1)-(3) indicate that a long passage of time or a process was undergone before an anticipated final stage was reached. (4) indicates that persistent effort over a long period of time has led to the final result. Implies the speaker’s deep emotion regarding the events or time leading up to the outcome.

Also, as shown in (5) and (6), とうとう is sometimes used when a situation that was maintained for a length of time passes a certain limit. (5) means “a man who usually doesn’t get angry could no longer control his ire,” and (6) means “it had been threatening to rain since morning, and although it held off during the daytime, in the evening it started to rain.”

Similar expressions include やっと (at long last) and ついに (finally/in the end).

For details, refer to やっと (Usage 1).

2. とうとう...V-なかった

（1）二時間 も待 ったが、とうとう彼 は来 なかった。／We waited for two hours, but in the end he never showed up.

（2）何週間 も捜索 が続 けられたが、遺体 はとうとう発見 されなかった。／The search continued for several weeks, but ultimately the body was never found.

（3）全力 をあげて調査 が行 われたが、事故 の原因 はとうとう分 からなかった。／An all-out investigation was conducted, but the cause of the accident was never determined.

Used when an anticipated situation ultimately fails to come about. The expression ついに can be used in the same way, but やっと does not take this pattern.

<< 【とおす】 | Home | 【とおり】 >>

【とおもう】

1. ...かとおもうほど

（1）彼 は、いつ寝 ているのかと思 うほどいそがしそうだ。／He seems so busy that it makes me wonder when he sleeps.

（2）その家 は、ほかに金 の使 い道 を思 いつかなかったのだろうかと思 うほど、金 のかかったつくりだった。／That house cost so much to build that it makes me wonder if they couldn't think of any other ways to spend their money.

（3）その人 のあいさつは、永遠 に終 わらないのではないかと思 うほど長 いものだった。／That person’s opening remarks were so long that we wondered if they might go on forever.

（4）死 んでしまうのではないかと思 うほどの厳 しい修行 だった。／The training was so rigorous that we wondered if it might kill us.

Means “so outrageous that it makes people wonder such-and-such.” The form Xかと思うほど（の）Y is used to emphasize the high degree of Y. Sometimes the form ...かと思うほどだ is also used, as in the following example.

（例）彼はいそがしい。いつ寝ているのかと思うほどだ。／He is busy. So much so that it makes me wonder when he sleeps.

2. ...かとおもえば

a. V-るかとおもえば

（1）勉強 しているかと思 えば漫画 を読 んでいる。／There she was reading comic books, when I thought she was studying!

（2）来 るかと思 うと欠席 だし、休 むかと思 うと出席 している。／When I think he’ll come, he’s absent, and when I think he'll be absent, he attends.

（3）今年 こそ冷夏 と思 えば、猛暑 で毎日 うだるような暑 さだ。／Just when I thought we’d have a cool summer this year, there’s a heat wave and every day is a scorcher.

The forms V-るかとおもえば and V-るかとおもうと are used to express that the present situation is contrary to the speaker’s expectations. Since these express that an unexpected situation occurs repeatedly and/or that the present situation is contrary to expectation, they are typically followed by the dictionary form at the end of the sentence. This usage does not usually take the form かと思ったら.

b. V-るかとおもえば...も

（1）熱心 に授業 に出 る学生 がいるかと思 えば、全然 出席 せずに試験 だけ受 けるような学生 もいる。／There are students who enthusiastically come to class, and there are students who never come to class but just take the final exam.

（2）一日 原稿 用紙 に向 かっていても一枚 も書 けない日 があるかと思 うと、一気 に数 十枚 も書 ける日 もある。／While there are some days when you sit staring at the manuscript paper all day long without being able to write a single page, there are also days when you can dash off dozens of pages at a stretch.

Expresses the parallel existence of conflicting or contrasting situations. Can also take the form V-るかとおもうと. Often verbs of existence like ある, いる, etc. are repeated. While the pattern V-るかとおもえば (see a, above) expresses a gap between expectation and reality, the pattern here doesn’t have such a meaning. It merely presents a comparison between two situations of a different nature.

3. ...からとおもって

（1）体 にいいからと思 って、緑 の野菜 を食 べるようにしています。／I believe it's good for the health, so I make it a point to eat green vegetables.

（2）せっかくパリまで来 たのだからと思 って、一流 レストランで食事 することにした。／I figured that since I’d come all the way to Paris, I should have dinner at a first-class restaurant.

（3）明日 の試験 に遅 れては大変 だからと思 い、今晩 は早寝 することにした。／I know that it would never do to be late for tomorrow's exam, so I’m going to bed early tonight.

Follows a clause and means that an action is or will be taken on account of the reason expressed in that clause. The reason given in the first clause typically expresses something that will happen as a result of the action in the second clause (i.e. the aim of the action). In the second clause, an expression that indicates intentional action is used.

4. ...とおもったら

a. V-たとおもったら

→【とおもう】9b

b. 疑 問 詞 ...かとおもったら

（1）何 を言 うのかと思 ったらそんなくだらないことか。／Who would have thought she would end up saying such a stupid thing?

（2）食事 もしないで何 をやってるのかと思 ったら、テレビゲームか。／I was wondering what he was doing that was so important that he had to skip dinner, and it turned out to be a video game.

（3）会議中 に席 を立 ってどこへ行 くのかと思 ったら、ちょっと空 が見 たいって言 うんだよ。あいつ、最近 おかしいよ。／I was wondering why he stepped out of the meeting, and he said he just wanted to take a look at the sky. That guy’s really been strange lately.

（4）2才 の赤 ん坊 が夢中 で何 かやっている。何 をやっているのかと思 ったら、鏡 にむかってにこにこ笑 ったり、手 をふったりしているのだ。／The two-year-old child was completely absorbed in something. When I went to see what she was doing, I saw her looking into the mirror, grinning and waving.

Expresses that the speaker has directed his/her attention to something that s/he thinks is strange or unusual. The latter part of the sentence expresses an unexpected discovery or a surprising event.

5. ...たいとおもう→【おもう】

6. ...とおもいきや

（1）今場所 は横綱 の優勝 間違 いなしと思 いきや、3日目 にケガで休場 することになってしまった。／I was sure this sumoo tournament would be won by the yokozuna (grand champion), and then on the third day he withdrew because of an injury.

（2）今年 の夏 は猛暑 が続 くと思 いきや、連日 の雨 で冷害 の心配 さえでてきた。／Just when I expected that the heat wave would continue this summer, we had so many days of rain that now there are even concerns about cold-weather damage to the crops.

（3）これで一件 落着 かと思 いきや、思 いがけない反対 意見 で、この件 は次回 の会議 に持 ち越 されることになった。／I thought this would settle the matter, but there was unexpected opposition, so the issue has been tabled until the next meeting.

Follows a clause and means that, although the speaker had expected the outcome expressed in that clause, the actual outcome was, to his/her surprise, the opposite. As in (3), sometimes the particle か appears right before と. A somewhat old-fashioned expression used in written language.

7. ...とおもう→【おもう】

8. ...とおもうまもなく

（1）つめたい雨 が降 ってきたと思 う間 もなく、それは雪 にかわった。／Just as I thought a cold rain had started to fall, it turned to snow.

（2）両目 に涙 があふれてきたかと思 う間 もなく、その子 は大声 で泣 き出 した。／The child’s eyes welled up with tears, and a loud outburst of wailing immediately followed.

（3）帰 ってきたなと思 う間 もなく息子 は「遊 びに行 ってくる！」と叫 んで出 ていった。／I had hardly welcomed my son home when he cried, "I'm going out to play!" and left.

（4）雲 を突 き抜 けたと思 う間 もなく、翼 の下 に、街 の灯 が広 がった。／Just as we broke through the clouds, the city lights spread out beneath the wings of the plane.

Expresses two events occurring in succession without a break in time. Sometimes the particle か appears right before と. Used in written language. In the pattern XかとおもうまもなくY (I hardly thought X had happened when Y occurred), neither the X clause nor the Y clause can express an action done by the speaker.

（×）私はうちに帰ったかと思う間もなく友達に電話した。／I hardly thought I had come home when I telephoned a friend.

（○）私は家に帰るとすぐ友達に電話した。／I telephoned a friend right after arriving home.

9. ...とおもうと

a. V-るかとおもうと

→【とおもう】2a

b. V-たとおもうと

（1）急 に空 が暗 くなったかと思 うと、大粒 の雨 がふってきた。／I had just realized how dark the sky had become when large drops of rain started to fall.

（2）山田 さんたら、来 たと思 ったらすぐ帰 っちゃった。／That Yamada-san went home right after she got here.

（3）さっきまで泣 いていたと思 ったらもう笑 っている。／Until just a moment ago he was in tears, but now there is already a smile on his face.

（4）やっと暖 かくなったかと思 うと、今朝 は突然 の春 の雪 でびっくりした。／I thought it was finally getting warm, so I was surprised this morning at the sudden spring snowfall.

（5）夫 はさっき家 に戻 ってきたかと思 ったら、知 らぬ間 にまた出掛 けていた。／I thought my husband had just come home, but before I knew it, he had gone out again.

（6）今 までニコニコしていたかと思 えば、突然 泣 き出 したりして、本当 に、よく気分 の変 わる人 だ。／Just when you think that up till now she’s been all smiles, all of a sudden she bursts out crying and stuff; really, she’s such a temperamental person.

（7）ちょっとうとうとしたかと思 うと、突然 大 きな物音 がして目 が覚 めた。／Just as I felt myself nodding off, suddenly there was a loud noise and I woke up.

Expresses the successive but virtually simultaneous occurrence of two contrasting situations. The forms V-たとおもったら and V-たとおもえば can also be used, and the form V-たかとおもったら is common too. In many cases, this pattern is followed by an expression that refers to the speaker's shock or surprise. Cannot be used to describe the actions of the speaker him/herself.

（×）私は、うちに帰ったと思うとまた出かけた。／I thought I had just come home when I went out again.

（○）私は、うちに帰って、またすぐに出かけた。／I came home and soon went out again.

10. ...とおもったものの →【ものの】1

11. Nにとおもって

（1）おばあちゃんへのお土産 にと思 って、湯飲 み茶碗 を買 った。／I bought a Japanese teacup as a souvenir for my grandmother.

（2）つまらないものですが、これ、お子 さんにと思 って...。／It’s just a little something I thought your child might like....

（3）健康 維持 にと思 い、水泳 を始 めた。／To keep fit, I started swimming.

Used with nouns that refer to a person or a purpose/goal and means “for that person or purpose.” Followed by an expression of intentional action. Can also be used in the form ...にと思い.

12. ...ものとおもう→【ものとおもう】

13. ...ようとおもう→【おもう】5

<< 【とか2】 | Home | 【とかんがえられる】 >>

【とかく】

1. とかく...がちだ

（1）女 だというだけでとかく軽 く見 られがちだ。／Women tend not to get taken seriously just because of their sex.

（2）年 を取 ると、とかく外 に出 るのがおっくうになるものだ。／When you get older, going out gets to be more and more of a bother.

（3）われわれはとかく学歴 や身 なりで人間 の価値 を判断 してしまう傾向 がある。／We are often inclined to judge a person’s worth according to his or her academic background or personal appearance.

（4）とかく人 の世 は住 みにくいものだ。／Human society is a difficult place to live in.

This expression is accompanied at the end of the sentence by expressions such as ...がちだ (prone to), やすい (easy to...), 傾向がある (there is a tendency to...), ものだ (that’s the way it is). It means “if anything, the general trend seems to be such-and-such.” Typically expresses something that is not very good or desirable. Expressions like ともすれば and ややもすると can be used instead of とかく. Generally used in written language.

2. とかく

（1）先 のことを今 からとかく心配 してもしようがない。／Fretting now over all kinds of things in the future won't accomplish anything.

（2）他人 のことをとかく言 う前 に自分 の責任 をはたすべきだ。／You ought to carry out your own responsibilities before you start saying this, that, and the other thing about other people.

（3）とかくしているうちに時間 ばかり過 ぎていった。（書 きことば的 ）／Meanwhile, time was wasting away. (has the feel of written language)

Expresses the way that someone thinks or talks about all kinds of things. Often implies a negative evaluation of that person’s actions or statements. Slightly literary in tone. In modern Japanese, it is more common to use とやかく.

<< 【ときたひには】 | Home | 【ときているから】 >>

【ときたら】

1. Nときたら

（1）うちの亭主 ときたら、週 のうち3日 は午前様 で、日曜 になるとごろごろ寝 てばかりいる。／That husband of mine—he’s out till after midnight at least three times a week, and then come Sunday, he just lies around the house!

（2）あそこの家 の中 ときたら、散 らかし放題 で足 の踏 み場 もない。／You know that house over there? The inside is so cluttered that there's no place to stand!

Used by the speaker to introduce a certain person or situation as the topic of conversation and then state an evaluation of that person/situation. The topic is someone or something that is well-known to the speaker, and s/he uses ときたら to express a particularly strong emotion or evaluation that s/he has regarding it. Usually followed by expressions that indicate criticism or dissatisfaction, such as 本当にいやになる (I really hate it) or あきれてしまう (I’m shocked). Used mostly in spoken language.

2. ...ときたら

（1）毎日 残業 の後 に飲 み屋 のはしごときたら、体 がもつはずがない。／He works overtime every day and then goes bar-hopping, so there's no way his health could hold up.

（2）働 き者 で気立 てがいいときたら、みんなに好 かれるのも無理 はない。／She’s so hard-working and good-tempered—it's no wonder everyone likes her.

（3）新鮮 な刺 し身 ときたら、やっぱり辛口 の日本酒 がいいな。／If there’s fresh sashimi (raw fish), I’ll go for—what else?—a dry Japanese sake.

（4）ステーキときたらやっぱり赤 ワインでなくちゃ。／When you’re having steak, you’ve got to have red wine!

Used to introduce as the topic of conversation a person, thing, or situation with an extreme characteristic. Means “in this kind of case/situation, of course this is the only thing to do (or the only thing that will happen).” As shown in (3) and (4), this pattern also takes the form NときたらN, in which case it conveys the meaning that “N goes best with N” or “for N, N is the best.”

<< 【どことなく】 | Home | 【ところ2】 >>

【ところ1】

1. Nのところ

（1）今 のところ患者 は小康状態 を保 っています。／At present the patient’s condition is stable.

（2）現在 のところ応募者 は約 100 人 ほどです。／We currently have about 100 applicants.

（3）このところ肌寒 い日 が続 いている。／We’re having a spell of chilly weather these days.

Attaches to nouns denoting the present, such as 今 (now), げんざい (at present), and この... (this...). Expresses a situation as of the present moment, as in “at the present stage, at this point, recently.”

2. V-るところとなる

（1）この政治的 スキャンダルは遠 からず世界中 の人々 が知 るところとなるだろう。／It won’t be long before this political scandal becomes known to people all over the world.

（2）彼 らの別居 はたちまち周囲 の人 の知 るところとなった。／The news of their separation immediately became common knowledge to everyone around them.

Means that a rumor or news becomes common knowledge. Usually used in the form 知るところとなる. Has the tone of written language.

3. V-るところに　よると／よれば

（1）聞 くところによれば、あの二人 は離婚 したそうだ。／According to what I hear, apparently those two have divorced.

（2）現地 記者 の話 すところによると、戦況 は悪化 する一方 のようである。／The reporters on location are saying that the war situation is steadily worsening.

（3）特派員 の伝 えるところによると、アフリカの飢饉 はさらに悪化 しているらしい。／What we hear from the special correspondents is that the famine in Africa seems to be getting even worse.

Uses verbs that denote the output or transfer of information, like 聞く (hear), 話す (speak), or 伝える (tell), and is followed by a clause that specifies the information that has been relayed. The sentence often ends with expressions such as らしい (seem/appear), そうだ (they say/I hear), or とのことだ (so they say). Often used in news reports.

4. V-る／V-ている　ところのN

（1）私 が知 るところの限 りでは、そのようなことは一切 ございません。／As far as I know, that is not the case at all.

（2）彼 が目指 すところの理想 の社会 とは、身分 差別 のないすべての人 が平等 であるような社会 であった。／The ideal society to which he aspired was one in which there is no discrimination according to status but equality among all people.

This expression is a rather direct translation of relative pronouns used in Western languages. In Japanese it is possible to say, for example, 彼の目指す理想の社会 (the ideal society he aspires to), so there is usually no need to use this expression; when it is used, it sounds like a translation. Used mostly in written language.

5. V-るところまでV

（1）堕 ちるところまで堕 ちてしまった。／She sank as low as it was possible for her to sink.

（2）とにかく、行 けるところまで行 ってみよう。／At any rate, let’s try to go as far as we can.

（3）時間内 にやれるところまでやってみてください。／Please try to do as much as you can in the allotted time.

The same verb is used at the beginning and end of this pattern to express the notion that an action or change reaches its utmost limit or an ultimate stage. When the potential form V-れる is used, as in (2) and (3), the meaning is that the action is performed to the greatest extent possible.

6. V-ているところをみると

（1）平気 な顔 をしているところをみると、まだ事故 のことを知 らせられてないのだろう。／From the calm expression on his face, I would guess that he hasn’t heard about the accident yet.

（2）大勢 の人 が行列 しているところを見 ると、安 くておいしい店 のようだ。／Judging from the long line of people, it looks like a good restaurant with reasonable prices.

Used when the speaker is stating a supposition based on firsthand experience. At the end of the sentence, expressions such as らしい (seem/appear), ようだ (like/as if), or にちがいない (must be/without a doubt) are often used. The forms ...ところから and ...ところからみて may also be used.

（例）高級車に乗っているところから、相当の金持ちだと思われる。／Seeing as he drives a luxury car, we can presume he’s quite wealthy.

<< 【ところ1】 | Home | 【どころ】 >>

【ところ2】

1. V-たところ〈resultative〉

（1）先生 にお願 いしたところ、早速 承諾 のお返事 をいただいた。／On making a request of my teacher, I immediately received a reply of consent.

（2）駅 の遺失物 係 に問 い合 わせたところ、届 いているとのことだ。／Upon contacting the lost and found office at the station, I was told that my article had been turned in.

（3）ホテルに電話 したところ、そのような名 前 の人 は泊 まっていないそうだ。／When I called the hotel, I was told that there was no one by that name staying there.

（4）教室 に行 ってみたところが、学生 は一人 も来 ていなかった。／When I went and took a look at the classroom, there wasn't a single student there.

ところ is attached to the ta-form of an action verb to express the occurrence of a situation and the triggering of a discovery. The situations that appear before and after this expression are not in a direct cause-effect relationship; rather, their relationship is something like “when I did..., by chance/it so happened that such-and-such was the case.” The situation in the second clause is a discovery on the part of the speaker that was triggered by the action in the first clause, and this discovery is stated using language that denotes a previously-realized fact. Sometimes ところ is followed by the particle が, as in (4), creating the form V-たところが. In this case, the second clause usually expresses a situation contrary to expectation.

2. V-たところが〈adversative connective〉

（1）親切 のつもりで言 ったところがかえって恨 まれてしまった。／I spoke with the intention of being kind, and instead I find myself being resented.

（2）高 いお金 を出 して買 ったところが、すぐ壊 れてしまった。／I spent a lot of money to buy it, and it broke right away.

（3）仕事 が終 わって急 いで駆 けつけてみたところが、講演 はもうほとんど終 わってしまっていた。／After finishing work I rushed to get there as soon as I could, only to find that the performance was already almost over.

This adversative usage can be replaced by のに (even though) and expresses that an outcome is contradictory to anticipation or expectation. In contrast to the resultative usage shown above, が is usually not omitted.

<< 【ところ2】 | Home | 【ところが】 >>

【どころ】

1. ...どころか

［N／Na（な）　どころか］

［A-いどころか］

［V-るどころか］

（1）病気 どころか、ぴんぴんしている。／We thought she was sick, but there she was in the pink of health!

（2）A:あの人 、まだ独身 でしょう。／That person is still single, right?

B:独身 どころか、子供 が3人 もいますよ。／Far from it! He has three children, you know!

（3）彼女 は静 かなどころか、すごいおしゃべりだ。／She’s hardly the quiet type—she talks nonstop!

（4）A:そちらは涼 しくなりましたか。／Has it cooled off where you are?

B:涼 しいどころか、連日 30 度 を越 える暑 さが続 いていますよ。／Just the opposite! It isn't cool at all—the heat continues day after day, with temperatures over thirty degrees!

（5）風雨 は弱 まるどころか、ますます激 しくなる一方 だった。／The wind and rain did not abate but, on the contrary, continued to increase in intensity.

（6）この夏休 みはゆっくり休 むどころか、仕事 に追 われどおしだった。／This summer vacation has been anything but relaxing—I’ve been swamped with work the whole time!

Attaches to nouns, adjectives, etc. When used with na-adjectives, as in (3), the na is sometimes inserted, but it can also be omitted. The fact stated after どころか is the exact opposite of what was stated before it. Used to state a fact that completely overturns the anticipations or expectations of the speaker or listener.

In (2), for example, Speaker B doesn’t just say “No, s/he isn’t” in response to Speaker A’s assumption that the person in question “is single”; instead, Speaker B tells Speaker A that the person actually “has three children,” with the effect of thoroughly refuting Speaker A’s original assumption.

2. ...どころか...ない

［...どころか...さえ（も）...ない］

［...どころか...も...ない］

［...どころか...だって...ない］

（1）最近 の大学生 の中 には、英語 どころか日本語 の文章 さえもうまく書 けない者 がいる。／These days there are some college students who can’t even write well in Japanese, let alone English!

（2）旅行先 で熱 を出 してしまい、見物 どころか、温泉 にも入 れなかった。／I came down with a fever on the trip, so I never even got to bathe in the hot spring, let alone go sightseeing!

（3）彼女 の家 まで行 ったが、話 をするどころか姿 も見 せてくれなかった。／I went all the way to her house, but she wouldn’t even come to the door, let alone speak to me.

（4）A:今夜 お暇 ですか。／Do you have some free time this evening?

B:暇 などころか、食事 をする暇 さえありませんよ。／Free time? I don’t even have time to eat supper!

（5）お前 のような奴 には、1万円 どころか1円 だって貸 してやる気 はない。／I wouldn’t lend one yen to someone like you, let alone 10,000 yen!

The meaning and conjunctive use of this expression correspond to those of 1 (see above). どころか is followed by expressions of negation such as さえ(も)...ない, も...ない, and だって...ない to express not only that the average standard or expectation will not be met, but also that one far easier or far lower will not be met, either.

(1), for instance, means that although it is generally expected that Japanese university students should have the ability to use English as a foreign language, some students have such a severe lack of writing ability that they cannot even write properly in Japanese, which should be easier for them than English.

3. ...どころではない

［Nどころではない］

［V-ているどころではない］

（1）この1か月 は来客 が続 き、勉強 どころではなかった。／I’ve had a string of visitors this past month, so I haven’t done much studying.

（2）こう天気 が悪 くては海水浴 どころではない。／This kind of bad weather puts a stop to any swimming in the sea.

（3）仕事 が残 っていて、酒 を飲 んでいるどころではないんです。／I still have work to do, so this is hardly the time to go drinking.

（4）A:今晩 一杯 いかがですか。／How about getting together for a drink tonight?

B:仕事 がたまっていて、それどころではないんです。／I have a pile of work to do, so that’s out of the question.

Attaches to verbs and action nouns to convey the meaning that “this is not a situation or case in which such-and-such can be done.” As in (4), sometimes a demonstrative like それ (that) is used to refer to the previous utterance. Example (4) could be paraphrased as 酒を飲んでいるどころではない, which means “This is not a time to go drinking.”

4. Nどころのはなしではない

Nどころのさわぎではない

（1）受験生 の息子 を二人 もかかえ海外旅行 どころの話 ではありません。／With two sons studying for entrance exams, the last thing we should be talking about is an overseas trip.

（2）こう忙 しくてはのんびり釣 りどころの話 ではない。／As busy as I am right now, this is no time to talk about taking it easy and going fishing!

（3）原子力 発電所 の事故 発生 でバカンスどころのさわぎではなくなった。／The accident at the nuclear power plant put an end to any talk of a vacation.

Used with nouns or action nouns and has essentially the same meaning as Usage 3 above. Implies that “this is no time to be making irresponsible comments like that!”

<< 【どころ】 | Home | 【ところだ】 >>

【ところが】

1. ところが〈contrary to prediction〉

（1）天気 予報 では今日 は雨 になると言 っていた。ところが、少 し曇 っただけで、結局 は降 らなかった。／The weather forecast was for rain today. However, it was only a little cloudy, and we never got any rain after all.

（2）ダイエットを始 めて3週間 になる。ところが、減 った体重 は、わずか1キロだけだ。／It’s been three weeks since I started dieting. But I’ve only lost one measly kilogram.

（3）いつもは8時半 ごろ会社 に着 く。ところが、今日 は交通 事故 に巻 き込 まれ、1時間遅 れで到着 した。／She always gets to work around 8:30 a.m. But today she was involved in a traffic accident and arrived an hour late.

（4）兄 は大変 な秀才 である。ところが弟 は大 の勉強 嫌 いで、高校 を無事 に卒業 できるかどうかも危 ぶまれている。／The older brother is really brilliant. On the other hand, the younger brother absolutely hates to study, and there's concern about whether or not he'll even be able to finish high school.

（5）A:春休 みはゆっくりされているんでしょうね。／I guess you’re taking it easy this spring vacation, right?

B:ところが、締 め切 り原稿 があってそうもしていられないんです。／As a matter of fact, I have an article deadline, so I really can't take it easy at all.

（6）A:来週 のパーティには是非 いらしてくださいね。／Please tell me you’ll come to the party next week!

B:ところが、その日 急 に予定 が入 ってしまったんです。／Actually, something unexpected has come up that I have to do that day.

Used to connect two sentences when the content of the second sentence contradicts or clashes with what is naturally anticipated or expected from the first sentence. Also used when there is a relationship of contrast between two situations, as in (3) and (4). In conversations like (5) and (6), it is used to tell the addressee something like, “That’s what you may think, but the reality is different.” In other words, this usage signals a discrepancy between the other person’s expectations and reality.

In all cases, the sentence after ところが contains an expression that indicates an established fact. Non-factual expressions, including expressions of intention, desire, command, or conjecture, cannot be used. Note the examples of incorrect usage given below.

（×）合格はかなり難しそうだ。ところが、受験してみるつもりだ（意志）／挑戦してみたい（希望）／頑張れ（命令）／ひょっとしたら受かるかもしれない（推量）。／It looks like it will be difficult to pass. However, I intend to try to take the test. (intention)/...I want to take up the challenge. (desire)/...do your best! (command)/...I might just pass after all. (conjecture)

2. ところが〈discovery〉

（1）急 いで家 を出 た。ところが、途中 で財布 を忘 れていることに気 がつき、あわてて引 き返 した。／I left home in a hurry. Then, on the way, I realized I had forgotten my wallet and hurried back.

（2）友人 の家 に電話 した。ところが、1週間前 から海外旅行 に行 って留守 だという。／I called my friend’s house. But I was told that he’s not home because he’s been out of the country on a trip since a week ago.

Used when the speaker is surprised by a new turn of events, or an event that was hard to anticipate from the situation or course of events described in the previous sentence. The sentence after ところが is information newly-discovered by the speaker that contradicts what would naturally be anticipated from the situation described in the previous sentence.

This usage of ところが does not usually allow for substitution with expressions like しかし, けれども, or だが, and when substitution is possible, the meaning of the sentence changes.

<< 【ところが】 | Home | 【ところで】 >>

【ところだ】

1. Vところだ〈phase of a situation〉

ところだ attaches to verbs and is used to report the current status or progress of a situation or event. ところだった expresses that something was at a certain stage in the past. The expression ところだ itself does not usually appear in negative or interrogative forms. The preceding verb does not usually take the negative form, either.

a. V-たところだ

（1）今 帰 ってきたところです。／I just got home.

（2）海外 勤務 を終 え、先月 帰国 したところです。／I finished my overseas assignment and returned home just last month.

（3）電話 したら、あいにくちょっと前 に出 かけたところだった。／When I called, unfortunately she had just stepped out a little earlier.

Expresses the stage immediately after an action or change has taken place. Often used with adverbs that refer to the time immediately preceding, such as 今 (now), さっき (just a moment ago), or ちょっと前 (a little while ago).

b. V-ているところだ

（1）A:もしもし、和雄 君 いますか。／Hello, is Kazuo-kun there?

B:今 お風呂 に入 っているところなんです。／Right now he is taking a bath.

（2）だだ今 電話 番号 を調 べているところですので、もう少々 お待 ちください。／I am looking up that phone number right now, so please wait a few moments.

（3）ふすまを開 けると、妻 は着物 を片付 けているところだった。／When I slid the doors open, my wife was in the middle of putting her kimono away.

Expresses that an action is currently in progress.

c. V-ていたところだ

（1）いい時 に電話 をくれました。私 もちょうどあなたに電話 しようと思 っていたところなんです。／You’ve called at a good time. I was just thinking about giving you a call, too.

（2）思 いがけなくも留学 のチャンスが舞 い込 んできた。そのころ私 は、将来 の進路 が決 められずいろいろ思 い悩 んでいたところだった。／I was unexpectedly blessed with the chance to study overseas. At that time in my life, I couldn’t decide on a future direction and was worrying about all sorts of things.

Expresses that a certain condition has continued from a previous time to the point in time indicated in the sentence. Often used when explaining one’s thinking or psychological condition, to express that it has changed or a new development has come about.

d. V-るところだ

（1）これから家 を出 るところですから、30 分 ほどしたら着 くと思 います。／I am just about to leave home, so I should be there in about thirty minutes.

（2）飛行機 は今 飛 び立 つところだ。／The plane is just about to take off.

（3）A:ご飯 もう食 べた？／Have you already had (breakfast/lunch/supper)?

B:ううん、これから食 べるところ。／No, I’m just about to eat.

（4）家 に戻 って来 ると、妻 は買 い物 に出掛 けるところだった。／When I returned home, my wife was just leaving to go out shopping.

Expresses the stage immediately before an action or change takes place. Sometimes used with adverbs like ちょうど (just now), 今 (now), and これから (after this/now).

2. Vところだ〈counter-factual〉

Expresses a situation counter to reality. Means “if things were different, then such-and-such would be the case.” Often preceded by a conditional clause marked with たら, なら, or ば.

a. ...たらVところだ

（1）昔 だったらそんな過激 な発言 をする人間 は、処刑 されているところだ。／If this were still the old days, people who make such radical statements would be executed.

（2）父 がそのことを知 ったら激怒 するところだ。／If my father found out about that, he would be furious.

（3）先生 がお元気 だったら、今日 のような日 には一緒 に中華料理 でも食 べているところでしょう。／If my teacher were still in good health, on a day like today we would be together eating Chinese food or something.

（4）知 らせていただかなければ、とっくにあきらめていたところです。／If you hadn’t let me know, I would already have given up.

Placed after the dictionary form or ta-form of a verb and preceded by a conditional clause marked by ...ば, ...たら, etc. Expresses that, although the reality is different, the speaker can imagine a situation that would arise if a certain condition were realized.

For example, (1) means “If this were the old days, we would expect them to be executed,” but this does not happen in present-day society.

b. ...ところだった

［V-るところだった］

［V-ていたところだった］

（1）もし気 がつくのが遅 かったら、大惨事 になるところだった。／If we had noticed too late, it could have been a real tragedy.

（2）あっ、あなたに大事 な話 があるのを思 い出 しました。うっかり忘 れるところでした。／Oh, I just remembered that I have something important to discuss with you. I had almost forgotten.

（3）ありがとうございます。注意 していただかなければ忘 れていたところでした。／Thank you so much. If you hadn’t warned me, I would have forgotten.

Means that under different circumstances a certain event would have occurred, but it was narrowly avoided, just in time. Often used with conditional clauses marked with ...ば or ...たら. To emphasize that the event was right on the verge of occurring, the expression もうすこしで...ところだった (any longer and...would have...) may be used.

c. ...なら（ば）...ところ　だが／を

（1）普通 ならただではすまないところだが、今回 だけは見逃 してやろう。／Ordinarily I wouldn't let this pass, but I'll overlook it just this once.

（2）本来 ならば直接 お伺 いすべきところですが、書面 にて失礼 致 します。／I know that under normal circumstances I should come to see you in person, but I hope you don’t mind my sending you a letter instead.

（3）通常 は定価 どおりのところを、お得意 さんに限 り特別 に1万円 引 きになっております。／Although normally we charge the list price, we are offering a special 10,000 yen discount to our best customers only.

（4）いつもなら1時間 で行 けるところを、今日 は交通 事故 があって3時間 もかかった。／We can usually get there in an hour, but today there was a car accident, so it took us three hours.

Used with expressions such as 普通 (usually), 通常 (normally), and 本来ならば (under ordinary circumstances). Expresses that the current state of affairs is special and differs from the usual one.

<< 【ところに】 | Home | 【とされている】 >>

【ところを】

1. Vところを...V

（1）お母 さんは子供 が遊 んでいるところを家 の窓 から見 ていた。／The mother was watching the children play, from the window of the house.

（2）こっそりタバコを吸 っているところを先生 に見 つかった。／I was sneaking a smoke when my teacher spotted me.

（3）駅前 を歩 いているところを警官 に呼 び止 められた。／She was walking in front of the station when she was stopped by the police.

（4）男 は金庫 からお金 を盗 み出 そうとしているところを現行犯 で逮捕 された。／Just as he was taking the money out of the safe, he was caught in the act and arrested.

（5）人々 がぐっすり寝込 んだところを突然 の揺 れが襲 った。／The people were sleeping soundly when all of a sudden there was a jolt.

（6）あやうく暴漢 に襲 われかけたところを見知 らぬ男性 に助 けてもらった。／Just as I was about to be assaulted by a thug, I got help from a man I had never seen before.

This pattern contains two verbs, with the second one denoting an action that exerts a direct effect on the development of the situation expressed by the first. The second verb is a verb of sight or discovery, such as 見る (see), 見つける (find), 見つかる (be found), or 発見する (discover), or a verb that denotes cessation, capture, attack, or rescue, such as 呼び止める (call to a halt), 捕まえる (catch/capture), 捕まる (be caught/be captured), 襲う (attack), or 助ける (save/help). These all share the meaning of halting or obstructing the development of the action or event denoted by the first verb.

2. ...ところ（を）

［Nのところ（を）］

［Aところ（を）］

［R-ちゅうのところ（を）］

（1）お楽 しみのところを恐縮 ですが、ちょっとお時間 を拝借 できないでしょうか。／I am sorry to disturb you while you’re having such a pleasant time, but could I please have a few moments of your time?

（2）ご多忙 のところ、よくきてくださいました。／Thank you so much for taking time out of your busy schedule to be here today.

（3）お忙 しいところを申 し訳 ありませんが、ちょっとお邪魔 いたします。／I am very sorry to disturb you, but I’m going to have to interrupt.

（4）お取 り込 み中 のところを失礼 します。／Please excuse me for intruding when you’re in the middle of something.

（5）お休 み中 のところをお電話 してすみませんでした。／I am sorry to be calling during your vacation.

（6）難 しいことは承知 のうえですが、そこのところをちょっと無理 して聞 いていただけないでしょうか。／I am well aware of how difficult this is, but can’t I ask you to make a special effort to consider what I have to say?

（7）A:最近 ちょっと忙 しくて...。／I am rather busy these days....

B:そこんところを何 とかよろしくお願 いしますよ。／I know, but I still want to ask you to find some way to help me out.

Used by the speaker to express that s/he is taking the addressee’s situation into consideration when s/he is making a difficult or unreasonable request or causing inconvenience to the other person. Often used to preface requests, apologies, or expressions of gratitude. As in (6) and (7), sometimes the previously-stated circumstances are referred to with a demonstrative, resulting in forms like そこのところ (regarding that point).

<< 【とされている】 | Home | 【として】 >>

【としたら】

Formed by attaching the particle と to したら. Means something like “supposing that is true,” “supposing that such-and-such exists/occurs,” or “based on this fact/the present state of affairs.” Used to establish the conditions for the supposition “if one were to think such-and-such.” Can hardly ever be replaced by たら alone.

1. ...としたら〈not-yet-realized condition〉

［N／Na　だとしたら］

［A／V　としたら］

（1）家 を建 てるとしたら、大 きい家 がいい。／If you’re going to build a house, a big one is best.

（2）もし1億円 の宝 くじがあたったとしたら、家 を買 おう。／If I were to win a hundred million yen in the lottery, I’d buy a house.

（3）仮 にあなたが言 っていることが本当 だとしたら、彼 は私 に嘘 をついていることになる。／Supposing that what you say is true, that would mean he’s lying to me.

（4）いらっしゃるとしたら何時 ごろになりますか。／If you were to come, what time do you think it might be?

（5）責任 があるとしたら、私 ではなくあなたの方 です。／If someone is responsible for this, it’s not me but you.

Means “supposing we assume that such-and-such is a fact,” or “in the event that such-and-such occurs or exists.” としたら is followed by an expression of the speaker’s intention, judgment, or evaluation. Sometimes accompanied by 仮に (supposing that.../granting, for the sake of argument, that...) or もし (if/provided that...). としたら can be followed by expressions of intention or evaluation; in such cases, とすると and とすれば are not natural.

（×）宝くじがあたった｛とすると／とすれば｝家を買おう。／{When/If} I’d win the lottery, then I’ll buy a house.

2. ...としたら〈already-realized condition〉

［N／Na　（なの）だとしたら］

［A／V　（の）だとしたら］

（1）これだけ待 っても来 ないのだとしたら、今日 はもう来 ないでしょう。／If she hasn’t come after we’ve waited this long, then she probably isn’t going to come at all today.

（2）A:私 はそのことを誰 にも話 していません。／I haven’t said anything about that to anyone.

B:あなたが話 してないのだとしたら、一体 誰 がもらしたのだろう。／ If you haven’t said anything, then who in the world let it slip?

Expresses a supposition based on the present situation or information received from another person. Means “if we consider a situation/fact like this.” Often used in the form ...のだとしたら. This usage cannot be combined with the expressions 仮に or もし (see above) .

3. （そう）だとしたら

（1）A:寝台車 は全 て満席 だって。／They say all the sleeper cars are full.

B:だとしたら、普通 の座席 に座 って行 くしかないわね。／If that’s so, then we have no other choice but to go and sit in the regular seats.

（2）A:会議 は1時間遅 れの開始 になったそうですよ。／I heard that the meeting is going to start about an hour late.

B:そうだとしたら、こんなに急 いでくるんじゃなかった。／If that’s true, then we didn't have to hurry as much as we did to get here.

（3）台風 の上陸 と満潮 の時刻 が重 なるらしい。だとしたら、沿岸 では厳重 な警戒 が必要 になる。／It looks like the typhoon will hit at the same time as high tide. If that's the case, coastal areas will have to be on close alert.

Refers to the preceding sentence or an utterance made by the addressee and means “if we take that fact/situation into consideration” or “if that is a fact.”

<< 【としては】 | Home | 【とする1】 >>

【としても】

1. Nとしても→【として】3

2. ...としても

［N／Na　（だ）としても］

［A／V　としても］

（1）彼 の言 っていることが真実 だとしても、証拠 がなければ信 じるわけにはいかない。／Even if what he says is true, I can’t very well believe it without proof.

（2）たとえ賛成 してくれる人 が一人 もいないとしても、自分 の意見 を最後 まで主張 するつもりだ。／I intend to stick with my opinion to the very end, even if there isn't a single person who concurs with it.

（3）留学 するとしても、来年 以降 です。／If I do study overseas, it will have to be next year or later.

（4）今 からタクシーに乗 ったとしても、時間 には間 に合 いそうもない。／Even if we took a taxi at this point, it’s not very likely we would make it in time.

（5）渋滞 でバスが遅 れたとしても、電話 ぐらいしてくるはずだ。／Even if the bus was delayed in traffic, I would at least expect a phone call.

（6）加藤 さんの忠 告 がなかったとしても、やっぱり病院 を変 えていただろう。／Even if Kato-san hadn’t warned me, I would probably have changed hospitals anyway.

（7）同級生 に駅 で出会 わなかったとしても、やっぱり授業 をさぼって映画 に行 っただろう。／Even if I hadn’t run into a classmate at the station, I probably still would have cut class to go see a movie.

Takes the pattern XとしてもY (even if X, then Y). Expresses that “even if X were true/had happened, it would not have caused or hindered the occurrence of Y.” Y expresses something that contradicts or deviates from what is expected from X.

When X is a verb, the pattern V-たとしても (ta-form) is the most common, as shown in (4)-(7). However, the pattern V-るとしても (dictionary form) is also used, as shown in (3). (3) means “if something like studying abroad happens in the future,” and the time frame indicated by Y is essentially the same as that for the occurrence of X. On the other hand, V-たとしても means “even if/when situation X has arisen,” so this pattern expresses that X occurs before Y. For example, (4) means “even if we do take a taxi, the end result will probably still be that we won’t make it in time.”

In (6) and (7), X expresses a situation that is contrary to fact, and Y expresses a result that probably would have happened anyway: “In fact, Kato-san did warn me, but even if s/he hadn’t...” and “I did actually run into a classmate, but even if I hadn’t....”

3. ...はいいとしても

（1）彼 はいいとしても、彼女 が許 してくれないだろう。／Even if he’s OK with it, she probably won’t allow it.

（2）計算 を間違 えたのはいいとしても、すぐに報告 しなかったことが問題 だ。／Even if we overlook the miscalculation, the fact that you didn't report it right away is a problem.

（3）時間 通 り来 たのはいいとしても、宿題 を忘 れて来 たのはよくない。／You may have come on time, but it's not acceptable that you forgot to bring your homework.

（4）あのホテルは、部屋 はいいとしても、従業員 の態度 がよくない。／The rooms at that hotel might be all right, but the employees don’t have a very good attitude.

Placed after nouns and clauses. Takes the pattern XはいいとしてもY (even if I accept X, still Y). Y contains an expression of negative evaluation, such as よくない (not good), and the pattern as a whole means “even if I consider X to be all right, I cannot say the same about Y.” This expression is used to contrast two situations, X and Y. It means that while X lies within the range of what is permissible, Y does not.

<< 【とする2】 | Home | 【とすれば1】 >>

【とすると】

すると is attached to the particle と and refers to the preceding clause. Means “if we assume that to be a fact,” or “in the event that...occurs,” or “based on the present situation/facts.” Followed by the expression of a judgment that would hold in the event that the preceding assumption is made. This pattern is used to establish a set of hypothetical conditions and conveys the meaning “in the event that a certain assumption is made.” と by itself does not have this meaning, so とすると can hardly ever be replaced by と.

1. ...とすると〈not-yet-realized condition〉

［N／Na　だとすると］

［A／V　とすると］

（1）医学部 に入 るとすると、一体 どのくらいお金 が必要 なのだろうか。／If I were to enter the school of medicine, I wonder just how much money I would need.

（2）もし、今後 も雨 が降 らないとすると、水不足 になるのは避 けられないだろう。／If the lack of rainfall continues, it probably won't be possible to avoid a water shortage.

（3）仮 に被告 が言 っていることが事実 だとすると、彼女 は嘘 の証言 をしていることになる。／If we assume that the defendant is telling the truth, that means her testimony is a lie.

Means “if we assume that such-and-such is a fact/will occur,” even though the speaker doesn’t actually know whether or not the thing in question is a fact/will occur. Often accompanied by 仮に (supposing that) or もし (if).

2. ...とすると〈already-realized condition〉

［N／Na　だとすると］

［A／V　とすると］

（1）1時間 待 ってまだ何 の連絡 もないとすると、途中 で事故 にでもあったのかもしれない。／If there hasn’t been any word from him/her whatsoever after waiting a full hour, it could mean that there was an accident or something along the way.

（2）A:図書館 は明日 から2週間 休館 になります。／The library is going to close tomorrow for two weeks.

B:2週間 休館 だとすると今日 のうちに必要 な本 を借 りておかなければならないな。／ If it's going to be closed for two weeks, then I guess I’ll have to borrow the books I need today.

Means “taking into account the current situation/facts,” based on the actual situation or information received from another party. かりに (supposing that) and もし (if) do not combine with this usage.

3. （だ）とすると

（1）A:今年 の2月 の平均 気温 は平年 より数度 も高 いそうですよ。／They say that this year the average temperatures in February have been several degrees above normal.

B:とすると、桜 の開花 も早 くなるでしょうね。／If that’s so, then the cherry trees will probably bloom early, won’t they?

（2）脱線 事故 で今日 一日 電車 は不通 の見込 みだという。だとすると、道路 は相当 混雑 するだろう。／I heard that, because of a derailment, the trains are expected to stop running all day today. If that’s the case, the roads will probably be pretty congested.

Refers to the previous sentence or a statement made by another person and means “taking into account the present situation/facts.”

<< 【とすれば1】 | Home | 【とたん】 >>

【とすれば2】

Formed by attaching すれば to the particle と. Refers to the preceding clause and means “if we assume that to be a fact,” “in the event that...occurs,” or “based on these facts/the present situation.” Used by the speaker to establish a set of hypothetical conditions and conveys the meaning “in the event that a certain assumption is made.” ば by itself does not have this meaning, so とすれば can hardly ever be replaced by ば.

1. ...とすれば〈not-yet-realized condition〉

［N／Na　だとすれば］

［A／V　とすれば］

（1）死 ぬとすれば 10 歳 年上 の私 の方 が早 いはずだ。／If one of us is going to die, then it’s bound to be me first, since I'm ten years older than you.

（2）台風 は上陸 するとすれば、明日 の夜 になるでしょう。／If the typhoon does make landfall, it'll probably be tomorrow night.

（3）仮 に 20 人 来 るとすれば、この部屋 ではちょっと狭 すぎるだろう。／If we assume that twenty people will come, this room will probably be a little too small.

（4）この結婚 に反対 する人 がいるとすれば、それは一番 身近 な母親 である可能性 が高 い。／If there’s going to be anyone who is against this marriage, then it’s most likely to be the person most closely related—the mother.

Expresses a hypothetical condition. Means “if we assume that such-and-such is a fact” or “in the event that such-and-such occurs/exists,” although the speaker doesn’t actually know whether or not the thing in question is a fact or will occur. Sometimes accompanied by adverbials such as かりに (supposing that) or もし (if). Often followed by expressions that indicate a judgment on the part of the speaker, such as だろう (probably/likely) or はずだ (should/must be).

2. ...とすれば〈already-realized condition〉

［N／Na　だとすれば］

［A／V　とすれば］

（1）これだけ待 っても来 ないとすれば、もともと来 る気 がなかったんじゃないだろうか。／If she hasn't come after we’ve waited this long, I’d say she probably never intended to come in the first place.

（2）我々 の計画 が敵 に知 られていたとすれば、仲間 のだれかがもらしたことになる。／If our plans were known to the enemy, that means it was one of us that leaked them.

（3）A:この時間 に容疑者 は友人 と会 っていることが分 かっています。／We know that the suspect was meeting with a friend at this time.

B:そうか。彼 にアリバイがあるとすれば、では、犯人 は一体 誰 なのだろう。／Is that so? Well, if he’s got an alibi, then who the heck is the culprit?

Used when the speaker comes to the realization that something is true, based on the present situation or on information received from another party. Means “taking into account the current situation/facts,” or “if I were to make a judgment based on that....” Followed by an expression that indicates a judgment on the part of the speaker. かりに (supposing that) and もし (if) are not combined with this usage.

3. （だ）とすれば

（1）A:家 に電話 しても誰 も出 ないんですよ。／When I call home, nobody answers.

B:だとすれば、もうこちらに向 かっているということじゃないですか。／If that’s the case, don't you think they're already on their way here?

（2）あの日 彼女 は一日中 彼 と一緒 だったことが証明 された。とすれば、彼女 にはアリバイがあるということになる。／It has been proven that, on that day, she was with him all day long. And if that is so, it means she has an alibi.

Refers to the previous sentence or a statement made by another person. Means “if that is a fact” or “if we assume that is correct.” Usage is the same as 2 above. A slightly formal expression. In ordinary conversation, expressions like だったら and そうなら are often used.

4. NをNとすれば

a. NがNだとすれば

（1）テレビを茶 の間 のものとすれば、ラジオは個室 のものである。／If a television is something that goes in the living room (= shared space), then a radio is something that goes in a person’s room (= private space).

（2）兄 が実業家 タイプだとすれば、弟 は学者 タイプの性格 である。／If I were to say that my older brother is the entrepreneurial type, then my younger brother has the scholarly type of personality.

This is a formulaic expression that contrasts two items. It means something like “if I (we) were to say that one of them is..., then I (we) can say that the other is....” It can be replaced by NがNなら(ば), as, for example, in 兄が実業家タイプなら(ば), 弟は学者タイプだ (If my older brother is the entrepreneurial type, then my younger brother is the scholarly type). It is not entirely impossible to use とすると and としたら with this pattern, but とすれば and なら are used most often.

<< 【となく】 | Home | 【となっては】 >>

【となったら】

Follows a clause or noun and expresses either the meaning “in such a case/situation” or “should such a thing become an issue.” When the situation or issue “turns out to be the case,” the overriding meaning is that the outcome is a natural result. Stated also as となると and となれば.

1. ...となったら

［N／Na　（だ）となったら］

［A／V　となったら］

（1）もし、一戸建 の家 を建 てるとなったら、銀行 から相当 の借金 をしなければならない。／If you’re going to build a single dwelling house, you’ll have to get a considerable loan from the bank.

（2）引 き受 ける人 が誰 もいないとなったら、私 がやるしかない。／If there is no one else who will take on the task, then I’ll just have to do it.

（3）彼女 がすでに他 の人 と結婚 してしまったとなったら、もう諦 めるしかない。／If she has already married someone else, there’s nothing to do but give up.

（4）A:夫 が海外 勤務 になったんですよ。／My husband has been assigned a position overseas.

B:そうですか。海外 で生活 するとなったら、お子 さんの学校 のことなど、いろいろ大変 ですね。／Is that so? If you’re living overseas, then you’ll have all sorts of challenges, like schooling for your children and so on.

Follows a clause and means “in the case of that sort of thing/situation coming about.” Can be used either when making an assumption about a fact that has yet to be realized, or when an actual situation has been newly understood. The meaning will depend on the context. For example, in (2), the meaning can be either “assuming such a case” or “the fact of the matter has become clear.” Hypothetical assumptions are sometimes accompanied by かりに or もし. (4) is a case of hearing a person’s statement and can be paraphrased with そうなったら.

2. いざとなったら

（1）いざとなったら私 が責任 をとります。／If the situation arises, I’ll take responsibility.

（2）いざとなったら、今 の仕事 を辞 めても自分 のやりたい道 に進 むつもりだ。／If push comes to shove, I intend to quit my present job and proceed on the course I want to take.

Expresses what will happen in the case that some impediment arises in the implementation of some action. An expression of intent is often used in the latter clause. In that case, となったら can be restated as となれば but not となると.

3. N（のこと）となったら

（1）日本 料理 となったらここの板前 の右 に出 る者 はいないそうだ。／When it comes to Japanese cuisine, there’s no one better than the chef here.

（2）自分 の専門 のこととなったら、彼 は何時間 でも話 し続 ける。／When it comes to his field of expertise, he can continue talking for hours on end.

Used after a noun that is taken up as the point in question. Expresses the meaning “with regard to” or “when that is the topic.”

<< 【となったら】 | Home | 【となる】 >>

【となっては】

1. いまとなっては

（1）今 となっては、名前 も顔 も思 い出 すことができない。／Now at this point, I can’t recall either his name or face.

（2）全 てが終 わってしまった今 となっては、じたばたしてもしかたがない。／Now that everything is over and done with, there’s no sense in fretting.

（3）当時 はずいぶん辛 い思 いをしたものだが、今 となっては、それも懐 かしく思 い出 される。／At the time it was quite painful for me, but now I can think back on it with some nostalgia.

Expresses the meaning “having proceeded through a variety of events to reach this point.” Often followed by expressions stating “that was to be expected/as one would think.” Though it is often followed by negative evaluations of “cannot be done” or “there’s no point anymore,” as in (1) and (2), it can also be a neutral evaluation, as in (3).

2. ...となっては

［N／Na　（だ）となっては］

［A／V　となっては］

（1）子供達 だけで海外 へ行 くとなっては、親 としてはちょっと心配 になる。／With the children going overseas all by themselves, as a parent I am a little concerned.

（2）病状 がここまで進 んだとなっては、もうどうすることもできない。／As the illness has progressed to this point, there’s nothing that can be done.

（3）誰 も引 き受 けてくれないとなっては、自分 でやるしかない。／As there’s no one willing to take on the task, it’s up to me to do it.

Following a clause, this expresses the meaning “in the case that such a situation arises.” Often used for conditions that have already been realized, and the latter half expresses the evaluation or judgment of the speaker regarding what s/he expects as the natural outcome of situation. In many cases, negative evaluations such as 心配だ (worrisome) or 仕方がない (can’t be helped) are expressed.

<< 【となる】 | Home | 【となれば】 >>

【となると】

1. となると

（1）A:先生 はご病気 で昨日 入院 されました。／The professor was hospitalized yesterday because of illness.

B:となると、しばらく授業 は休講 ということになりますね。／If that’s so, then our lessons will probably be canceled for a while, right?

（2）長期 予報 によれば今年 の梅雨 は空梅雨 になるとのことだ。となると、野菜 の値段 の高騰 や、水不足 の心配 が予想 される。／The long range forecast says that this year’s rainy season will be a dry one. In that case, steep increases in the price of vegetables and concerns about water shortages can be expected.

Used in the sentence-initial position and expresses the meaning “based on that reality.” The first clause is either something that the speaker has newly learned about or something mentioned by someone else. The second clause contains the opinion that the speaker arrives at based on that information.

2. ...となると

［N／Na　（だ）となると］

［A／V　となると］

（1）医学部 に進 むとなると相当 にお金 がかかるだろう。／Proceeding on to medical school will likely cost a considerable amount of money.

（2）彼 は、決断 するまでは時間 がかかるが、やるとなると実行 するのは早 い。／For him, it takes a long time to make a decision, but when he does take action, he moves on it quickly.

（3）いざ、海外 に行 くとなると、事前 の準備 が大変 だ。／If sometime you do go overseas, the preparations beforehand are considerable.

（4）仮 に、このまま水不足 が続 くとなると営業時間 を短縮 しなければならなくなる。／Should the current water shortage continue like this, we may have to shorten our hours of operation.

（5）この時間 になっても帰 っていないとなると、何 かの事件 に巻 き込 まれている可能性 がある。／When she still hasn’t come home at this late hour, there’s a possibility that she’s been involved in some incident.

（6）現場 に残 された指紋 が彼 のものと一致 するとなると、彼 が犯人 である公算 が高 い。／If his fingerprints match those left at the scene, there’s a high probability that he’s the criminal.

（7）これほど大企業 の経営 状態 が悪 いとなると、不況 はかなり深刻 ということになる。／When the operations of a large corporation are as bad as this, the recession can be said to be rather serious.

（8）社長 がそう言 っているとなると、変更 はほとんど不可能 でしょう。／If the company president said something like that, any revision is almost impossible.

Follows a clause to express the meanings “in such a case” or “when such a case arises.” Depending on the context, it can be used to talk about an actual situation or an assumed one. For a hypothetical situation, expressions such as もし／かりに are used.

3. いざとなると

（1）危険 は承知 の手術 だが、いざとなると不安 になるものだ。／There’s expected risk in any surgery, but when it actually happens, we get uneasy.

（2）スピーチは原稿 を何度 も読 んで練習 してきたが、いざとなるとあがってしまい、うまくしゃべれなかった。／I reviewed the manuscript over and over and practiced the speech, but when it came time to do it, I got a bad case of nerves and couldn’t deliver it well.

An idiomatic expression with the meaning “in the case of actually implementing (something).” The second clause often continues with an expression to show that the outcome was a natural result of the situation.

4. N（のこと）となると

（1）芸能人 のスキャンダルとなると、マスコミは夢中 になって追跡 する。／When it comes to a celebrity scandal, the mass media pursue it relentlessly.

（2）試験 問題 のこととなると学生 は急 に真剣 になる。／When the lesson turns to a possible exam question, the students suddenly get serious.

Follows a noun to express the meaning “at the time that the matter becomes an issue/problem.” The latter half of the sentence continues with an expression to show that an attitude contrary to the usual one is taken when the issue arises.

5. ...かとなると

（1）どうすればこの問題 を解決 できるかとなると、簡単 には答 えられない。／If I am asked what to do to solve this problem, I can’t give a simple answer.

（2）実際 にだれがその危険 な仕事 にあたるかとなると、積極的 な人 は一人 もいない。／If you want to know who actually is to undertake such a risky task, there’s not a single person who has come forward.

Follows a query to express the meaning “when this becomes a problem.” The latter half follows with a negative expression to show that the solution or implementation is impossible or challenging.

6. Nともなると→【ともなると】

<< 【となると】 | Home | 【とにかく】 >>

【となれば】

1. ...となれば

［N／Na　（だ）となれば］

［A／V　となれば］

（1）外国 へ住 むとなればやはりその国 の言葉 ぐらいは勉強 しておいたほうがよい。／If one’s to live overseas, then it follows that it’s a good idea to study the language of that country.

（2）結婚 してから両親 と同居 するとなれば、今 の家 では狭 すぎるだろう。／If you’re going to live with your parents after getting married, then your present house is too small.

（3）今 から急 いで行 ってももう間 に合 わないとなれば、焦 ってもしかたがない。／If it’s already too late even if they rush there now, there’s no point in getting flustered.

（4）彼 が言 ったことが全 て嘘 だとなれば、我々 はまんまとだまされていたことになる。／If everything he has said turns out to be a lie, it means that we have been completely deceived.

Follows a clause to convey meanings such as “in such a case that...” or “in the case of such a situation...” or “based on such a fact....” Continues with expressions that indicate either an expected judgment or the proper action to take regarding the situation. Depending on the context, the form can be used for hypothetical conditions or already-realized situations.

2. いざとなれば

（1）手持 ちの現金 では足 りないかもしれないが、いざとなればクレジットカードを使 うことができる。／You may not have enough cash on hand, but if the need arises, you can use a credit card.

（2）一人 で留学 するのは不安 だが、いざとなれば、友達 が助 けてくれるから大丈夫 だ。／I am worried about studying overseas by myself, but if something happens, I’ll be all right because my friends will help me.

An idiomatic expression that means “in the event that such a situation were actually to arise.” Often used to express that, even if a difficult or unmanageable situation arises, things will be all right. Also takes the forms いざとなると and いざとなったら.

3. N（のこと）となれば

（1）いつもは生気 のない彼 の目 もサッカーのこととなれば急 に生 き生 きと輝 いてくる。／His usually lifeless eyes suddenly start to sparkle animatedly when the talk turns to soccer.

（2）脳死 問題 となれば学者 も安易 な発言 はできない。／When it comes to the issue of brain death, even scholars are not able to make simplistic statements.

Follows a noun and means “when that becomes the topic of conversation.” Used to introduce something as a topic. Usually followed by expressions indicating that when that becomes the topic of conversation, a person’s (or people’s) attitude or way of handling things differs from the usual.

4. ...かとなれば

（1）どうすれば解決 できるかとなれば、答 えは簡単 には出 てこないものだ。／When it comes to solving problems, the answer is not always easily found.

（2）首相 が発言 どおり実行 するかとなれば、必 ずしもそうとばかりは言 えない。／If you ask whether the prime minister will do exactly as he says, the answer is not necessarily yes.

となれば is placed after an interrogative expression and means “when the matter of...becomes the topic/problem at hand.” Followed by a negative expression stating, for example, that solving or implementing something is difficult or impossible. Often used to contrast one situation with another and also bring up an important problem. For example, (2) means something like, “He does state his views, but when it comes to whether or not he acts on them when the time comes....”

5. Nともなれば→【ともなれば】

<< 【となれば】 | Home | 【との】 >>

【とにかく】

Used to put aside discussion of a certain matter or action for the time being in order to focus on another matter or action. The form ともかく is also used.

1. とにかく

（1）あの人 はとにかく大変 な秀才 です。／At any rate, she’s exceptionally bright.

（2）田中 さんの新 しい家 、とにかくすごく大 きい家 なんですよ。／You know Tanaka-san’s new house—whatever else you might say about it, it's incredibly huge!

（3）戦闘 の後 の町 は、とにかくひどい状況 です。／Now that the battle is over, the town is all in all in a terrible state.

Means “although many things could probably be said, this one comes first.” Followed by an expression that indicates an extraordinary degree of something, such as 非常に／大変／すごく...だ (it is extremely/very/incredibly...). Used to emphasize this meaning. Tends to be used in spoken language.

2. とにかくV

（1）うまくいくか分 かりませんが、とにかくやってみます。／I don’t know whether or not I'll succeed, but at any rate, I’ll try.

（2）とにかく言 われたことだけはやっておきました。／Anyway, I’ve done at least what I was told to do.

（3）お忙 しいとは存 じますがとにかくおいでくださいますようお願 いいたします。／We know how very busy you are, but we would be grateful if you would please just honor us with your presence.

（4）まだ全員 そろっていませんが、時間 ですのでとにかく始 めることにしましょう。／Not everyone is here yet, but since it’s time, let’s just get started.

Followed by a verb expressing an intentional action and means “giving priority to this action for now, regardless of other considerations.” Used by the speaker to assert his/her own intention, a fact, etc. or to urge the addressee to implement an action.

3. Nはとにかく（として）

（1）見 かけはとにかく味 はよい。／Never mind what it looks like, it tastes good.

（2）成績 はとにかくとして、明 るくて思 いやりのあるいい子供 です。／Putting aside the matter of his grades, he is a cheerful and considerate child.

（3）私 はとにかく、あなたはこの仕事 に満足 しているんですか。／Never mind me—are you satisfied with this job?

（4）あいさつはとにかくまずは中 にお入 りください。／The greetings can wait until later—please come inside.

（5）A:先日 はお世話 様 でした。／Thank you so much for the other day.

B:いいえ。それはとにかく、お願 いした仕事 の方 は引 き受 けてくださいますか。／Not at all. Be that as it may, are you willing to take on the work I asked you about?

Placed after a noun and used to contrast that thing with something else that is more important or should be done first. In conversation, as in (5), it can also be used at the beginning of a sentence in forms like それはとにかく（として） to refer to something the other person has said and introduce a different topic.

<< 【とにかく】 | Home | 【とは】 >>

【との】

1. ...とのことだ

（1）みなさんによろしくとのことでした。／He said to give his regards to everyone.

（2）無事 大学 に合格 なされたとのこと、まことにおめでとうございます。／I heard that you passed your university entrance exams—sincere congratulations on your success!

（3）社長 はすこし遅 れるので、会議 を始 めておいてくれとのことでした。／The company president will be a little late, so she said we should start the meeting without her.

（4）そちらは、寒 い日 が続 いているとのことですが、皆様 お変 わりありませんか。／I hear that you have been having a cold spell—how is everyone doing?

（5）あの二人 も、長 かった婚約 に終止符 を打 ち、6月 に挙式 するとのこと。／I hear that those two are bringing their long engagement to a close and getting married in June.

Means “I hear/they say that....” Used by the speaker to say something that s/he has heard or learned from another person. As in (2) and (5), sometimes だ is dropped and the clause or sentence ends with こと. May take the ta-form, as in とのことだった／でした (I heard/they said that...). Cannot be used in the negative form.

2. ...とのN

（1）恩師 から結婚式 には出席 できないとの返事 を受 け取 った。／I received a reply from my mentor that she won’t be able to attend the wedding.

（2）学生 から留学 するため一年 休学 させてほしいとの希望 が出 されている。／The student has submitted a request for a year's leave of absence in order to study abroad.

（3）この件 については、次回 の審議 に回 してはどうかとの議長 の提案 に全員 賛成 した。／Everyone agreed to the proposal made by the chair for deliberation on this matter to be tabled until the next meeting.

（4）来月 から一年間 、札幌 の支社 に出向 せよとの辞令 を受 けた。／I’ve received an official notice that I’ll be reassigned to our branch office in Sapporo for a year, starting next month.

（5）文部 大臣 は、学校 教育 を改善 するためには、高等 教育 機関 の入学 試験 制度 の抜本的 改革 が必要 だとの見解 を述 べた。／The Minister of Education has stated his view that, in order to improve formal education, a drastic overhaul of the entrance examination system for institutions of higher education is necessary.

In the pattern ...とのN, a clause that describes the content of a certain linguistic expression or thought is used to modify a noun. Used in formal style. The N slot is filled by a noun that denotes either a speech activity, such as 手紙 (letter), 返事 (reply), 依頼 (request), 提案 (proposal), 警告 (warning), or 命令 (order), or a thought activity, such as 意見 (opinion), 見解 (viewpoint), 考え (idea), or 希望 (hope). Used when talking about something that another person has said or thought. When the speaker’s own thoughts are being expressed, usually the form という is used instead of との, as below.

（例）私は夫婦別姓を合法化すべきだという意見をもっている。／I am of the opinion that the use of different surnames by married couples should be legalized.

<< 【との】 | Home | 【とはいいながら】 >>

【とは】

1. ...とは〈definition〉

（1）パソコンとは、個人 で使 える小型 のコンピューターのことだ。／A pasokon (personal computer) is a small-sized computer for individual use.

（2）蓮華 とは蓮 の花 のことだ。／A renge (Chinese milk vetch) is a lotus flower.

（3）21世紀 の日本 で求 められる福祉 の形態 とはどのようなものだろうか。／What will be the form of social welfare system required by Japanese society in the 21st century?

（4）「普遍的 」とは、どんな場合 にも広 く一般的 に当 てはまるという意味 だ。／“Universal” means that something applies broadly and generally, in all cases.

（5）私 にとって家族 とは一体 何 なのだろうか。／What exactly does “family” mean to me?

とは is used after a noun to describe the meaning, characteristics, or content of the noun. In the patternとは...ものだ, it is used to express the essential features of the noun, and in the patterns ...とは...のことだ／意味だ and ...とは...ということだ／意味だ, it is used to define the meaning or content of a word or phrase. Used mainly in written language. In spoken Japanese, Nというのは is more common.

2. ...とは〈quotation〉

（1）A:森山 さん、会社 退職 するそうですよ。／I’ve heard that Moriyama-san’s leaving the company, you know.

B:えっ、退職 するとは、結婚 するということですか。／Oh, does that mean she’s getting married?

（2）《書 き置 きを見 て》「お世話 になりました」とは、もう帰 ってこないということだろうか。／《looking at a note》“Thank you for all you’ve done for me...” I wonder if this means she won’t be coming back.

（3）A:このお話 、なかったことにしてください。／Let’s just say this didn’t happen.

B:「なかったことにする」とはどう言 うことですか？／What do you mean, “This didn’t happen”?

（4）親 に向 かって「バカヤロー」とは何事 だ。／What makes you think you can call your parents “stupid idiots”?

Used in response to a verbal utterance, written information, or some other linguistic input, to indicate the speaker’s evaluation of the utterance/information or to confirm its real intention. Often accompanied by feelings such as surprise, amazement, or anger. というのは is often used instead of とは. However, とは cannot be replaced by というのは in fixed expressions such as とは何事だ (see (4) above).

3. ...とは〈surprise〉

（1）一人 で5種目 も優勝 とはまったく驚 いた。／It is absolutely amazing that you won five different events on your own.

（2）全員 そろって授業 をサボる とはあきれた学生達 だ。／What an appalling group of students, all of them cutting class together!

（3）人 を2時間 も待 たせておいて「すみません」の一言 もないとはまったく非常識 な奴 だ。／Someone who keeps you waiting for two hours and then doesn’t offer a word of apology is an absolute boor.

（4）タクシーの中 に忘 れた現金 がもどってくるとは思 いもよらないことでした。／I never expected that the cash I had left in the taxi would be returned to me!

とは expresses the speaker’s surprise and amazement when s/he encounters an unexpected situation. In casual speech, なんて is often used instead of とは. As shown below, the clause following とは (or なんて) may be omitted.

（例）あの人がこんな嘘をつくとは。／(What a surprise that) s/he would tell such a lie!

（例）ベテラン登山家の彼が遭難するとは。／To think that an experienced climber like him should go missing in the mountains!

（例）こともあろうに、結婚式の日がこんなひどい土砂降りになろうとは。／(I never imagined there would be) a downpour like this on my wedding day, of all days!

<< 【とはいうものの】 | Home | 【とはいっても】 >>

【とはいえ】

とはいえ follows a clause or a sentence and means “that is true, but....” Used when the actual result contradicts what is expected from the previous clause/sentence. A formal expression used mainly in written Japanese. とはいいながら, とはいうものの and と(は)いっても may be used instead of とはいえ.

1. ...とはいえ

［N／Na　（だ）とはいえ］

［A／V　とはいえ］

（1）男女 平等 の世 の中 とはいえ、職場 での地位 や仕事 の内容 などの点 でまだ差別 が残 っている。／Despite the so-called equality of the sexes in today’s world, there is still discrimination in the workplace with respect to things like status and job content.

（2）国際化 が進 んだとはいえ、やはり日本 社会 には外国人 を特別視 するという態度 が残 っている。／Although internationalization has progressed, when all is said and done, Japanese society retains an attitude of looking at foreigners in a special way.

Used after a clause, とはいえ means “that is true, but....” Used when the actual result contradicts what is expected from the preceding clause. A formal, mainly written expression. とはいいながら, とはいうものの, and と(は)いっても may be used instead.

2. とはいえ

（1）病状 は危険 な状態 を脱 して、回復 に向 かっている。とはいえ、まだ完全 に安心 するわけにはいかない。／She is out of critical condition and on her way to recovery. Having said that, we cannot let our guard down completely yet.

（2）生徒 の非行 には家庭 環境 が強 く影響 する。とはいえ、学校 教育 のあり方 に責任 の一端 もある。／The home environment strongly affect pupils’ delinquency. That said, the current system of school education is also partly responsible for it.

Used at the beginning of a sentence, とはいえ refers to the previous sentence and means “that is true, but....” Used when the actual result contradicts what is expected from the previous sentence. A written expression. とはいいながら, とはいうものの, and と(は)いっても may be used instead.

<< 【とはかぎらない】 | Home | 【とはちがって】 >>

【とばかり】

1. ...とばかり

（1）今 がチャンスとばかり、チャンピオンは猛烈 な攻撃 を開始 した。／The champion launched a fierce attack, as if to say that this was a chance not to be missed.

（2）横綱 はいつでもかかってこいとばかりに身構 えた。／The yokozuna (a sumoo wrestler of the highest rank) stood poised to attack, as if to say, “Come and get me!”

（3）もう二度 と来 るなとばかりに私 の目 の前 でピシャッと 戸 を閉 めた。／She slammed the door in my very face, as much as to say, “Never come back!”

（4）「どうだ、すごいだろう」とばかりに、新 しい車 を見 せびらかしている。／He’s showing off his brand-new car to us, as much as to say, “Look! Isn’t this great?”

Used after a clause, とばかりexpresses the meaning “as if to say....” It is used to convey the speaker’s sense that another person actually wants to say something like what is expressed in the とばかり clause. とばかりis followed by words/phrases that indicate a strong degree of vigor or force. It is a formal, mainly written expression and is often used in idiomatic expressions, such as この時とばかりに攻め込む／攻めかかる “now is the time to strike/attack” and えいっとばかりに切りつける／切りかかる “slash at/strike at (someone) with all one’s might” (lit. “with a shout of exertion; with a battle cry”).

2. ...といわんばかり

（1）お前 は黙 っていろと言 わんばかりに兄 は私 をにらみつけた。／My older brother glared at me, as if to say, “Keep your mouth shut!”

（2）警察 は「お前 がやったんだろう」と言 わんばかりの態度 で男 を尋問 した。／The attitude of the police officer as he interrogated the man was, “Come on, you know you did it!”

Used after a clause, といわんばかり means “look/act as if s/he is about to say....” Used in essentially the same way as 1 above.

<< 【とはちがって】 | Home | 【とも】 >>

【とみえて】

［N／Na　（だ）とみえて］

［A／V　とみえて］

1. ...とみえて

（1）最近 忙 しいとみえて、いつ電話 しても留守 だ。／He must be very busy recently, because he is not in whenever I call.

（2）夜中 に雨 が降 ったとみえて、水 たまりができている。／It seems to have rained during the night, because there are puddles outside.

（3）何 かいいことがあったとみえて、朝 からずっとにこにこしている。／Something nice must have happened to him, because he’s been grinning since morning.

（4）隣 の家 は留守 とみえて、ドアの前 に数日分 の新聞 がたまっている。／It looks like our next-door neighbor is away, because there are newspapers from the past several days piled up in front of the door.

States a conjecture based on a current state of affairs. The first clause contains the speaker’s conjecture, and the second presents the reason or basis for this conjecture. For instance, in (2) above, the speaker states the conjecture 夜中に雨が降ったようだ (it looks like it rained during the night) in the first clause, and this conjecture is based on the state of affairs 水たまりができている (there are puddles) given in the second clause. The second clause describes a fact that the speaker has actually observed.

2. ...とみえる

（1）今日 の田中 君 はやけに気前 がいい。何 かいいことがあったとみえる。／Today Tanaka-kun is being unusually generous with his money. Something good must have happened.

（2）合格 発表 を見 に行 った妹 は、帰 ってくるなり部屋 に閉 じ込 もってしまった。どうも不合格 だったとみえる。／As soon as my sister, who went to find out her results for the entrance exam, got back, she locked herself in her room. It looks like she failed.

（3）学生 にパソコンの使 い方 を説明 したが、ほかの人 に聞 いているところを見 ると、一度 聞 いただけではよくわからなかったとみえる。／Although I explained to the student how to use a computer, it seems that hearing it just once was not enough for him to understand, because I saw him asking someone else.

（4）花子 は先生 にほめられた絵 を会 う人 ごとに見 せている。ほめられたことがよほどうれしかったとみえる。／Hanako shows the drawing her teacher praised her for to everyone she sees. She must have been so happy that she was praised.

とみえる is used to state, as if the speaker were talking to him/herself, a conjecture based on what s/he has observed. Young Japanese speakers do not use this expression very often.

<< 【ども2】 | Home | 【ともいうべき】 >>

【ともあろうものが】

［Nともあろうものが］

（1）大蔵 官僚 ともあろうものが、賄賂 を受 け取 るとは驚 いた。／It is shocking to know that even an official of the Ministry of Finance took a bribe.

（2）警察官 ともあろうものが、強盗 をはたらくとは何 ということだろう。／It is astounding that a police officer, of all people, committed burglary.

（3）母親 ともあろうものが、生 まれた自分 の子供 をゴミ箱 に捨 てるとは、まったく恐 ろしい話 だ。／It is absolutely terrifying that a mother would dump her own new-born in a garbage can.

Means “such a (competent, honorable, etc.) person (does something unexpectedly).” Placed after a noun indicating social status, role or occupation, it is used to describe an action that, according to conventional wisdom, a person in such a role should not have performed. ともあろうものが is followed by an expression that conveys surprise, anger, or suspicion. もの can be replaced by other words that refer to people, such as 人 (person) or 人物 (person/figure).

（例）国会議員ともあろう人物がこのような巨額の脱税を平気で行うのだから、議員のモラルも低下したものである。／The professional morals of politicians have really deteriorated when a member of the Diet, of all people, thinks nothing of evading such an enormous amount of tax.

<< 【ともなると】 | Home | 【ともに】 >>

【ともなれば】

［Nともなれば］

［Vともなれば］

（1）9月 ともなれば、真夏 の暑 さはなくなり過 ごしやすくなる。／Once September comes, the summer heat is over and the weather is more comfortable.

（2）子供 も 10 歳 ともなればもう少 し物分 かりがよくてもいいはずだ。／Once a child is ten, she should be a little more perceptive.

（3）結婚式 ともなればジーパンではまずいだろう。／When it comes to a wedding ceremony, it’s not appropriate to wear jeans.

（4）主婦 ともなれば朝寝坊 してはいられない。／If you’re a homemaker, you can’t sleep in in the morning.

（5）学長 に就任 するともなれば、今 までのようにのんびり研究 に打 ち込 んではいられなくなる。／Once you assume the presidency of the university, you won’t be able to focus freely and easily on your research, as you have until now.

Used with a noun or a verb referring to time, age, a role or an event, ともなれば means “if/when such a thing or event is realized.” It is followed by an expression indicating the speaker’s judgment that if such a change in situation takes place, a certain consequence will naturally follow. ともなると can also be used instead of ともなれば.

<< 【ともよい】 | Home | 【とりわけ】 >>

【とやら】

1. Nとやら

（1）例 の啓子 さんとやらとはうまくいっていますか。／Are you getting along well with that Keiko-san, or whatever her name is?

（2）娘 が「ムサカ」とやらいうギリシャ料理 を作 ってくれました。／My daughter cooked me a Greek dish called something like moussaka.

Means “called something like...” and is used after a name that the speaker does not remember precisely. In (1), とやら is attached directly to a particle, but this can be considered to be an abbreviation of the phrase とやらいう人 (a person called something like...), with いう人 (a person called) omitted.

2. ...とやら

（1）私 の答案 を見 て、先生 がびっくりした顔 をしていたとやら。／I heard that when the teacher saw my answers she looked astonished, or something.

（2）結局 あの二人 は結婚 して、田舎 で仲良 く暮 らしているとやら。／I heard that those two ended up getting married and are living happily together in the countryside, or something.

とやら follows information that the speaker has heard from someone else and means, “it may not be completely accurate, but I heard something like this.” Although the meaning of とやら is similar to that of とか聞いている, とのことだ and そうだ, とやら conveys a strong sense that the information quoted is not very precise because the speaker’s recollection is vague. とやら is rarely used in everyday spoken language.

<< 【とわず】 | Home | 【とんでもない】 >>

【とんだ】

［とんだN］

（1）あなたが邪魔 したなどと、とんだ思 い違 いをしていました。／Saying that you had disturbed me was a complete misunderstanding on my part.

（2）A:通勤 の途中 で、事故 に遭 ってしまったんですよ。／I had an accident on my way to work, you know.

B:それはとんだ災難 でしたね。／What a terrible thing to have happened!

（3）親 にかくれてたばこを吸 うとは、とんだ不良 娘 だ。／What a terrible daughter, to smoke behind her parents’ backs.

（4）もし1分 でも気 が付 くのが遅 れていたら、とんだ大事故 になっていたかもしれない。／If I had noticed even just one minute later, it might have turned into a disastrous accident.

（5）とんだ野郎 に見込 まれてしまったものだ。／Some guy like that is counting on me.

（6）委員会 の議長 に選 ばれるとは、とんだことになってしまった。／Being elected to chair the committee was totally unexpected.

とんだ precedes a noun referring to a person or situation and means that the person or situation is contrary to one’s expectations. It usually conveys a negative evaluation, with the meaning of “awful,” “stunning; shocking,” “troublesome,” or “terrible,” and is used to describe an unexpected result or a person who doesn’t conform to commonly-accepted standards of behavior. However, in cases such as (5) above, とんだ can also convey a positive evaluation that implies warmth and familiarity, with the meaning of “(a) unique and uncommon (individual).”

<< 【どんな】 | Home | 【ないか】 >>

【どんなに】

1. どんなに...だろう（か）

（1）希望校 に合格 できたらどんなにいいだろうか。／How great it would be if I could pass the entrance exam for the school of my choice.

（2）息子 の戦死 を知 ったら両親 はどんなに悲 しむことでしょう。／How sad his parents would be if they knew that their son had died in the war.

（3）父 が生 きていたらどんなに喜 んでくれたことだろうか。／How pleased my father would have been for me if he were alive!

（4）子供 が無事 だと分 かった時 、私 はどんなにうれしかっただろう。／How delighted I was when I found out that my child was safe.

（5）私 はこの日 がくることをどんなに望 んだことだろう。／How eagerly I had waited for this day!

The pattern どんなに...だろう(か) combines with expressions of joy, sorrow, hope, and so on to create exclamatory statements indicating that the degree of emotion is far greater than what is usual. In (1)-(3), this pattern is used to make a conjecture about something that hasn’t actually happened and conveys the meaning of “if X were so, then surely (I) would be/would have been extremely Y.” On the other hand, in (4) and (5) it expresses that someone actually was very happy or did eagerly look forward to something.

2. どんなに...ても

（1）どんなに金持 ちでも愛情 に恵 まれなければ幸福 とは言 えない。／No matter how rich you are, you cannot claim to be happy without being loved.

（2）たとえどんなに苦 しくても最後 まで頑張 ります。／No matter how hard it will be, I’ll make every effort to see this through to the end.

（3）どんなに働 いても暮 らしはちっとも楽 にならない。／No matter how hard I work, it doesn’t get any easier to make ends meet.

Means that, regardless of the degree or level of the condition indicated by this clause, what is stated in the subsequent clause is always true (or, in the case of a negative form, not true). どんなに...ても can be immediately preceded by たとえ (if; even if) and replaced by いかに／いくら...ても (however/no matter how (much)).

<< 【どんなに】 | Home | 【ないかしら】 >>

【ないか】

...ないか is used mainly by male speakers. However, ...ない？, which is an abbreviated form of polite expressions such as ...ませんか and か, is used by both male and female speakers.

1. V-ない（か）〈invitation〉

（1）ちょっと、食 べてみない？／Want to try some of this?

（2）今度 、いっしょにスキーに行 かないか。／Why don’t we go skiing sometime?

（3）そろそろお茶 にしませんか。／How about taking a break for tea pretty soon?

（4）ちょっと寄 っていきません？／Would you like to drop by there?

When combined with verbs expressing a volitional action, the pattern V-ない(か) is used to suggest that an interlocutor take some action or to invite him/her to do something together. The polite form of V-ない(か) is V-ませんか. V-ない(か) forms are usually pronounced with rising intonation, and か can be omitted.

2. V-てくれない（か）〈request〉

（1）お塩 、とってくれない？／Can you pass me the salt?

（2）ちょっと手伝 ってくれませんか。／Would you help me for a moment?

（3）この本 、2、3日 貸 してもらえない？／Can I borrow this book for a few days?

（4）5時 までにおいでくださいませんか。／Would it be possible for you to be here by five o’clock?

（5）明日 もう一度 ご来店 いただけないでしょうか。／Could you come to our shop again tomorrow?

This pattern, used in the forms V-てくれないか and V-てもらえないか, expresses a request from a speaker to an interlocutor. It is more polite when used in forms such as V-てくださいませんか／いただけませんか／いただけませんでしょうか or お／ご...くださいませんか, as in (4), and お／ご...いただけないでしょうか, as in (5).

Note that when this pattern is used with もらう and いただく, the potential forms もらえる and いただける should be negated to create the forms V-てもらえないか／いただけないか. Also, when いただく and くださる are attached to honorific expressions such as おいでになる (to come/to be here) or Sino-Japanese verbs such as 来店する (to come to a shop), になって and して are usually omitted and the forms おいでいただけませんか／くださいませんか and ご来店いただけませんか／くださいませんか are used.

V-てくれないか forms are often pronounced with a rising intonation, and か can be omitted. In polite language, these forms can also be replaced by ...願えないか (lit. “can’t/couldn’t I ask...?”), as shown below.

（例）もう一度ご来店願えないでしょうか。／Could we ask you to come to our shop again?

3. V-ないか〈imperative〉

（1）おい、待 たないか。／Hey, can’t you wait?

（2）だまらないか。／Can’t you shut up?

（3）いい加減 でやめないか。／It’s about time you stopped.

（4）早 く起 きないか。／Why don’t you get up now?

（5）さっさと出 かけないか。／Why don’t you hurry up and get going?

Used to order an interlocutor to take action immediately when s/he does not seem to be doing so. For instance, (1) means “Wait!” and (2) “Shut up.”

These expressions are similar to imperatives. However, because they are used in situations where an interlocutor is reluctant to take immediate action, they often convey the sense that the speaker is irritated or upset. V-ないか is pronounced with falling intonation in a demanding tone and does not have a polite form. It is used by male speakers.

4. ...ない（か）〈confirmation〉

［N／Na　ではないか］

［A-くないか］

［V-ないか］

（1）A:彼 が犯人 じゃないですか。／Isn’t he guilty?

B:そうかな。／We’ll see.

（2）A:子供 には無理 じゃないですか。／Isn’t this impossible for a child?

B:大丈夫 ですよ。／It should be all right.

（3）A:君 にはちょっと難 しくない？／Isn’t this a bit difficult for you?

B:ええ、でもやってみます。／Yes, but I’ll try.

（4）A:この部屋 、変 な匂 いがしない？／Doesn’t this room smell strange?

B:うん、なんだかちょっと。／Yeah, a bit....

（5）A:ちょっと駅 から遠 すぎませんか。／Isn’t it a little too far from the station?

B:そうですか。歩 いて 15 分 ぐらいですけど。／Do you think so? But it’s only about a fifteen-minute walk.

（6）彼 の様子 、ちょっと変 だと思 いませんか。／Don’t you think something about him looks a bit strange?

Used to ask the listener to confirm whether or not what the speaker is thinking is correct. Even though this pattern takes negative forms such as Xじゃないか (isn’t it X?), what the speaker wants to confirm is a positive state of affairs, Xである (it is X). When the listener agrees with what the speaker says, s/he responds with はい／うん、そうだ, and when the listener disagrees, s/he uses いいえ／いや、そうではない. When the speaker wants to confirm an event that has apparently already taken place, s/he uses the ta-form, as below.

（例）A:何か物音がしなかったか。／Didn’t you hear a noise?

B:いや、僕には何も聞こえなかったけど。／No, I didn’t hear anything.

（例）A:私に電話かかって来ませんでしたか。／Wasn’t there a phone call for me?

B:いいえ。／No, there wasn’t.

5. ...ない（か）〈mild assertion〉

［N／Na　ではないか］

［A-くないか］

［V-ないか］

（1）彼 が、東大 に合格 したなんて何 かの間違 いではないか。／Wasn’t it some kind of mistake that he passed the entrance exam for Tokyo University?

（2）最近 の彼 の言動 はちょっと変 じゃないか。／Don’t you think that lately he’s been behaving a little strangely?

（3）このスープ、ちょっと、塩味 が薄 くない？／Doesn’t this soup need a little more salt?

（4）やめといたほうがよくないか。／Wouldn’t it be better if you just let it drop?

（5）そんなに働 いたら病気 にならないか。／Don’t you think that working so hard will make you sick?

Used to make a mild assertion of personal opinion. Conveys the speaker’s feeling that “I think this might be so” and is used to make an inconclusive statement that leaves room for a little doubt. As shown in (5), the use of ...ないか often implies the speaker’s anxiety or concern.

...ないか is often replaced by expressions implying conjecture or doubt, such as (の)ではないか, (の)ではないだろうか／(の)ではなかろうか／(の)ではあるまいか or ないかしら／ないかな. When talking about a past event, (では)なかったか is used, as illustrated below.

（例）昨日見かけた人、山田さんの奥さんじゃなかったか。／Wasn’t the person we saw yesterday Yamada-san’s wife?

In spoken Japanese, when ...ではないか attaches to a noun or a na-adjective it is usually replaced by じゃないか.

6. ...じゃないか→【じゃないか1】、【じゃないか2】

7. ...ではないか→【ではないか1】、【ではないか2】

<< 【ないか】 | Home | 【ないかな】 >>

【ないかしら】

The ないかしら pattern consists of the negative form of an inflected word combined with かしら, which expresses a sense of uncertainty on the part of the speaker. It is used for both self-addressed questions and questions addressed to an interlocutor. In the past, ないかしら was conventionally used by female speakers. However, now it is infrequent, and ないかな is used instead.

1. ...ないかしら〈wish, desire〉

［V-ない／V-れない かしら］

［V-てくれないかしら］

（1）またあの人 から手紙 が来 ないかしら。／I do hope I will receive a letter from him again.

（2）お金持 ちと結婚 できないかしら。／I wish I could marry a rich man.

（3）バス、すぐに来 てくれないかしら。／I do hope the bus comes soon.

（4）ちょっと手伝 ってくれないかしら。／I wonder if you could help me for a moment.

When ないかしら is used with the negative form of an action verb, the negative form of the potential V-れる, or the pattern V-てくれない, it expresses the speaker’s hope or desire. When a sentence like (4) is directly addressed to a listener, it can be understood as a request from the speaker.

2. ...ないかしら〈conjecture, concern〉

［N／Na　ではないかしら］

［A-くないかしら］

［V-ないかしら］

（1）向 こうからくる人 、鈴木 さんじゃないかしら。／Could that be Suzuki-san over there, walking this way?

（2）この着物 、私 にはちょっと派手 じゃないかしら。／I wonder if this kimono is a little too showy for me.

（3）このご飯 、ちょっとかたくないかしら。／I wonder if this rice isn’t a bit undercooked.

（4）あんなに乱暴 に扱 ったらこわれないかしら。／I wonder if it might not break if it’s handled so roughly.

Expresses a conjecture, as in “I’m not absolutely sure, but it just might be so,” or a feeling of anxiety or concern, as in “I have the sense that/I’m worried about....” If the speaker is talking to him/herself, ないかしら functions as a self-addressed question, but if this expression is used to address a listener, it means “Don’t you think so?” and functions as an appeal for the listener’s judgment.

<< 【ないかしら】 | Home | 【ないことはない】 >>

【ないかな】

...ないかな consists of the negative form of an inflected word combined with かな, which expresses uncertainty on the part of the speaker. It is used for both self-addressed questions and questions addressed to others. Unlike かしら, ないかな can be used by both male and female speakers. However, since this expression is not polite language, when it is used to address others it should be used only with interlocutors who have a close relationship to the speaker.

1. ...かな（あ）〈wish, desire〉

［V-ない／V-れない　かなあ］

［V-てくれないかなあ］

（1）早 く夏休 みにならないかなあ。／I can’t wait for summer vacation.

（2）今夜 いい夢 が見 られないかな。／I hope I’ll have a good dream tonight.

（3）息子 が一流 大学 に入 ってくれないかな。／I wish my son would enter a top-class university.

When ないかな takes the negative form of a verb referring to an action, a change of state, or existence, or the negative form of the potential V-れる, it means “I hope so” or “I wish it would happen.” Expresses the speaker’s hope, wish, or desire.

2. ...かな（あ）〈conjecture, concern〉

［N／Na　ではないかなあ］

［A-くないかなあ］

［V-ないかなあ］

（1）あの人 、森田 さんの奥 さんじゃないかな。／I wonder if that person isn’t Morita-san’s wife.

（2）彼 だったら大丈夫 じゃないかな。／If it’s him, I guess he’ll be fine with it.

（3）こっちのほうがよくないか。／Isn’t it better this way?

（4）子供 にはちょっと難 しすぎないかな。／Isn’t this a little bit too difficult for a child?

（5）この靴 、ちょっと小 さくないかな。／I wonder if these shoes aren’t a bit small.

（6）あんなことを言 って、彼女 怒 っていないかな。／I wonder if she’s upset because I said such a thing to her.

When used with the negative form of a predicate, ...かな(あ) expresses a conjecture, like “I’m not completely sure, but it just might be so,” or a feeling of anxiety or concern, like “I’m concerned/I have the sense that....” If the speaker is talking to him/herself, ...かな(あ) functions as a self-addressed question, but if this expression is addressed to a listener, it means “don’t you think so?” and functions as an inquiry regarding the listener’s judgment.

<< 【ないかな】 | Home | 【ないこともない】 >>

【ないことはない】

［V-ないことはない］

（1）A:とても明日 までには終 わりそうにないんですけど...。／There doesn’t seem to be any way for me to finish this by tomorrow....

B:いや、やる気 があればできないことはありませんよ。／Well, if you are motivated enough, it’s not impossible.

（2）A:彼女 は来 ないんじゃないか。／She isn’t coming, is she?

B:来 ないことはないと思 うよ。遅 れても必 ず来 ると言 っていたから。／I don’t think she’s not coming. She said she’d come for sure, although she might be late.

（3）A:1週間 でできますか。／Can you do this in a week?

B:できないことはないですが、かなり頑張 らないと難 しいですね。／It’s not totally impossible, but unless I try really hard, it’ll be difficult.

（4）A:行 きたくないの？／Don’t you want to go?

B:行 きたくないことはないけど、あまり気 がすすまないんだ。／It’s not that I don’t want to go, but I can’t say I’m very enthusiastic about it.

ないことはない is used in response to a statement an interlocutor has made, either to deny the statement completely, with the meaning “that is not at all the case,” or to defer making a firm judgment, with the meaning “that is partly true/possible, but not necessarily 100% so.” (1) and (2) are instances of the former use, and (3) and (4) of the latter.

More precisely, in (1) B responds to A’s negative statement, which means “I can’t do this,” by saying, “it’s not impossible for you to do it,” implying that B thinks A actually can do it. On the other hand, in (3), B’s response means “I can do it, but I won’t guarantee it,” which implies “there is a possibility that I can’t do it.”

The latter usage of ないことはない (above) can be rephrased as ないこともない. However, this is not possible for the former usage.

<< 【ないこともない】 | Home | 【ないである】 >>

【ないで】

ないで is the te-form of a negated verb. It indicates the manner, situation, or circumstances in which the action or state referred to after ないで is realized.

1. V-ないで〈attendant circumstances〉

（1）息子 は今朝 もご飯 を食 べないで出 かけた。／My son left the house again this morning without eating breakfast.

（2）彼女 は一生 結婚 しないで独身 を通 した。／She didn’t marry, she remained single for her entire life.

（3）傘 を持 たないで出 かけて雨 に降 られてしまった。／I went out without an umbrella and got rained on.

（4）予約 しないで行 ったら、満席 で入 れなかった。／I went without making a reservation, so I couldn’t get in because every seat was taken.

（5）歯 を磨 かないで寝 てはいけません。／Don’t go to bed without brushing your teeth.

Followed by a main verb clause X, V-ないでhas the meaning of “do X without doing Y.” In written language, ...ずに is also used. Cannot be replaced by V-なくて.

2. V-ないで〈instead of〉

（1）親 が来 ないで子供 が来 た。／The child came, but not the parents.

（2）ロンドンには行 かないでパリとローマに行 った。／Instead of London, I went to Paris and Rome.

（3）運動 してもちっともやせないで、かえって体重 が少 し増 えた。／Even though I’m working out, I’m not losing weight at all—instead I’ve gained a little.

（4）頑張 っているのに成績 はちっともよくならないで、むしろ下 がってきている。／Even though I’m trying my best, my marks aren’t getting any better—if anything, they’re getting worse.

V-ないで is used to make a contrastive statement about two things. Means “do such-and-such instead of doing something else,” or “such-and-such happens instead of something else.” Often implies that what follows V-ないで is a result that contradicts the speaker’s expectation or anticipation. In written language, ...ずに is also used.

It is not impossible to replace V-ないで with V-なくて. However, なくて does not convey the contrastive meaning of 代わりに (instead of). Rather, it means that two situations or states of affairs have been realized at virtually the same time. Thus, when the speaker wants to express contrastive meaning, ないで must be used.

3. V-ないで〈cause〉

（1）子供 がちっとも勉強 しないで困 っています。／I don’t know what to do, because my child isn’t studying at all.

（2）やつが来 ないで助 かった。／I was relieved that the guy didn’t come.

（3）試験 にパスできないでがっかりした。／I was disappointed because I couldn’t pass the exam.

（4）朝 起 きられないで授業 に遅 れた。／I was late for class because I couldn’t get up in the morning.

（5）大事故 にならないでよかった。／I’m glad it didn’t turn into a big accident.

Means “because someone does not do X” or “because something does not happen.” Often followed by expressions that indicate an emotion or evaluation, such as 困った (didn’t know what to do) in (1) and 助かった (was relieved) in (2), or expressions that present a chronological relationship between situations or events, as in (4). In this usage, ないで can be replaced relatively freely by なくて.

<< 【ないといい】 | Home | 【ないまでも】 >>

【ないともかぎらない】

（1）今日 は父 の命日 だから、誰 かが突然 訪 ねてこないともかぎらない。／Today is the anniversary of my father’s death, so there’s no guarantee there won’t be anyone stopping by unannounced.

（2）鍵 を直 しておかないと、また泥棒 に入 られないともかぎらない。／There is still a possibility that our house will be broken into again, unless we fix the lock.

（3）間違 えないとも限 らないので、もう一度 確認 した方 がいい。／You should check it one more time, because you can never be sure you haven’t made a mistake.

（4）事故 じゃないとも限 らないし、ちょっと電話 を入 れてみた方 がいいかもしれない。／It might well have been an accident, so maybe you should try to give them a call.

Means that something is not 100% certain. Often used to say that the listener should not complacently assume that nothing will happen but be prepared to take some kind of countermeasure. Usually attaches to negative-form expressions. However, いつ死ぬともかぎらない (below) is an exception. This is an idiomatic usage that takes an affirmative expression and means “no one knows when s/he is going to die.”

（例）人間いつ死ぬともかぎらないのだから、やりたいことはやりたい時にやった方がいい。／Since we don’t know when we’re going to die, we should do whatever we want, whenever we want.

<< 【ないともかぎらない】 | Home | 【ないものか】 >>

【ないまでも】

［V-ないまでも］

（1）毎日 とは言 わないまでも、週 に2、3度 は掃除 をしようと思 う。／I’m not saying every day, but I’d like to do the cleaning at least two or three times a week.

（2）絶対 とは言 えないまでも、成功 する確率 はかなり高 いと思 います。／Even though I cannot say it is definite, I think there is a fairly high probability that it will succeed.

（3）予習 はしないまでも、せめて授業 には出 て来 なさい。／Even if you haven’t prepared for it, you should at least come to class.

（4）授業 を休 むのなら直接 教師 に連絡 しないまでも友達 に伝言 を頼 むか何 かすべきだと思 う。／If you’re going to be absent from class, even if you can’t contact the teacher directly, you should at least ask a friend to give her a message or something.

Used with the negative form of a verb, ないまでも means “such a great extent is not necessarily expected, but at least this lesser extent is expected.” The first clause presents a situation or state of affairs of greater extent in terms of quantity or importance, followed by one of lesser extent in the second clause. As shown in (1) and (2) above, this expression is often used in the forms ...とは言わない／言えないまでも, in which case it means “one won’t/can’t ask that much, but at least this much is expected.” Expressions of obligation, such as すべきだ and ...た方がよい, or expressions of intention, command, or desire are used at the end of the sentence. V-ぬまでも conveys the same meaning but sounds more literary and formal.

<< 【ないものか】 | Home | 【なおす】 >>

【なお】

1. なお〈degree〉

（1）あなたが来 てくれればなお都合 がよい。／If you could come, it would be even better.

（2）薬 を飲 んだのに、病状 はなお悪化 した。／Even though I took the medicine, my condition kept getting worse.

（3）祖父 は老 いてもなお精力的 に仕事 を続 けている。／Even though my grandfather is getting old, he is still working energetically.

（4）退院 するまでには、なお1週間 ぐらい必要 だ。／You still need another week before you can be released from the hospital.

（5）反対 されるとなおやってみたくなる。／The more they oppose me, the more I want to do it.

Means that one thing has a comparatively higher degree of something than another, in which case it is similar to 一層 (all the more), もっと (further), さらに (still more), and そのうえ (on top of that). In other contexts, it means that the same situation continues as before, in which case it is similar to まだ (still/yet), 相変わらず (as usual), and 今もなお (still). When the first and second clauses contrast in meaning, as in (5), the meaning of なお is close to that of かえって (instead/all the more).

2. なお〈provisional clause〉

（1）入学 希望者 は期日 までに、入学金 を納入 してください。なお、いったん納入 された入学金 は、いかなる場合 にもお返 しできませんので、ご了承 ください。／Prospective students should pay the enrollment fee by the due date. Also, please note that once the enrollment fee has been paid, it is not refundable under any circumstances.

（2）毎月 の第三 水曜日 を定例 会議 の日 とします。なお、詳 しい時間 などは、1週間前 までに文書 でお知 らせすることにします。／The day for the regular meeting will be the third Wednesday of every month. Note that further details, including the time, will be communicated in writing no later than one week in advance.

（3）参加 希望者 は葉書 で申 し込 んでください。なお、希望者 多数 の場合 は、先着順 とさせていただきます。／Applicants are requested to register by postcard. Please also note that if the number of applicants exceeds the limit, selection will be made on a first-come-first-served basis.

（4）明日 は、2、3年生 の授業 は休講 になります。なお、4年 生 のみが対象 の授業 は、通常 どおり行 いますので注意 してください。／Classes for second- and third-year students will be canceled tomorrow. However, please be aware that classes for fourth-year students will be held as usual.

Used to add a proviso, supplementary explanation, exception, or special case to a topic that has just been concluded, or to present a new topic that is not directly related to the previous sentence. As illustrated in (4), when the sentence after なお adds information that is not consistent with the expectation created by the previous sentence, the meaning of なお is similar to that of ただし (but/however). なお is not used often in spoken Japanese. However, it is used often in posted notices, written announcements, explanatory notes in academic papers, and other written contexts.

<< 【なお】 | Home | 【なか】 >>

【なおす】

1. R-なおす〈volitional〉

（1）出版 の際 に論文 の一部 を書 き直 した。／I rewrote part of my thesis when I published it.

（2）俳優 がセリフを間違 えたため、同 じ場面 を3度 も撮 り直 さなければならなかった。／Since the actor bungled his lines, we had to re-shoot the same scene three times over.

（3）答案 をもう一度 見直 してください。／Please check your answers one more time.

（4）顔 を洗 って出直 して来 い。／Don’t come back till you’ve sorted yourself out. (lit. “Wash your face before you come back.”)

（5）一度 はこの大学 をやめようと思 ったが、思 い直 して卒業 まで頑張 ることにした。／I was once tempted to leave this university, but then I thought better of it and decided to hang on till graduation.

When attached to the stem of a verb expressing an intentional action, なおす means to repeat an action that was done before. It is often used when the result of the previous action is considered unfavorable and the action is repeated in order to correct the original result. Except for a few cases such as 出る (leave/go out), なおす usually attaches to transitive verbs. Other examples include 言い直す (correct oneself/restate), 考え直す (think over/reconsider), し直す (do over again/try again), 立て直す (restore/rearrange),　建て直す (rebuild),　作り直す (reconstruct/remake),　練り直す (rework/revise), 飲み直す (go somewhere else for another round of drinks),　焼き直す (reheat/rework), and やり直す (do again/start over again).

2. R-なおす〈non-volitional〉

（1）今年 になって景気 が持 ち直 した。／The economy has rebounded since the beginning of this year.

（2）病人 はだいぶ持 ち直 した。／The patient has recovered considerably.

（3）勇敢 な態度 を見 て彼 にほれ直 した。／I fell in love with him all over again when I saw his courageous attitude.

（4）部長 のことを見直 した。／I have come to think better of our department head.

When なおす is attached to the stem of a non-volitional verb, which refers to a situation or state of affairs that does not involve any intentional action on the part of a person, it expresses the meaning of a spontaneous change for the better. For example, 持ち直す means that the economy (1) or a patient’s condition (2) improves. (3) and (4) mean that someone has newly recognized someone else’s merits and reassessed his/her overall value. A limited range of verbs can combine with なおす for this usage, including those in the examples above and also 気を取り直す (take heart/pull oneself together). This usage of なおす is different from Usage 1 (above) in that there is no intention on the part of the subject to amend or redo something.

<< 【ながす】 | Home | 【なきゃ】 >>

【ながら】

1. R-ながら〈simultaneity〉

（1）音楽 を聴 きながら勉強 や仕事 をする人 のことを「ながら族 」という。／People who listen to music while studying or working are called nagarazoku.

（2）その辺 でお茶 でも飲 みながら話 しましょう。／Let’s talk somewhere over a cup of tea or something.

（3）母 は鼻歌 を歌 いながら夕飯 の用意 をしている。／My mother is humming a song while preparing dinner.

（4）よそ見 をしながら運転 するのは危険 です。／It’s dangerous to take your eyes off the road while driving.

（5）飛行機 は黒煙 をあげながら真 っ逆 さまに墜落 して行 った。／The airplane was trailing thick black smoke as it went into a nosedive.

（6）液体 はぶくぶくとガスを発生 させながら発酵 を続 けている。／The liquid is generating bubbles of gas as it continues to ferment.

Links two verbs in a sentence and expresses that two actions are proceeding concurrently. In this usage, the second verb presents the main action of the sentence, and the first verb (in the nagara clause) presents a secondary action that depicts the circumstances in which the main action is carried out. For instance, in (1), “studying or working” is the main action, and it is accompanied by the action of “listening to music.” In the same way, the incorrect ながら sentence below means that the action of getting on the train and the action of reading the book were carried out simultaneously. It cannot be interpreted to mean that the subject was reading a book on the train.

（×）電車に乗りながら本を読んだ。／I read a book while I was boarding the train.

（○）電車に乗って本を読んだ。／I got on the train and read a book.

Both of the verbs must have the same subject (see incorrect example below), and in most cases they refer to the intentional actions of a person. However, as illustrated in (5) and (6), in some cases the subject may be an airplane, a natural phenomenon, or something else capable of moving or changing by virtue of its own power.

（×）私は本を読みながら、彼はウイスキーを飲んだ。／While I was reading a book, he drank whiskey.

2. ...ながら〈appearance, manner〉

［Nながら］

［R-ながら］

（1）いつもながら見事 なお手並 みですね。／Your work is marvelous, as always.

（2）この清酒 メーカーは、昔 ながらの製法 で日本酒 をつくっている。／This refined sake maker uses the traditional method of manufacture.

（3）被害者 は涙 ながらに事件 の状況 を語 った。／In tears, the victim related the circumstances of the incident.

（4）生 まれながらのすぐれた才能 に恵 まれている。／She is gifted with a great natural talent.

（5）この子 は生 まれながらにして優 れた音楽的 感性 を備 えている。／This child was born with exceptional musical sensibility.

When attached to a noun or the stem of some verbs, ながら expresses a state or situation that continues as it is without change. For instance, 生まれながら and 昔ながら mean “just as it is, ever since a certain time,” and these expressions are similar to 生まれつき (by nature) and 昔のまま (as it was before), respectively. 涙ながらに means “in a tearful state” and can be replaced by 涙を流して (weeping). Expressions that exemplify this usage are relatively fixed, and only a small number of words, including those in the examples above, can precede ながら.

3. ...ながら（も／に）〈adversative connective〉

［N／Na　ながら］

［A-いながら］

［R-ながら］

（1）このバイクは小型 ながら馬力 がある。／In spite of its small size, this motorbike has impressive horsepower.

（2）敵 ながらあっぱれな態度 であった。／Although he was my foe, I must admit he behaved admirably.

（3）子供 ながらになかなかしっかりとした挨拶 であった。／That was quite a good speech, for a child.

（4）残念 ながら、結婚式 には出席 できません。／Unfortunately, I will not be able to attend the wedding.

（5）狭 いながらもようやく自分 の持 ち家 を手 に入 れることができた。／Cramped as it was, I was finally able to get my own home.

（6）何 もかも知 っていながら教 えてくれない。／Even though he knows everything, he won’t tell me.

（7）すぐ近 くまで行 きながら、結局 実家 には寄 らずに帰 って来 た。／I was in my parents’ neighborhood, but I ended up coming home without dropping by.

（8）学生 の身分 でありながら、高級車 で通学 している。／Even though she’s a student, she travels to school in a luxury car.

（9）細々 ながらも商売 を続 けている。／We’re continuing to run our business, although we’re just scraping by.

（10）ゆっくりながらも作業 は少 しずつ進 んでいる。／Although it’s going very slowly, the work is progressing little by little.

When ながら is attached to a noun, an i- or na-adjective, a verb stem, or an adverb (without と or に, in the case of adverbs that usually take these particles), it expresses the meaning of contradiction or opposition, similar to ...のに or ...けれども／が. It can also be combined with the particle も and used in the form ながらも. ながらに, as in (3), sounds old-fashioned and is not normally used in colloquial speech. In this so-called “adversative” usage, ながら is usually preceded by a stative predicate. On the other hand, in Usage 1, which presents “parallel/simultaneous” actions, ながら must be preceded and followed by action verbs.

4. ...とはいいながら→【とはいいながら】

<< 【なくちゃ】 | Home | 【なくては】 >>

【なくて】

［Nがなくて］

［N／Na　でなくて］

［A-くなくて］

［V-なくて］

（1）検査 の結果 、ガンでなくて安心 した。／I was relieved to find out from the test results that I don’t have cancer.

（2）結婚 した頃 は、お金 がなくて苦労 した。／When we got married, we had no money so we had a really hard time.

（3）子供 の体 が丈夫 でなくて大変 だ。／I’m having a hard time because my child’s health is not very good.

（4）思 ったより高 くなくてほっとした。／I can breathe easily now, since it’s less expensive than I had expected.

（5）ちっとも雨 が降 らなくて困 っている。／We are in a bad way because it hasn’t rained a bit.

（6）あいつが来 なくて助 かった。／I’m glad that guy didn’t come.

Means “since such-and-such did not happen/is not the case.” The clause that ends with なくて indicates the cause or reason for the situation or event described in the subsequent clause. The subsequent clause includes an expression describing the speaker’s emotion or evaluation, such as 安心する (be relieved), 困る (be in trouble/be at a loss), or 助かる (be saved some trouble).

However, なくて essentially indicates that the events or situations in the first and second clauses are realized simultaneously. Its main function is not to specify a cause or reason. Because of this, it often sounds unnatural if なくて is replaced by ないので or ないから (see examples above).

<< 【なけりゃ】 | Home | 【なさい】 >>

【なければ】

［N／Na　でなければ］

［A-くなければ］

［V-なければ］

When the verb する is used with this expression, it may take the form せねば, in addition to the usual form しなければ. In spoken Japanese, なけりゃ and/or なきゃ may also be used.

1. ...なければ...ない

（1）この映画 は成人 でなければ見 ることができない。／You can’t watch this movie unless you’re an adult.

（2）体 がじょうぶでなければこの仕事 はつとまらない。／You must have a strong physical constitution to carry out this task.

（3）私 はワープロでなければ論文 が書 けない。／I can’t write an academic paper without a word processor.

（4）背 が高 くなければファッションモデルにはなれない。／You can’t be a fashion model unless you’re tall.

（5）安 くなければ買 わない。／I won’t buy it unless it’s inexpensive.

（6）勉強 しなければ大学 には入 れない。／You can’t get into university unless you study hard.

（7）君 が手伝 ってくれなければこの仕事 は完成 しない。／I won’t be able to finish this job without your help.

なければ is used in combination with the negative form of a verb or a negative expression such as 無理だ (impossible/unreasonable) or むずかしい (difficult) at the end of the sentence. It means that when one situation or event is not realized, another situation or event is not realized either. It is also possible to say なくては...ない.

2. ...なければいけない

...なければならない

...なければだめだ

（1）教師 は生徒 に対 して公平 でなければならない。／Teachers have to be fair to students.

（2）そろそろ帰 らなければいけません。／It’s about time to go home.

（3）もっと自分 を大切 にしなければだめですよ。／You’ve got to look out for yourself more.

Means that it is necessary, essential, or obligatory to be or do something. The second clause can be omitted, as below.

（例）もう 10 時だから、そろそろ帰らなければ。／It’s already ten o’clock, so I should head home pretty soon.

なければいけない can sometimes be replaced by なくてはいけない, なくてはならない, or なくてはだめだ. However, there are some differences between these expressions, as explained below.

なければならない and なくてはならない mean that it is obligatory or necessary to be or do something, in light of conventional social wisdom or the nature of the thing in question. These expressions are usually used to state widely-held views that all people have the obligation or need to do a certain thing. On the other hand, なければいけない and なくてはいけない are often used when particular circumstances oblige or necessitate a certain action. なければだめだ and なくてはだめだ are similar to なければいけない and なくてはいけない, but the first two are more colloquial in tone.

When なければ is replaced by ねば, and ならない by ならぬ, the result is a more formal expression usually used in written Japanese.

（例）人生には我慢せねばならぬこともある。／In life, there are some things that you must endure.

Also, ならん and いかん are sometimes used instead of ならない and いけない, respectively, but the former are colloquial forms that sound rather old-fashioned.

（例）優勝するには、もっと志気を高めなければならん。／We must boost the morale of the team in order to win.

（例）少しぐらいつらくても、我慢しなければいかんよ。／Even if things are a little difficult, you must be patient.

3. ...なければV-た

（1）彼 が助 けてくれなければこの本 は完成 しなかっただろう。／Without his help, this book would not have been completed.

（2）金 目当 てでなければ、彼女 はあんな老人 とは結婚 しなかったに違 いない。／I’m sure she wouldn’t have married such an old man if she hadn’t been after his money.

（3）あの一言 さえなければ別 れることにはならなかったのに。／If I hadn’t said that one thing, I know we wouldn’t have broken up.

（4）あのミスさえしていなければ合格 できたはずなのに。／If I hadn’t made that mistake, I could have passed the exam.

（5）体 がこんなに弱 くなければ仕事 が続 けられたのに。／If my health were not so poor, I could have continued working.

Expresses the counter-factual meaning that if the circumstances had been different, there would also have been a different result. This pattern is often used in combination with sentence-final expressions such as だろう (I suppose), にちがいない (there is no doubt that...), はずだ (should be/do), and のに (I wish/if only...).

<< 【なしでは...ない】 | Home | 【なぜか】 >>

【なしに】

［Nなしに］

（1）この山 は冬 は届 け出 なしに登山 してはいけないことになっている。／This mountain is not to be climbed in winter without prior notification.

（2）断 りなしに外泊 したために、寮 の規則 で一週間 ロビーの掃除 をさせられた。／Because I stayed out overnight without permission, I had to clean the main foyer for a week, in accordance with dormitory regulations.

（3）前田 さんは忙 しい人 だから約束 なしに人 と会 ったりしないでしょう。／Since Maeda-san is a busy man, he probably doesn’t see people without an appointment.

（4）研究会 では、前置 きなしにいきなり本題 に入 らないように、皆 にわかりやすい発表 をこころがけてください。／At the research conference, don’t jump straight into the main topic without introduction; keep in mind that your presentation should be easy for everyone to follow.

（5）今度 事務所 に来 たアルバイトの高校生 はいい子 なのだが、いつもあいさつなしに帰 るので、いつ帰 ったかわからなくて困 る。／The new high school part-timer in our office is a good kid, but she always goes home without saying goodbye, so it’s a bit of a problem because we never know when she has left.

When used with action nouns such as 届け出 (notification) or 断り (permission), なしに means doing something without having done the action expressed by the noun. It is often used in the sense of “do X without doing Y, which should of course have been done in advance.”

When the noun is preceded by 何の, as in the example below, the particle も is inserted after the noun and Nなしに changes to 何のNもなしに.

（例）彼は何の連絡もなしに突然たずねてきて、金の無心をした。／He showed up all of a sudden without contacting me in advance and asked for money.

なしに is mainly a written expression. In spoken Japanese, しないで is used.

<< 【なぜかといえば...からだ】 | Home | 【など】 >>

【なぜならば...からだ】

（1）原子力 発電 には反対 です。なぜならば、絶対 に安全 だという保証 がないからです。／I am opposed to nuclear power generation. The reason is that there is no guarantee that it’s absolutely safe.

（2）殿下 のご結婚 相手 はまだ発表 するわけにはいかない。なぜならば、正式 な会議 で決 まってないからだ。／We cannot announce yet that she is going to marry His Imperial Highness. The reason is that it has not been decided at an official meeting.

（3）私 は車 は持 たないで、タクシーを利用 することにしている。なぜなら、タクシーなら、駐車場 や維持費 がかからず、結局 安上 がりだからである。／I use taxis rather than owning a car. This is because, with a taxi, there aren’t any parking or maintenance costs, so it’s cheaper in the long run.

なぜならば...からだ is used to explain the underlying circumstances or reason for what has been stated in the previous sentence. ば is sometimes omitted. This pattern tends to be used in written Japanese, or in spoken Japanese for formal situations. In daily conversation, it is more common to use なぜかというと／なぜかといえば...からだ.

<< 【なぜならば...からだ】 | Home | 【なに...ない】 >>

【など】

In casual speech, なんか is used instead of など.

1. ...など

a. Nなど

（1）ウェイトレスや皿洗 いなどのアルバイトをして学費 を貯 めた。／I did part-time jobs like waitressing and dishwashing to save money for my school expenses.

（2）A:このスーツに合 うブラウスを探 しているんですけど...。／I’m looking for a blouse that goes with this suit, but....

B:これなどいかがでしょうか。お似合 いだと思 いますよ。／How about something like this? I think it’ll look good on you.

（3）デパートやスーパーなどの大 きな店 ができたために、小 さな店 は経営 が苦 しくなった。／Since large retailers like the department store and the supermarket were built, the small shops have found it hard to stay in business.

Used to present a few main examples out of a larger range of items. Implies that there are other similar items as well.

b. V-るなどする

（1）ひげをそるなどして、もうすこし身 だしなみに気 を付 けてほしい。／I wish you’d pay a little more attention to your personal appearance, including things like shaving.

（2）時 には呼 びつけて注意 するなどしたのですが、あまり効 き目 はなかったようです。／Sometimes I did call her in and give her advice and whatever, but it doesn't seem to have been very effective.

Used to present a few main examples out of a larger range of actions. Implies that there are other similar actions as well.

2. ...などと

（1）学校 をやめるなどと言 って、みんなを困 らせている。／It’s a big headache for all of us because he’s saying things like he’s going to leave school.

（2）来年 になれば景気 が持 ち直 すから大丈夫 などとのんきなことを言 っている。／She’s making these casual comments, like everything will be all right next year since the economy is going to improve.

（3）東京 で仕事 を探 すなどと言 って、家 を出 たきり帰 ってこない。／After he said he was going to find a job in Tokyo or whatever, he left home and hasn’t been back.

などと, followed by a verb of utterance such as 言う, is used to express the gist of something that someone has said. This pattern is used for quotation, but it implies that other similar things may also have been said.

3. ...など...ない

（1）あなたの顔 など見 たくない。／I don’t even want to look at you.

（2）私 は嘘 などつきませんよ。／I would never tell a lie.

（3）賛成 するなどと言 っていない。／I never said I would agree.

（4）あんな男 となどいっしょに働 きたくない。／I don’t want to work with a guy like that.

（5）そんなことで驚 いたりなどしないさ。／I just wouldn’t be surprised by such a thing.

（6）別 にあなたを非難 してなどいませんよ。／I’m not blaming you or anything, you know.

（7）こんな難 しい問題 が私 のようなものになど解 けるはずがありません。／I’m not at all the person to be able to answer such a difficult question.

（8）こんな結果 になるなどとは考 えてもみませんでした。／I never thought it would come to something like this.

など attaches to a variety of constituents, including nouns, verbs, and noun + particle combinations, and is followed by a negative expression. This pattern expresses not only the negation of a certain thing, situation, or event but also the speaker’s feeling of contempt, modesty, surprise, etc. with respect to whatever is marked by など.

For instance, (7) simultaneously conveys the meaning that there is no way the speaker could ever answer such a difficult question and the sense that the speaker is humble and does not hold too high an opinion of him/herself.

4. ...など...V-るものか

（1）そんな馬鹿 げた話 などだれが信 じるものか。／Who would ever swallow such a ridiculous story?

（2）お前 になど教 えてやるものか。／Why would I ever tell someone like you?

（3）あんなやつを助 けてなどやるものか。／He’s the last guy I’d ever help!

（4）これくらいの怪我 でだれが死 になどするものか。／No one ever died from such a minor injury!

（5）私 の気持 ちがあなたなどに分 かるものですか。／How on earth would someone like you ever understand my feelings?

May be preceded by a variety of constituents, including nouns, verbs, and noun + particle combinations. Expresses a strong negation, as well as the speaker’s feeling that the person, thing, or situation marked by など is trivial and worthy only of contempt.

<< 【なにげない】 | Home | 【なににもまして】 >>

【なにしろ】

（1）なにしろ彼 は頭 がいいから、私 がどんなに頑張 っても言 い負 かされてしまう。／After all, he is smart, so no matter how hard I try, I lose every argument.

（2）なにしろ観光 シーズンですからどのホテルも予約 は取 れないと思 います。／At any rate, this is the tourist season, so I don’t think you’ll be able to get reservations at any hotel.

（3）もっと早 くお便 りしようと思 っていたのですが、なにしろ忙 しくてゆっくり机 に向 かう暇 もありませんでした。／I meant to write to you much earlier, but what with my busy schedule, I haven’t even had time to sit down at my desk.

（4）どこにも異常 はないかもしれないが、なにしろ大至急 検査 をしてみる必要 がある。／There may be no problem anywhere, but still it’s necessary to do an examination as soon as possible.

Used to emphasize a certain thing, at least for the time being, while leaving various other possibilities aside. Often used to state the reason for something, in patterns such as なにしろ...から and なにしろ...て. Similar to なんにしても (in any case) and とにかく (anyway).

<< 【なにより】 | Home | 【なら1】 >>

【なまじ】

（1）なまじ急 いでタクシーに乗 ったために、渋滞 に巻 き込 まれてかえって遅刻 してしまった。／Because I was in a rush and jumped into a taxi, I ended up getting caught in a traffic jam and arriving late.

（2）今 の段階 でなまじ私 が発言 すれば、かえって事態 を混乱 させることになりかねない。／If I were to make an incomplete comment at this stage, it would only confuse the situation.

（3）なまじ自信 があったのがわざわいして、重大 なミスを犯 してしまった。／Overconfidence in my own ability led me to make to a serious mistake.

（4）なまじ彼女 の状況 が理解 できるだけに、こんな仕事 はとても頼 みづらい。／It’s because I understand her current situation that it’s hard to ask her to take this job on.

（5）なまじの知識 は役 に立 たないどころか邪魔 になることもある。／A little knowledge is not just useless; it can even be a hindrance.

（6）彼女 の前 ではなまじなことは言 わない方 がいい。彼女 はこの問題 を徹底的 に調 べているらしいから、我々 もそのつもりで準備 しなければ負 けてしまう。／We shouldn’t say anything half-baked in front of her. It sounds like she’s been investigating this problem thoroughly, so if we don’t prepare with that in mind, we’ll be outplayed.

Expresses a situation in which something positive ends inconclusively or only halfway, without displaying its full value. Used to say that something with an intrinsically positive value actually results in a negative outcome.

When なまじ modifies a noun, it is used in the patterns なまじのN and なまじなN, as in (5) and (6). In these cases, なまじ can be replaced by 中途半端な (halfway, unfinished). For instance, (5) means that knowledge, which is usually a good thing to have, instead becomes a hindrance because it is superficial.

<< 【なまじ】 | Home | 【なら2】 >>

【なら1】

When なら is attached directly to a noun, it expresses the topic of a sentence. The form ならば may also be used.

1. Nなら

（1）A:めがねはどこかな。／I wonder where my glasses are.

B:めがねならタンスの上 に置 いてありましたよ。／Your glasses? They were on top of the dresser.

（2）A:アルバイトを雇 うには金 がかかりますよ。／Hiring a part-time worker will be expensive.

B:お金 のことなら心配 しなくていいですよ。何 とかなりますから。／If it’s a matter of money, you don’t have to worry. We can manage.

（3）A:佐藤 さん見 ませんでしたか。／Have you seen Sato-san?

B:佐藤 さんなら、図書館 にいましたよ。／Sato-san? He was in the library.

（4）時間 ならば十分 ありますから、ご心配 なく。／As for time, we have plenty of it, so don’t worry.

（5）例 のことならもう社長 に伝 えてあります。／If you mean that thing we talked about, I’ve already informed the company president.

なら is used when the speaker takes something that the addressee has said, something mentioned during discussion of the previous topic, or something that can be predicted from the current situation, makes it a new topic, and then continues talking about it. Often used when the speaker adopts as a topic something that was previously brought up by the addressee.

なら can often be replaced by the topic marker は. However, なら essentially has the hypothetical meaning “if N were the topic,” while は does not have such meaning. Therefore, when なら is replaced by は, the meaning of the sentence changes slightly. なら is synonymous with Nだったら, and these two expressions are interchangeable.

2. NならNだ

（1）山 ならやっぱり富士山 だ。／When it comes to mountains, naturally it has to be Fuji-san (Mt. Fuji).

（2）ストレス解消法 ならゴルフに限 る。／If you’re looking for a way to get rid of stress, nothing beats golf.

（3）酒 ならなんといってもここの地酒 が一番 だ。／When it comes to sake, the locally brewed sake here is unquestionably the best.

（4）カキ料理 なら広島 が本場 だ。／If you want good oyster cuisine, Hiroshima is the place to go.

Nなら can be followed by Nだ, or by expressions such as Nに限る (there’s nothing better than N), Nが一番だ (N is the best), and Nがいい (N is good). Nなら is used to define the range of the topic and then describe the most highly evaluated item within that range. In this usage, Nなら can be replaced by Nは without any great change in meaning.

3. ...（助 詞 ）なら

（1）あの人 となら結婚 してもいい。／I wouldn’t mind getting married, if it were to him.

（2）フランス語 はだめですが、英語 でなら会話 ができます。／I’m no good at French, but in English, I can carry on a conversation.

（3）あと一人 だけなら入場 できます。／Only one more person can get in.

（4）A:足 の具合 はいかがですか。／How is your leg?

B:ゆっくりとなら歩 けるようになりました。／If I go slowly, I can walk now.

（5）仕事 の後 なら時間 があります。／If it’s after work, I’ll have time.

When なら follows a noun, adverb, or noun/particle combination, it expresses the meaning that “Y doesn’t hold in other cases, but in the case of X, Y can be realized.” The Y clause that follows なら usually represents something desirable, and this pattern is used when the speaker actively selects an X that makes Y possible. This usage of なら is similar to the contrastive use of は. However, なら can be combined with interrogative words, while は cannot.

（○）何時なら都合がいいですか。／What time would be convenient for you?

（○）誰となら結婚してもいいですか。／Who would it have to be, in order for you to consider getting married?

（×）何時は都合がいいですか。／What is the time convenient for you?

（×）誰とは結婚してもいいですか。／I wouldn’t mind marrying who.

<< 【なら1】 | Home | 【なら3】 >>

【なら2】

［N／Na　なら］

［N／Na　だった（の）なら］

［A-い／A-かった　（の）なら］

［V-る／V-た　（の）なら］

When combined with the dictionary form or the ta-form of a predicate, なら expresses the meaning “if the actual situation or circumstances were like that.” The forms のならば, のなら, and ならば are also used. In spoken Japanese, の often becomes ん.

Although there is often no clear difference in meaning related to the presence or absence of の, のなら tends to be used in response to a statement on the part of the addressee, or a concrete situation, and conveys the meaning “if you say so,” “if that is true,” or “if that is the actual situation.” On the other hand, when の is not used, なら tends to convey the meaning of “generally, in such cases” or “if/when someone does so.” When (の)なら is combined with a noun or a na-adjective, の is often omitted. When (の)なら is combined with a verb or an i-adjective, it is synonymous with のだったら, and these two are interchangeable. However, の in のだったら cannot be omitted.

（×）知っているだったら教えてほしい。／If you happen know, I want you to tell me.

（○）知っている（の）なら教えてほしい。／If you happen to know, I want you to tell me.

知っているのだったら教えてほしい。／If you happen to know, I want you to tell me.

1. ...（の）なら〈hypothetical condition〉

（1）A:風邪 をひいてしまいまして。／Unfortunately, I’ve caught a cold....

B:風邪 なら早 く帰 って休 んだほうがいいよ。／If you’ve got a cold, you should go home early and rest.

（2）彼女 のことがそんなに嫌 いなら別 れたらいい。／If you dislike her so much, you should break up with her.

（3）A:頭 がずきずき痛 むんです。／I have a splitting headache.

B:そんなに痛 い（の）なら早 く帰 ったほうがいいですよ。／If it hurts that much, you should go home early.

（4）行 きたくない（の）ならやめておいたらどうですか。／If you don’t want to go, why don’t you just say no?

（5）真相 を知 っている（の）なら私 に教 えてほしい。／If you know the truth, I’d like you to tell me.

（6）郵便局 に行 く（の）なら、この手紙 を出 してきてくれますか。／If you’re going to the post office, could you mail this letter for me?

（7）あなたがそんなに反対 する（の）ならあきらめます。／If you’re so against it, I’ll give up on it.

（8）A:ちょっと買 い物 に行 ってくる。／I’m off to do a little shopping.

B:買 い物 に行 く（の）ならついでにおしょうゆを買 ってきてちょうだい。／If you’re going shopping, please pick up some soy sauce while you’re out.

（9）A:沖縄 ではもう梅雨 に入 ったそうですよ。／I hear the rainy season in Okinawa has already started.

B:沖縄 で梅雨 に入 ったのなら、九州 の梅雨入 りも間近 ですね。／If the rainy season has started in Okinawa, it’ll start soon in Kyushu, too.

（10）二人 が昼 からこの店 で会 っていたのなら、二人 には午前中 のアリバイはないことになる。／If the two of them were with each other for (part of) the afternoon in this shop, that means they don’t have an alibi for the morning.

When combined with the dictionary form or the ta-form of a predicate, (の)なら expresses a hypothetical condition and means “if that is the actual situation” or “if that is true.” A speaker uses (の)なら to state his/her own opinion or view, to make a request, or to give advice to the addressee, in light of something the addressee has just said or the situation at hand.

なら cannot be used to refer to things that occur as a matter of course or events that arise naturally with the passage of time. In such cases, expressions like たら, ば, and/or と must be used instead. Also, expressions that merely state a fact cannot be used at the end of a sentence with なら. Expressions indicating a judgment, intention, command, request/demand, suggestion, evaluation, or some other subjective attitude on the part of the speaker must be used.

（×）春が来るなら花が咲きます。／If spring comes, flowers bloom.

（×）雨が降るなら道がぬかります。／If rain falls, the road gets muddy.

（○）春が｛来たら／来れば／来ると｝花が咲きます。／When spring comes, flowers bloom.

（○）雨が｛降ったら／降ると／降れば｝道がぬかります。／When it rains, the road gets muddy.

（○）《午後から雨が降ると聞いて》雨が降る（の）なら、傘を持って行こう。（意志）／《having heard that it will rain in the afternoon》If it’s going to rain, I’ll take an umbrella. (intention)

たら, ば and と are used when the condition expressed in the first clause happens prior to the second clause and the situation or event in the second clause is realized as a result. On the other hand, なら can be used even when the situation in the second clause is realized first and the situation in the conditional clause follows.

（例）イタリアに行ったらイタリア語を習いなさい。（イタリアに行ってからイタリアで習う）／When you go to Italy, study Italian. (= study the language in Italy, after arriving there)

（例）イタリアに行くならイタリア語を習いなさい。（イタリアへ行く前に自分の国で習う）／If you’re going to Italy, study Italian. (= study the language in your own country, before going to Italy)

2. ...（の）なら〈counter-factual〉

（1）電話 をくれるのなら、もう少 し早 い時間 に電話 してほしかった。／If you were going to call me, I wish you had called a little earlier.

（2）神戸 に来 ていたのなら、電話 してくれればよかったのに。／If you were in Kobe, you should have phoned me.

（3）あいつが来 るのならこのパーティには来 なかったんだが。／If I’d known he was coming, I wouldn’t have come to this party.

（4）結婚式 に出席 する（の）なら黒 いスーツを買 うのだが。／If I were going to a wedding, I would buy myself a black suit.

When (の)なら is used in the pattern X(の)ならY, either Y alone or both X and Y may contradict the given facts. In the first case, (の)なら is used when the speaker learns a new fact, X, and the pattern means “if I had known X (= factual), I could have done Y (= counter-factual), but since I didn’t know X, I didn’t do Y.” In the second case, (の)なら means “if X is done (= counter-factual), Y should be done (= counter-factual), but since X is actually not done, Y is not done either.” (1)-(3) illustrate the first case, and (4) illustrates the second case. For instance, (2), in which X is factual but Y is not, conveys the sense that when the speaker found out that the addressee had come to Kobe, s/he felt critical or regretful of the fact that the addressee hadn’t called him/her (you should have called me...). (4), in which both X and Y are counter-factual, means “if I were going to attend a wedding, I would buy a black suit, but since I’m not actually going to a wedding, I’m not going to buy one.”

(の)なら cannot be replaced by たら or ば in (1)-(4), because the meanings of these sentences are not the same as those of counter-factual conditional sentences with たら or ば. In counter-factual conditionals with たら or ば, X and Y are both counter-factual and X must occur prior to Y. On the other hand, in (1)-(3) only Y is counter-factual, and although both X and Y are counter-factual in (4), if X and Y were both realized in these sentences, the sequential relationship between them would be that X occurs after Y: “buy a black suit and then attend a wedding.” Such a relation can only be expressed by なら. Neither たら nor ば can be used instead.

（例）先週、神戸に来ていたのなら案内してあげたのに。／If you were in Kobe last week, I could have shown you around. (Means “I didn’t know you were in Kobe last week, so I couldn’t show you around.” X (you were in Kobe last week) is factual, while Y (I could have shown you around) is counter-factual.)

（例）先週、神戸に来て｛いれば／いたら｝案内してあげたのに。／If you had come to Kobe last week, I would have shown you around. (Means “you didn’t come to Kobe last week, so I couldn’t show you around.” Both X and Y are counter-factual.)

（例）結婚式に出るなら黒いスーツを買ったのだけど。／If I were going to a wedding, I would have bought a black suit. (Means “I’m not planning to attend a wedding, so I didn’t buy a black suit.” Both X and Y are counter-factual, and if both were realized, X would follow Y.)

（例）黒いスーツを買って｛いれば／いたら｝結婚式に出たのだが。／If I had bought a black suit, I would have attended the wedding. (Means “I hadn’t bought a black suit, so I didn’t attend the wedding.” Both X and Y are counter-factual, and if both were realized, Y would follow X.)

3. V-る（の）なら...がいい

（1）靴 を買 うならイタリア製 がいい。／If you’re buying shoes, Italian-made ones are the best.

（2）食事 をするなら、このレストランがいいよ。／If you’re going to eat out, I’d recommend this restaurant.

（3）英語 を習 うならアメリカかカナダに留学 することをすすめたい。／If you want to learn English, I’d suggest studying in the United States or Canada.

（4）A:大学 を卒業 したら留学 したいと思 っているんだ。／I’m thinking of going abroad to study after I graduate from college.

B:留学 するのならオーストラリアがいいよ。／If you’re going to study abroad, I’d recommend Australia.

When (の)なら is followed by expressions such as がいい and をすすめる, its function is to recommend the best way or method of doing something. This pattern is often used in advertising slogans and/or commercials.

When talking about an action in general, rather than a particular person’s action, の is usually omitted. The meaning of V-るなら...がいい is similar to the meaning of expressions in which なら and は are used as topic markers, such as Nなら...がいい and Nは...がいい.

（例）靴を買うならイタリア製がいい。／If you’re buying shoes, Italian-made ones are the best.

（例）靴ならイタリア製がいい。／When it comes to shoes, Italian-made ones are the best.

（例）靴はイタリア製がいい。／As for shoes, Italian-made ones are the best.

4. V-る（の）なら　...しろ／...するな

（1）何事 もやるなら最後 まで徹底的 にやれ。／Whatever you do, follow it through to the very end.

（2）女性 と付 き合 うなら真剣 に付 き合 いなさい。／If you’re going out with a girl, be serious about it.

（3）留学 するならいい加減 な気持 ちではするな。／If you’re going to study abroad, don’t do it halfway.

（4）私 のことを笑 うなら勝手 に笑 えばいい。／If you want to laugh at me, feel free to do so.

（5）泣 きたいのなら好 きなだけ泣 けばいい。／If you feel like crying, go ahead and cry your heart out.

When (の)なら is preceded and followed by the same verb, its function is to give instructions about how something should be done. (の)なら may be followed by expressions of command or prohibition, as well as expressions of suggestion or recommendation such as すればいい. (4) and (5) convey the meaning “if you want to do so, go ahead and do as you please.”

When this pattern is used to mean “when something is done in general,” なら is usually not preceded by の. However, when it is used in response to an utterance or intention of a particular person, with the meaning “if you have such an intention” or “if you want to do so,” it may take the form のなら, as shown in (5).

5. ...（の）なら...で

［Na ならNa で］

［A（の）ならAで］

［V（の）ならVで］

（1）嫌 なら嫌 で、そう言 ってくれたらよかったのに。今 となっては遅 すぎるよ。／If you didn’t like it, you should have told me so. It’s too late now.

（2）金 がないならないで、人生 何 とかなるものさ。／So what if there’s no money—life will still turn out all right.

（3）会社 を辞 める（の）なら辞 めるで、それからあとの身 の振 り方 ぐらい考 えておくべきだった。／Before I up and left the company, I should have at least considered what I would do next.

（4）遅 くなる（の）なら遅 くなるで、ちゃんと連絡 ぐらいしてくれればいいのに。／If you knew you’d be late, you could have at least let me know.

（5）行 かない（の）なら行 かないで、ちゃんと断 わりの連絡 だけはしておいたほうがいい。／If you’re not going, that’s fine, but you should at least make sure to send your regrets.

When the same word is repeated before and after (の)なら, the speaker is acknowledging a certain situation to be as it is. S/he then states what kind of action should be taken under such circumstances, or expresses criticism or regret that such an action has not been taken.

6. ...（の）なら...と

［NならN（だ）と］

［Na ならNa（だ）と］

［A（の）ならAと］

［V（の）ならVと］

（1）欠席 なら欠席 と前 もって知 らせておいてください。／If you’re going to be absent, please let me know in advance.

（2）そうならそうと言 ってほしかった。／I just wanted you to tell me the truth.

（3）嫌 なら嫌 だとはっきり言 ってくれればいいのに。／If you don’t like it, you should come straight out and tell me so.

（4）好 きなら好 きとはっきり言 っておけばよかった。／If I knew I liked him, I should have told him directly.

（5）都合 が悪 い（の）なら悪 いと言 ってくれればよかったのに。／If it wasn’t convenient for you, you should have said so.

（6）これからは来 ない（の）なら来 ないとちゃんと事前 に連絡 して下 さいね。／From now on, please be sure to contact me in advance when you’re not coming.

（7）行 く（の）なら行 く、行 かない（の）なら行 かないとちゃんと言 ってくれなければ困 るじゃないですか。／Can’t you see what trouble you cause for me if you don’t tell me whether or not you’re coming?

The same word is repeated before and after (の)なら, and ...とis followed by expressions of utterance such as 言う and 連絡する. This pattern expresses the speaker’s attitude that the listener or a third person should clearly indicate his/her intentions regarding his/her own actions.

This pattern is usually used to criticize someone else for not expressing his/her intentions clearly, or to advise him/her that s/he should have indicated them clearly. However, it can also be used by the speaker to express his/her regret that s/he didn’t make his/her own intentions clear, as shown in (4).

7. ...（の）ならべつだが

［N／Na　ならべつだが］

［A／V　（の）ならべつだが］

（1）そんなに勉強 がつまらない（の）なら別 だが、自分 の心構 えについても反省 してみてはどうだろうか。／It would be a different matter if your studies were really that boring, but how about reflecting on your own attitude for a change?

（2）やめたい（の）なら別 だが、もし続 けたい（の）ならもう少 し基礎的 なところから勉強 し直 した方 がいい。／If you want to quit, that’s fine, but if you intend to continue, you ought to go back to the basics and start studying all over again.

（3）本気 で頑張 る気 があるのなら別 だがいい加減 な気持 ちでやっているならやめたほうがいい。／It’s all right if you’re serious about doing this, but if you’re just fooling around, then you’d better quit.

（4）自分 のことなら話 は別 だが、人 のことにそんなに気 を揉 んでも仕方 がないだろう。／If it were your own problem, it’d be a different matter, but there’s no use worrying so much about other people.

（5）どうしても嫌 なら話 は別 だが、我慢 して今 の会社 にとどまるのも一 つの考 えだ。／If you really can’t stand it, that’d be different, but one idea to consider is hanging in there and staying with the company.

(の)ならべつだが assumes two distinct situations. It is used to introduce one situation as being inapplicable and to state the speaker’s opinion concerning the other possible situation. It is often followed by expressions intended to influence the listener, such as criticism, warning, or advice. As shown in (4) and (5), (の)ならべつだが may also take the form ...なら話は別だが．

8. ...というのなら

（1）A:明日 はほかに用事 があってお邪魔 できないのですが。／I have something else to do tomorrow, so I can’t come to visit you.

B:来 たくないと言 うのなら来 てもらわなくてもいい。／If you’re saying you don’t want to come, that’s fine with me.

（2）責任 をもつと言 うのなら、信頼 して任 せてみてはどうですか。／If she says she’ll take responsibility, why don’t you trust her and let her handle it?

（3）子供 が大事 だと言 うのなら、もっと家庭 を大切 にしなくてはだめだ。／If you say your child is important, then you have to take better care of your family.

（4）経営 に行 き詰 まっているというのならあんな派手 な商売 はできないはずだ。／If it’s true that their business is at a standstill, then they shouldn’t be able to put on such a flashy sales campaign.

というのなら is used to indicate a judgment on the part of the speaker regarding the content of the preceding conversation. It is followed by an expression of permission, advice, or suggestion directed toward the listener, or an inference made by the speaker. ということなら can also be used.

9. ...ということなら

（1）癌 だということなら退院 させてくれるはずがない。／If it really is cancer, there’s no way that they’ll release you from the hospital.

（2）自分 たちでやるということなら、やらせてみてはどうか。／If they say they’ll do it by themselves, how about letting them go ahead and do it?

（3）期限内 にできないということなら、ほかの業者 に頼 むことにしよう。／If he says they can’t finish it by the deadline, then we’ll ask another dealer.

Expresses the speaker’s response to something a third party has said. Used in more or less the same way as というのなら. However, というのなら can be used to respond to something said by either a direct addressee or a third person who is not present, in which cases it means “if you say so” or “if s/he says so,” respectively. ということなら usually means the latter only.

10. どうせ...（の）なら→【どうせ】2

11. ...ものなら→【ものなら】1

12. V-ようものなら→【ものなら】2

<< 【なら2】 | Home | 【ならいい】 >>

【なら3】

［N／Na　（だった）なら］

［A-い／A-かった　なら］

［V-る／V-た　なら］

In contrast with Usage 2 of なら, Usage 3 does not take the pattern のなら. Usage 3 is used in the form なら or ならば and is equivalent to the ba-form of N/Naだ. However, it can also be used after the dictionary form or the ta-form of a verb or i-adjective. When Usage 3 of なら is preceded by a verb or an i-adjective, it can be replaced by ば or たら with very little change in meaning. たなら is an emphatic form of たら and sounds a little old-fashioned.

1. N／Na　なら（ば）

（1）10 人 一緒 なら団体 の割 り引 き料金 になる。／Groups of ten get a reduced rate.

（2）まわりがもう少 し静 かならば落 ち着 いて勉強 できるのですが。／If it were a little quieter around here, I could settle down and study.

（3）東京 ならこんなに安 い家賃 で家 は借 りられません。／If this were Tokyo, you would never be able to rent a house for such a low price.

（4）その話 が本当 なら大 変 なことになりますよ。／If that story is true, you’re going to be in big trouble.

（5）私 があなたならそんなふうには考 えなかったと思 う。／If I were you, I wouldn’t have thought like that.

（6）日曜日 、お天気 ならハイキングに行 きましょう。／If the weather’s nice on Sunday, let’s go hiking.

N/Naなら(ば) is the ba-form of N/Naだ. It expresses a hypothetical condition, such as “if such-and-such was the case” or “supposing that...,” or a counter-factual condition, such as “if the circumstances were the other way around.” In formal written Japanese, であれば, which is the ba-form of である, can also be used. N/Naなら(ば) can be replaced by だったら.

The difference between Usage 3 of なら and Usage 1 is that Usage 1 attaches to nouns only and means “if N were the topic,” while Usage 3 expresses a supposition (if it were the case that...) regarding something that is either not known to be true, or is contrary to fact. However, in many cases it is difficult to decide which usage of なら actually applies.

2. NがNならNはNだ

（1）銀座 が東京 の中心 なら心斎橋 は大阪 の中心 だ。／If Ginza is the center of Tokyo, Shinsaibashi is the center of Osaka.

（2）パリが芸術 の都 なら、ロンドンは金融 の都 だ。／If Paris is the city of art, London is the city of finance.

（3）兄 が努力型 の秀才 なら弟 は天才型 の秀才 だ。／If the older brother is the hard-working prodigy type, the younger brother is the genius type.

NがNならNはNだ is used to compare people or things that have contrasting characteristics. Each person or thing is likened to something different (using different terms), and the pattern itself means “if ...can be expressed as ..., then ...can be expressed as ....”

3. NがNならNもNだ

（1）親 が親 なら子 も子 だ。／What can you expect from a child with parents like that? (lit. Like parent, like child.)

（2）先生 が先生 なら学生 も学生 だ。／What can you expect from students with a teacher like that?

（3）亭主 が亭主 なら女房 も女房 だ。／Both the husband and wife are hopeless.

（4）アメリカもアメリカなら日本 も日本 だ。／Both America and Japan are equally to blame.

The N slots in the pattern NがNならNもNだ are filled by pairs of nouns that represent people in a relationship, such as “husband” and “wife,” or institutions, organizations, etc. This pattern expresses a negative evaluation of the behavior or attitude of the people or organizations in question and means “both of them are equally terrible” or “they’re a totally outrageous bunch of people.” It is used to describe two parties with undesirable characteristics or attitudes, such as being thoughtless, lazy, impertinent, or rude. This pattern also takes the form N1もN1ならN2もN2だ, as in (4).

4. ...なら（ば）

［A／V　なら（ば）］

（1）今年 も真夏 の日照 時間 が短 い／短 かったならば米不足 の問題 は深刻 だ。／If there are too few hours of mid-summer sunlight again this year, the shortage of rice will be a serious problem.

（2）この機会 を逃 す／逃 したならばもう2度 と彼 には会 えないだろう。／If I miss this opportunity, I’m afraid I’ll never be able to see him again.

（3）このまま不況 が続 く／続 いたなら失業 問題 は深刻 になる。／If the recession continues like this, the unemployment problem will become critical.

（4）今後 1週間 雨 が降 らない／降 らなかったならば水不足 になる。／If it doesn’t rain in the next week, there will be a shortage of water.

Used with the dictionary form or the ta-form of an i-adjective or verb, なら(ば) means “in the event that such a situation is realized.” It is a hypothetical conditional used to state an assumption about a situation that may be realized in the future, as well as a prediction about something that will happen if that situation is realized. なら(ば) is similar in meaning to するなら and したなら. It is a literary expression that often appears in editorial or academic texts. It can be replaced by ば and たら, and in spoken Japanese the latter are more commonly used.

（5）今年 も真夏 の日照 時間 が｛短 ければ／短 かったら｝米不足 の問題 は深刻 だ。／If there are too few hours of mid-summer sunlight again this year, the shortage of rice will be a serious problem.

（6）この機会 を｛逃 せば／逃 したら｝もう2度 と彼 には会 えないだろう。／If I miss this opportunity, I’m afraid I’ll never be able to see him again.

（7）このまま不況 が｛続 けば／続 いたら｝失業 問題 は深刻 になる。／If the recession continues like this, the unemployment problem will become critical.

（8）今後 1週間 雨 が｛降 らなければ／降 らなかったら｝水不足 になる。／If it doesn’t rain in the next week, there will be a shortage of water.

5. ...たなら

［N／Na　だったなら］

［A-かったなら］

［V-たなら］

（1）私 が全能 の神様 だったなら、あなたを助 けてあげられるのに。／If I were the Almighty God, I could help you.

（2）もう少 し発見 が早 かったなら助 かったのに。／If only she had been found a little earlier, she would have been saved.

（3）困 ることがあったならいつでも相談 に来 い。／Come and talk to me anytime you have a problem.

（4）もしも私 に翼 があったなら大空 を自由 にかけまわりたい。／If I had wings, I would like to fly freely all over the open sky.

（5）《歌詞 》あの坂 を越 えたなら幸 せが待 っている。／《song》Happiness awaits over that hill.

...たなら, an emphatic form of たら that sounds a little old-fashioned, is used to express hypothetical or counter-factual conditions. It is often used in the lyrics of popular songs, but in daily conversation たら is more common.

6. V-るなら〈viewpoint〉

（1）事情 を知 らない人 の目 から見 るなら、少 しおおげさな感 じがするかもしれない。／In the eyes of someone who doesn’t know the actual situation, it may seem a bit blown out of proportion.

（2）私 に言 わせるなら、この作品 はあまり面白 いとは思 えない。／If you ask me, I don’t think this piece is all that interesting.

（3）戦前 と比 べるなら生活 レベルはずいぶん向上 したといえるだろう。／We can say that the standard of living has improved considerably, compared with before the war.

（4）一部 を除 くなら、彼 の意見 は正 しいと思 う。／Except for some parts, I think his opinion is correct.

When the dictionary form of verbs such as 見る, 言う, and 比べる is followed by なら, the result is an idiomatic expression that indicates the viewpoint from which a judgment or opinion (given in the subsequent clause) is stated. This pattern tends to be used in written Japanese. たら／と／ば can also be used with these verbs, and the resulting forms are, for the most part, interchangeable with V-るなら. Similar expressions include ...によるなら and ...を別にするなら.

<< 【なり1】 | Home | 【なり3】 >>

【なり2】

1. ...なり

［Nなり］

［V-るなり］

（1）何 かお飲物 なりお持 ちしましょうか。／Shall I bring you a drink or something?

（2）そんなに忙 しいんだったら友達 になり手伝 ってもらったらいいのに。／If you are so busy, you should ask a friend or somebody to help you.

（3）そんなに心配 なら先生 に相談 するなりしてみてはどうですか。／If you are worrying that much, why don’t you do something like consult your teacher?

（4）壁 に絵 を飾 るなりしたらもっと落 ちつくと思 いますよ。／I think doing something like putting pictures on the wall would calm the mood more.

Attaches to a variety of elements such as nouns and verbs and is used to refer to one possibility among several others as an example.

2. V-るなりV-ないなり

（1）行 くなり行 かないなりはっきり決 めてほしい。／I want you to decide whether you are going to go or not.

（2）やるなりやらないなり、はっきりした態度 をとらなければならない。／Whether you do it or not, you must make up your mind.

（3）来 るなり来 ないなりをきちんと連絡 してもらわなければ困 ります。／If you won’t give me a definite answer as to whether or not you’re coming, I’ll have trouble.

With an affirmative form of a verb followed by a negative form of the same verb, expresses the meaning of choosing one over the other. Followed by expressions indicating that choosing one over the other is required, desired, or suggested. Since V-るなりV-ないなり involves the speaker’s feeling to force the other party to choose one over the other, this expression could be considered rude if used inappropriately.

（×）参加なさるなりなさらないなりをお知らせください。／Please let me know whether you will attend or not.

（○）参加なさるかどうかをお知らせください。／Kindly let me know whether you will be attending or not.

3. ...なり...なり

［NなりNなり］

［V-るなりV-るなり］

（1）彼 の父親 なり母親 なりに相談 しなければならないだろう。／I should probably consult an appropriate person like his father or mother, for instance.

（2）東京 なり大阪 なり、好 きなところで生活 すればいい。／I don’t care whether it will be in Tokyo or in Osaka or wherever—live someplace you like.

（3）叱 るなり誉 めるなり、はっきりとした態度 をとらなければだめだ。／Whether you scold or praise him, you need to have a clear idea of your own stance.

NなりNなり and V-るなりV-るなり express the meaning of choosing between two things in the same group. It implies that there are some other possibilities in addition to the two.

4. ...なりなんなり

［N／V　なりなんなり］

（1）チューリップなりなんなり、少 し目立 つ花 を買 ってきて下 さい。／Please go buy some flowers—like tulips—that are a little showy.

（2）ここは私 が支払 いますからコーヒーなりなんなり好 きなものを注文 して下 さい。／I’ll pay for you here, so please order coffee or anything you like.

（3）転地 療養 するなり何 なりして少 し体 を休 めたほうがいい。／You should go somewhere for a change or do something to take at least a little rest.

（4）この部屋 は寒 そうだから、カーペットを入 れるなり何 なりしなければいけないね。／We need to carpet this room or do something because it seems cold.

N/Vなりなんなり expresses the meaning that anything would be fine if it is similar to what the speaker mentions. When it refers to a place, ...なりどこなり is used.

（例）外国なりどこなり、好きなところへ行ってしまえ。／Whether it’s a foreign country or somewhere else, go anywhere you like.

<< 【なんという】 | Home | 【なんとかいう】 >>

【なんとか】

1. なんとか〈volitional〉

（1）なんとかして山田 さんを助 け出 そう。／Let’s save Yamada-san somehow.

（2）このゴミの山 を早 くなんとかしないといけない。／We must somehow get rid of this pile of garbage soon.

（3）早 くなんとか手 を打 たないと、大 変 なことになりますよ。／If we don’t do something immediately, the situation will get out of hand.

（4）お忙 しいことは承知 していますが、何 とか明日 までに仕上 げていただけないでしょうか。／Although I understand that you are busy, could you possibly manage to finish this by tomorrow?

（5）A:あしたまでに仕上 げるのはちょっと無理 ですね。／It’s impossible for me to get it done by tomorrow.

B:そこを何 とかできないでしょうか。何 とかお願 いしますよ。／Couldn’t you manage to do that somehow? I’d really appreciate it.

Followed by a verb with the meaning of trying all possible means to do something, such as なんとかする or なんとか手を打つ, expresses the meaning of “taking a certain action for something.”

In the expression なんとかして...する／しよう, as in (1), expresses the meaning of finding a way out of some difficult situation by taking an action. When followed by some expression of request, as shown in (4) and (5), implies the speaker’s request to be asking too much of the listener although the speaker understands the listener’s difficult situation.

2. なんとか〈barely manage (to do something)〉

（1）安月給 だがなんとか食 べていくことはできる。／Despite my low salary, I can just eke out a living.

（2）みなさんのご支援 でなんとかここまで頑張 ってやって来 れました。／Thanks to all your support, I have managed to make it to this point.

（3）銀行 が金 を貸 してくれると言 うから、何 とか倒産 だけはまぬがれることができそうだ。／Since the bank told me that they would lend me money, it seems that I will somehow manage to at least avoid bankruptcy.

Followed by an expression with some potential form, expresses the meaning that one can somehow manage to do something despite a difficulty or insufficiency. See やっと (Usage 2) for differences between なんとか, どうにか, and やっと.

3. なんとかなる

（1）そんなに心配 しなくてもなんとかなりますよ。／Don’t worry, it will all work out somehow.

（2）二階 の雨漏 り、何 とかならないかしら。／Can’t we do anything about the leaky roof on the second floor?

（3）これだけ蓄 えがあれば何 とかなるだろう。／I guess we can get by on this much savings.

Expresses the meaning that one can change an unfavorable situation to a favorable one, or one can manage to make do although something is insufficient.

<< 【に】 | Home | 【にあたらない】 >>

【にあたって】

［Nにあたって］

［V-るにあたって］

（1）開会 にあたってひとことご挨拶 を申 し上 げます。／On the occasion of opening this meeting, I would like to give a few words of greeting.

（2）年頭 にあたって集会 を持 ち、住民 達 の結束 が揺 るぎないものであることを確認 しあった。／On the occasion of the New Year, we had a meeting to confirm that our solidarity as fellow residents was unshakable.

（3）試合 に臨 むにあたって、相手 の弱点 を徹底的 に研究 した。／Prior to the match, I thoroughly investigated my opponent’s weakness.

（4）お嬢 さんを嫁 に出 すにあたってのお気持 ちはいかがでしたか。／How did you feel when you gave away your daughter in marriage?

（5）新 しい生活 を始 めるにあたっての資金 は、親 の援助 で何 とか調達 できた。／As for the expenses necessary to start my new life, I could manage to arrange for them with my parent’s support.

With a noun or the dictionary form of a verb, expresses the meaning of “facing an important time which can be considered a turning point of something, someone, or some state/event.” Similar to this expression is ...にさいして. にあたって is often used as a formal expression for a speech at a ceremony or in letters of thanks. A more formal expression which can be used in place of にあたって is ...にあたり(まして). When modifying a noun, にあたって changes its form to ...にあたってのN, as shown in (4) and (5).

<< 【にあたり】 | Home | 【にいたる】 >>

【にあって】

1. Nにあって

（1）異国 の地 にあって、仕事 を探 すこともままならない。／Being in a foreign country, it isn’t easy looking for a job.

（2）住民 代表 という立場 にあって、寝 る時間 も惜 しんでその問題 に取 り組 んでいる。／As a representative of the residents, I am tackling the problem sparing little time for sleep.

（3）大臣 という職 にあって、不正 を働 いていたとは許 せない。／For someone in the position of a minister, committing an injustice is inexcusable.

（4）母 は病床 にあって、なおも子供達 のことを気 にかけている。／Even from her sickbed, my mother is caring for her children.

With a noun, expresses the meaning of “under the circumstance mentioned in the noun.” The relationship between the circumstance and the thing/state/event stated in the following is not always fixed. Depending on the contexts before and after the expression, it can be adversative or sequential. The sentences in (1) and (2) are adversative examples, whereas those in (3) and (4) are sequential examples. にあって in (3) and (4) means “even in the circumstance/although under the circumstance.”

2. Nにあっても

（1）彼 は苦境 にあっても、めげずに頑張 っている。／Even with hardships, he’s doing his best without giving up.

（2）暖 かい家庭 の中 にあっても、彼女 の心 は満 たされなかった。／Even with her warmhearted family, she felt dissatisfied.

（3）母 は死 の間際 にあっても、子供達 の幸福 を願 い続 けた。／Even on her deathbed, the mother kept wishing for her children’s happiness.

With a noun, expresses the meaning of “even under the circumstances stated in the noun.” Followed by some state/event which contradicts what can normally be expected under such circumstances. A formal, written expression.

3. Nにあっては〈circumstances〉

（1）こんな厳寒 の地 にあっては、新鮮 な野菜 が食卓 に上 るなど、滅多 にないことだ。／In such a bitterly cold place, it’s rare for fresh vegetables to make it to the table.

（2）いつ戦争 が起 こるか知 れない状況 にあっては、明 るい未来 を思 い描 くことなどできない。／In a situation where one never knows when a war might break out, it’s difficult to imagine a bright future.

（3）夫 が病床 にあっては、子供達 に十分 な教育 を受 けさせることもできなかった。／Since my husband was ill in bed, I couldn’t have my children receive an adequate education.

（4）わが社 にあっては、若者 が自由 に発言 できる雰囲気 を大切 にしている。／In our company, we value an atmosphere in which young employees can speak out freely.

（5）「鉄 の女 」といわれた彼女 も家庭 にあっては良 き母 であった。／Even the woman called “the Iron Lady” was a good mother at home.

With a noun expressing a place or circumstances, expresses the meaning of “under the circumstances stated in the sentence.” This is similar to ...において. When an expression which shows some difficult situation, such as 厳寒の地 (bitterly cold place) or 病床(sickbed) is used with にあっては, expressions of some unfavorable circumstances follow. If this is not the case, にあっては simply expresses the meaning of “at, in, as for” as shown in (4) and (5). This is a formal, written expression.

4. Nにあっては〈person〉

（1）高橋 さんにあっては、どんな強敵 でも勝 てそうにありませんね。／When it comes to Takahashi-san, she can’t lose no matter how strong her opponent is.

（2）あの男 にあっては、嘘 もまことと言 いくるめられる。油断 は禁物 だ。／Talking about that man, he can wheedle you into believing his lies. You don’t dare let down your guard.

（3）あなたにあってはかなわないな。しょうがない。お望 み通 りに致 しましょう。／No one can get the better of you. OK, OK. I’ll do what you want.

With a noun expressing a person, used to assess the person who cannot be beaten by anybody else. The sentence in (3) is uttered when the speaker cannot decline the listener’s adroit invitation or assertive demand, and may contain a slight shade of meaning that the speaker is teasing the hearer. にあっては can be rephrased with ...にかかっては.

<< 【にかかわらず】 | Home | 【にかぎったことではない】 >>

【にかかわる】

［Nにかかわる］

（1）人 の命 にかかわる仕事 をするにはそれなりの覚悟 がいる。／When you have a job that affects whether people live or die, you need to be ready for anything.

（2）こんなひどい商品 を売 ったら店 の評判 にかかわる。／Selling such poor products affects our shop’s reputation.

（3）例 の議員 が武器 の密輸 に関係 していたかどうかはっきりさせなければならない。これは政党 の名誉 にかかわる重大 な問題 だ。／We should make it clear whether the councilor in question was involved in smuggling arms. This is an important matter which affects the party’s honor.

（4）たとえ噂 でも倒産 しそうだなどという話 が広 まると、会社 の存続 にかかわる。／If a rumor goes around that the company is about to go bankrupt, it affects the continuing existence of the company.

（5）あんな人 にいつまでもかかわっていたら、あなたまで評判 を落 としてしまいますよ。／If you continue to be mixed up with such a person, you will hurt your reputation, too.

（6）この裁判 にかかわって以来 、子 どもの人権 について深 く考 えるようになった。／Since I began to be involved in this trial, I have been thinking deeply about children’s human rights.

（7）事件 が起 きてから十年 たった。いつまでもこの事件 にかかわっているわけにはいかないが、いまだに犯人 はつかまっていない。／It is ten years since this incident happened. I can’t be involved in it forever, but the culprit has not been arrested yet.

Expresses the meaning of “to affect” or “to be involved.” にかかわる in (1)-(4) means “to affect,” and the noun is chosen to express something influential such as 名誉 (honor), 評判 (reputation), 生死 (life and death) or 合否 (pass or failure). In contrast, にかかわる in (5)-(7) means “to be involved” or “to be linked,” and the noun is used to express a person, profession, or an incident.

<< 【にかけたら】 | Home | 【にかこつけて】 >>

【にかけて】

1. NからNにかけて

（1）台風 は今晩 から明日 の朝 にかけて上陸 するもようです。／The typhoon will probably hit land some time between tonight and tomorrow morning.

（2）今月 から来月 にかけて休暇 をとるつもりだ。／I intend to take a holiday from this month to next month.

（3）北陸 から東北 にかけての一帯 が大雪 の被害 に見舞 われた。／They were hard hit by a heavy snow throughout the Hokuriku and Tohoku districts.

With a noun expressing a place or time, means “between/over the two places or times.” When it indicates time, there are two cases. One is that にかけて refers to a particular moment between the two, as shown in (1), and the other is that it refers to the time over the two, as shown in (2). にかけて has uses similar to those for ...から...まで(に). However, にかけて is used when the speaker is not overly concerned with the time or space between or over the two mentioned in the sentence or about clearly-defined boundaries.

2. Nにかけて

（1）話術 にかけては彼 の右 にでるものはいない。／No one can match him in story-telling.

（2）忍耐力 にかけては人 より優 れているという自信 がある。／I have confidence that I surpass all others in patience.

（3）彼 は誠実 な男 だが、商売 にかけての才能 はあまり期待 できない。／He is a man of sincerity, but when it comes to his business ability, he doesn’t meet our expectations.

Expresses the meaning of “concerning something.” Often followed by an expression to state some evaluation for a skill or ability. Becomes NにかけてのN, as shown in (3), when modifying a noun.

3. Nにかけて（も）

（1）命 にかけてもこの秘密 は守 り通 す。／I pledge my life to keep this secret.

（2）私 の命 にかけて、彼 らを助 け出 してみせます。／I pledge my life to save them.

（3）面子 にかけても約束 は守 る。／On my honor, I will keep my promise.

An idiomatic expression. With a noun expressing something which assures someone’s existence or value socially, such as 命 (life), 名誉 (honor), 信用 (trust) or 面子 (face), used to express the speaker’s firm determination and means “even if it is risked” or “at all costs.” Followed by an expression showing the speaker’s determination or promise.

<< 【にきまっている】 | Home | 【にくらべて】 >>

【にくい】

［R-にくい］

（1）あの人 の話 は発音 が不明瞭 で分 かりにくい。／It’s hard to understand what he says because his pronunciation isn’t clear.

（2）砂利道 はハイヒールでは歩 きにくい。／It’s hard to walk on a gravel path wearing high heels.

（3）人前 ではちょっと話 しにくい内容 なのです。／This matter is a little bit difficult to talk about in public.

（4）あんなえらい先生 のところにはなかなか相談 に行 きにくい。／It’s fairly difficult to go consult with such a high-ranking professor.

Conjugates in the same way as i-adjectives. With the stem of a verb, expresses the meaning that something is hard to do or not easily done. Used when something is physically hard to achieve, as shown in (1) and (2), or when it is psychologically hard to accomplish, as shown in (3) and (4). Except for examples such as 分かりにくい(difficult to understand), にくい is preceded by a verb of volitional action such as 歩く(walk) or 話す(talk).

（×）あの人は喜びにくい人です。／That person is difficult to please.

（○）あの人を喜ばせるのはむずかしい。／It is difficult to please that person.

There is also an expression which shows the opposite meaning: R-やすい.

<< 【にて】 | Home | 【にどと...ない】 >>

【にとって】

［Nにとって］

（1）彼 にとってこんな修理 は何 でもないことです。／For him, such repairs are nothing.

（2）年金 生活者 にとってはインフレが深刻 な問題 である。／For pensioners, inflation is a serious problem.

（3）度重 なる自然 災害 が国家 の再建 にとって大 きな痛手 となった。／The succession of natural disasters became a huge obstacle to reconstructing the country.

（4）病床 の私 にとっては、友人 の励 ましがなによりも有 り難 いものだった。／When I was sick in bed, I appreciated the encouragement of my friends more than anything.

With a noun mostly expressing a person or an organization, expresses the meaning of “from the point of view.” May express the meaning of “considering that aspect” when it is preceded by a noun expressing a thing, state or an event, as shown in (3). Followed by some expression to show (in)ability or the speaker’s evaluation, such as むずかしい(difficult), 有り難い(grateful), or 深刻だ(serious). Cannot be followed by an expression to show the speaker’s attitude, such as 賛成, 反対 or 感謝する.

（×）その案は私にとって反対です。／For me, I disagree with the plan.

（○）私はその案に反対です。／I disagree with the plan.

<< 【には】 | Home | 【にはおよばない】 >>

【にはあたらない】

［V-るにはあたらない］

（1）中学校 で教師 をしている友人 の話 によると、学校 でのいじめが深刻 だという。しかし驚 くにはあたらない。大人 の社会 も同 じなのだから。／According to my friend who is teaching in junior high school, the problem of bullying at school is serious. But there’s nothing surprising about that. The same problem can be seen in adult society.

（2）彼 ひとりだけ仲間 を置 いて下山 したからといって、非難 するには当 たらない。あのような天候 のもとではそれ以外 の方法 はなかっただろう。／You can’t put the blame on him just because he left friends and went down the mountain. I think there was no other thing for him to do under such weather conditions.

（3）子 どもがちっとも親 のいうことをきかないからといって、嘆 くには当 たらない。きっといつか親 の心 がわかる日 がくる。／It’s nothing to be surprised at just because a child doesn’t listen to his parents. One day, he will understand how parents feel toward their children.

（4）彼 が会議 でひとことも発言 しなかったからといって責 めるには当 たらない。あのワンマン社長 の前 ではだれでもそうなのだ。／There’s no need to criticize him just because he didn’t speak a word at the meeting. In front of that dictatorial president, everybody behaves like that.

With a verb such as 驚く(be surprised) or 非難する(reprove), expresses the meaning of “it is not appropriate, it is off the point.” Often used with an expression showing some reason, such as ...からといって, and means “it is off the point to be surprised at or blame someone because of such a reason.”

<< 【による】 | Home | 【によれば】 >>

【によると】

1. Nによると

a. Nによると

（1）天気 予報 によると、明日 は晴 れるそうです。／According to the weather forecast, it will be sunny tomorrow.

（2）彼 の説明 によると、この機械 は廃棄物 を処理 するためのものだということです。／According to his explanation, this machine is for the disposal of waste.

（3）あの雲 の様子 によると、明日 は多分 晴 れるだろう。／Judging from those clouds, I think it will probably be sunny tomorrow.

Indicates a source from which the speaker has heard something, or a basis from which the speaker infers something. Followed by an expression of hearsay such as ...そうだ (I hear/they say) or ...ということだ (they say), or a suppositional expression such as ...だろう (probably), ...らしい (apparently), etc. In (1) and (2), it would also be possible to use ...によれば.

b. ことによると／ばあいによると

（1）ことによると今回 の旅行 はキャンセルしなければならないかもしれない。／It may turn out that I’ll have to cancel the upcoming trip.

（2）場合 によると彼 らも応援 に来 てくれるかもしれない。／Depending on the situation, they might come to help us.

Fixed, idiomatic expressions with the meaning of “maybe, perhaps” or “under certain conditions.” Followed by a suppositional expression. Also used in the forms ことによったら and 場合によったら.

2. Vところによると

（1）聞 いたところによると、最近 は飛行機 でいく方 が電車 より安 い場合 もあるそうですね。／From what I’ve heard, you know, these days flying can sometimes be cheaper than going by train.

（2）彼 の主張 するところによると、彼 は事件 とは関係 ないということだ。／Based on what he claims, he has nothing to do with the incident.

（3）祖父 の語 ったところによると、このあたりには昔 古 い農家 があったということだ。／According to what my grandfather told me, there used to be old farmhouses around here a long time ago.

Indicates a source from which the speaker has heard something, or the basis for a judgment. Followed by an expression of hearsay, such as ...そうだ (I hear/they say) or ...ということだ (they say), or an expression of judgment, such as a supposition or assertion. Also used in the form ...ところによれば.

<< 【のきわみ】 | Home | 【のだった】 >>

【のだ】

［N／Na　なのだ］

［A／V　のだ］

Usually used in written Japanese. In spoken Japanese, it often becomes んだ. The polite form of this expression is のです, which is also used in spoken Japanese. In casual spoken Japanese, だ may be dropped so the sentence ends with の (e.g. どうしたの？). In formal written Japanese, のである may be used.

1. ...のだ〈explanation〉

（1）道路 が渋滞 している。きっとこの先 で工事 をしているのだ。／The road is jammed with traffic. There must be some construction going on ahead.

（2）彼 をすっかり怒 らせてしまった。よほど私 の言 ったことが気 にさわったのだろう。／I made him totally angry. What I said must have really offended him.

（3）泰子 は私 のことが嫌 いなのだ。だって、このところ私 を避 けようとしているもの。／I’m sure Yasuko doesn’t like me, because she’s trying to avoid me these days.

Used to explain the cause or reason for what was stated in the preceding sentence, for the speaker’s immediate circumstances, etc.

2. ...のだ〈claim〉

（1）やっぱりこれでよかったのだ。／This was the right decision after all.

（2）誰 がなんと言 おうと私 の意見 は間違 っていないのだ。／Whatever anyone else may say, my opinion is ultimately right.

（3）誰 が反対 しても僕 はやるのだ。／I’m going to do it, no matter who is against it.

Used by the speaker to make a strong assertion to convince him/herself of something or to show his/her own determination.

3. 疑 問 詞 ...のだ

（1）彼 は私 を避 けようとしている。いったい私 の何 が気 に入 らないのだ。／He’s trying to avoid me. What in heaven’s name is it about me that he doesn’t like?

（2）こんな馬鹿 げたことを言 い出 したのはだれなのだ。／Whoever started saying such a stupid thing?

Placed after a clause containing a question word and used by the speaker to ask him/herself or the addressee for some kind of explanation.

4. つまり...のだ

（1）防災 設備 さえ完備 していればこのようなことにならなかった。つまりこの災害 は天災 ではなく人災 だったのだ。／If only disaster prevention equipment had been fully supplied, this wouldn’t have happened. In other words, this was not a natural disaster but a man-made one.

（2）私 が言 いたいのは、緊急 に対策 を打 たなければならないということなのだ。／What I want to say is that we must take emergency measures to deal with this.

（3）会社 の経営 は最悪 の事態 を迎 えている。要 するに、人員 削減 はもはや避 けられないことなのだ。／Company operations are facing the worst situation possible. In short, personnel cuts are now virtually unavoidable.

Used after expressions like つまり (in other words), 私が言いたいのは (what I want to say is), and 要するに (in short). Used to paraphrase what was stated previously.

5. だから...のだ

（1）コンセントが抜 けている。だからスイッチを入 れてもつかなかったのだ。／It wasn’t plugged in. That’s why it didn’t start when we switched it on.

（2）エンジンオイルが漏 れている。だから変 な臭 いがしたのだ。／The engine oil is leaking. That’s why we smelled something strange.

（3）産業 廃棄物 の不法 投棄 が後 を立 たない。そのために我々 の生活 が脅 かされているのだ。／There is no end to the illegal dumping of industrial waste. That is why our lives are threatened.

Used after expressions such as だから (that’s why) and そのために (for that reason). Means that what is stated in the sentence with のだ is a consequence of what was stated in the preceding sentence.

6. ...のだから

［N／Na　なのだから］

［A／V　のだから］

（1）まだ子供 なのだから、わからなくても仕方 がないでしょう。／Because he’s still a child, it can’t be helped if he doesn’t understand.

（2）私 でもできたのだから、あなたにできないはずがない。／Since even I was able to do it, there’s no reason you shouldn’t be able to.

（3）あした出発 するのだから、今日 中 に準備 をしておいた方 がいい。／Since we’re leaving tomorrow, we should get ready today.

（4）冬 の山 は危険 なのだから、くれぐれも慎重 に行動 してくださいね。／Mountains in the winter are dangerous, so please proceed with the greatest caution.

Placed after a clause. Indicates that the speaker acknowledges whatever is stated in that clause to be a fact, as well as that this fact is the cause or reason that leads to the judgment etc. stated in clause that follows. For instance, in (1), after the speaker acknowledges that “he is still a child,” s/he makes the judgment, based on this fact, that he (the child) should not be expected to understand. In contrast, in the sentenceまだ子供だからわからないのだろう, which means “the reason he doesn’t understand is probably that he is a child,” the speaker is guessing the reason. In spoken Japanese, のだから often becomes ...んだから.

<< 【のではなかろうか】 | Home | 【のに2】 >>

【のに1】

［N／Na　なのに］

［A-い／A-かった　のに］

［V-る／V-た　のに］

1. ...のに〈mid-sentence〉

Placed after a clause and used in the pattern XのにY. Expresses that the result Y is not what X would naturally lead one to expect, but something contradictory. Both X and Y express an established fact. This means that expressions indicating a situation that is not established as a fact, such as questions, commands, requests, invitations, intentions, desires, or suppositions, cannot usually appear in Y.

（×）雨が降っているのに出かけなさい。／Even though it’s raining, go out.

（×）雨が降っているのに出かけたい。／Even though it’s raining, I want to go out.

（×）雨が降っているのに出かけるだろう。／Even though it’s raining, I’ll probably go out.

a. ...のに〈converse cause〉

（1）5月 なのに真夏 のように暑 い。／Although it’s May, it’s as hot as the middle of summer.

（2）家 が近 いのによく遅刻 する。／Even though she lives close by, she’s often late.

（3）雨 が降 っているのに出 かけていった。／Despite the rain, I went out.

（4）真夜中 過 ぎたのにまだ帰 ってこない。／It’s already past midnight, but he hasn’t come back yet.

（5）今日 は日曜日 なのに会社 に行 くんですか。／Even though today is Sunday, you’re going to work?

（6）5月 なのに何 でこんなに暑 いんだろう。／Why is it so hot, even though it’s still May?

In this use of the pattern XのにY, there is a causal relation between X and Y, but this causal relation is not realized.

For example, のに in (3) expresses that the usual causal relation, which is “because it was raining, I didn’t go out,” is not established; rather, two incompatible conditions are realized at the same time. This usage is often accompanied by the speaker’s surprise or doubt regarding an unexpected result or discrepancy.

In (6), のに is used to ask the reason for the current situation, which is unexpected. It expresses the speaker’s sense of surprise and misgiving.

(5) is an interrogative sentence, but のに can be used in this case. The reason is that the situation of the addressee going to work (= Y) is an established fact. The speaker is astonished that “even though it’s Sunday, you’re going to work,” and this interrogative sentence uses the form のですか to ask a question about this fact.

In contrast, an interrogative sentence without のだ that asks if the addressee is going to work would be unnatural, as below.

（×）今日は日曜日なのに会社に行きますか。／Even though today is Sunday, are you going to work?

b. ...のに〈contrast〉

（1）昨日 はいい天気 だったのに今日 は雨 だ。／It was nice yesterday, but today it’s raining.

（2）あの中国人 は日本語 はあまり上手 でないのに、英語 はうまい。／Even though that Chinese person isn’t very good at Japanese, his English is good.

（3）お兄 さんはよく勉強 するのに弟 は授業 をよくサボる 。／The older brother studies hard, while the younger one often skips class.

In this usage, XのにY expresses a contrast between X and Y, not a causal relation.

For example, in (2) there is a contrastive relation between X, which is 日本語が上手でない (s/he is not good at Japanese), and Y, which is 英語がうまい (s/he is good at English), and のに links X and Y. The relation between X and Y is not a causal relation, like “because that Chinese person is not good at Japanese, s/he is good at English.”

のに in (2) can be paraphrased as けれども or が (see below). However, while けれども and が express a simple contrastive relation between the first and second clauses, のに implies that the relation between X and Y deviates from the one usually expected and that the speaker feels it is “unusual” or “strange.”

（例）あの中国人は日本語はあまり上手でない｛けれども／が｝、英語はうまい。／That Chinese person isn’t very good at Japanese, but his/her English is good.

c. ...のに〈unexpected〉

（1）合格 すると思 っていたのに、不合格 だった。／I thought I would pass the exam, but I failed.

（2）今晩 中 に電話 するつもりだったのに、うっかり忘 れてしまった。／I intended to make a phone call tonight, but it slipped my mind.

（3）和子 さんには来 てほしかったのに、来 てくれなかった。／I especially wanted Kazuko-san to come, but she didn’t.

（4）せっかくおいでくださったのに、申 し訳 ございませんでした。／After you took the trouble to come all the way here...I really must apologize.

Expresses that an outcome is different from what was expected or predicted.

In examples (1)-(3), X (in the pattern XのにY) is an expression of expectation, intention, or desire, such as ...と思っていた (I thought...), つもりだった (I intended), or 来てほしかった (I wanted (her) to come). Y describes an outcome that is contrary to X.

(4) means せっかくお出でくださったのに、(留守にしていて)申し訳ございません (you took the trouble to come all the way here, so I really must apologize (for being out)). However, the outcome 留守にしていて (for being out) is not actually verbalized, and のに is followed immediately by the speaker’s expression of apology for the unexpected outcome.

2. ...のに〈sentence-final〉

（1）スピードを出 すから事故 を起 こしたんだ。ゆっくり走 れと言 っておいたのに。／You had an accident because you drive too fast. I told you before you went out that you should drive slowly!

（2）絶対 来 るとあんなに固 く約束 したのに。／After he’d promised so firmly that he would definitely come!

（3）もっと早 く出発 すればよかったのに。／We should have left earlier.

（4）あなたも来 ればいいのに。／You really should come, too!

（5）あと5秒 早 ければ始発 電車 に間 に合 ったのに。／If I’d arrived five seconds earlier, I would have made the first train.

Used at the end of a sentence to express a feeling of regret regarding a result that differs from what was expected. Often used when the speaker is criticizing or complaining about someone else’s actions, or at the end of a counter-factual conditional sentence, as in (5).

3. せっかく...のに→【せっかく】5

4. Nでも...のに

（1）電気屋 でも直 せないのに、あなたに直 せるはずがないじゃないの。／Even an electrician can’t fix it, so how should you be able to fix it?

（2）九州 でもこんなに寒 いのに、まして北海道 はどんなに寒 いだろう。／If it’s this cold even in Kyushu, how cold must it be in Hokkaido?

（3）こんな簡単 な問題 、小学生 でも解 けるのに、どうして間違 えたりしたの？／Even an elementary school student could solve such an easy problem, so why did you get it wrong?

Expresses the development of a logical argument, as in “if N, then something is supposed to be such-and-such, but that was not the result (e.g. I thought an electrician would be able to fix it, but s/he couldn’t)” and “even N is such-and-such, so someone/something with less potential than N is all the more such-and-such (e.g. it is even more difficult for you, as a non-professional, to fix it).”

<< 【のみならず】 | Home | 【は...で】 >>

【ば】

［N／Na　なら（ば）］

［A-ければ］

［V-ば］

ば is a conjugation form for predicates and indicates a condition. It is the most typical marker for conditional clauses in Japanese, and its usage overlaps partially with that of たら, と, and なら.

When this conditional follows a noun or a na-adjective, ば is often dropped and the form N/Naなら is used. N/Naであれば is a formal, written expression for N/Naなら. The negative form N/Naでなければ is used in both written and spoken Japanese. The i-adjective いい always takes the form よければ, not いければ.

ば is usually used the same way as たら. However, ば tends to be used more in written Japanese, while たら is used more in spoken Japanese. In casual spoken language, sometimes the combination of “consonant + eba” at the end of a word changes to “consonant + ya” (e.g. あれば→ありゃ, 行けば→行きゃ, 飲めば→飲みゃ, なければ→なけりゃ), and the combination A-ければ may change to A-きゃ (e.g. なければ→なきゃ).

1. ...ば〈generic condition〉

［...ば　N／Na　だ］

［...ば A-い］

［...ば V-る］

（1）春 が来 れば花 が咲 く。／When spring comes, flowers bloom.

（2）10 を2で割 れば5になる。／When you divide ten by two, you get five.

（3）台風 が近 づけば気圧 が下 がる。／When a typhoon approaches, the atmospheric pressure drops.

（4）年 をとれば身体 が弱 くなる。／People get weaker with age.

（5）経済 状態 が悪化 すれば犯罪 が増加 する。／When the economy deteriorates, the crime rate increases.

（6）人間 というものは、余分 な金 を持 ち歩 けばつい使 いたくなるものだ。／If people carry around extra money, they will want to spend it.

（7）信 じていれば夢 はかなうものだ。／If you believe in your dream, it will come true.

（8）だれでもほめられればうれしい。／Everyone is happy when praised.

（9）風 がふけば桶屋 がもうかる。／Bliss often falls into the hands of an unexpected person. (lit. “If the wind blows, the bucket-maker profits.”)

（10）犬 が西 向 きゃ尾 は東 。／If a dog faces west, its tail will point east. (used to emphasize that something is obvious or a matter of course)

（11）終 りよければすべてよし。／All’s well that ends well.

Used to state a conditional relation regarding a general state of affairs, not a specific person or thing. Means “when X happens, Y also happens, without exception.” Expresses logical or rule-based relations or cause-and-effect relations that are not situated at a particular point in time but always hold true. The dictionary form is always used at the end of the sentence. Not used to talk about a personal experience or one particular event. Used to say that “when X is realized, Y is the natural consequence,” “such-and-such generally happens,” or “something is intrinsically such-and-such.”

When this expression is used, the subject is often omitted. When the subject appears, it is one that refers to some kind of group as a whole, such as 人はだれでも (everyone/all people) or Nというものは (N in general). This use of the ba-form is often followed at the end of the sentence by ものだ, which indicates that the thing in question intrinsically has a certain nature, as exemplified in (6) and (7). Often used in proverbs and maxims as well, as in (9)-(11).

2. ...ば〈repetition, habit〉

Used with respect to a particular person or thing and expresses a habit or an action that is repeated. Means “every time X happens, Y happens too,” “whenever X is done, Y is invariably done as well.” The difference between this usage and the generic conditional described in 1 is that the generic conditional, which describes a situation that has an indefinite subject and transcends time, is always used with the dictionary form of a predicate at the end of the sentence, whereas the repetitive/habitual conditional can be used with not only the dictionary form but also the ta-form. This conditional is used to describe a habit or a repeated action of a definite subject.

a. ...ば... V-る

（1）祖母 は天気 がよければ毎朝 近所 を散歩 します。／My grandmother takes a walk in the neighborhood every morning, if the weather is nice.

（2）彼 は暇 さえあればいつもテレビを見 ている。／Whenever he has time, he always watches television.

（3）父 は私 の顔 を見 れば「勉強 しろ」と言 う。／Whenever my father sees me, he says “Go study!”

（4）愛犬 のポチは主人 の姿 を見 ればとんでくる。／My pet dog, Pochi, always runs to me (= his master) when he sees me.

This usage of the ba-form has the dictionary form of an action verb at the end of the sentence. Expresses a current habit or a repeated action of a definite subject.

b. ...ば... V-た

（1）子供 のころは、天気 がよければ、よく母 とこの河原 を散歩 したものだ。／When I was a child, I often used to take walks with my mother along this riverbed, if the weather was nice.

（2）学生 のころは暇 さえあればお酒 を飲 んで友達 と語 り明 かしたものだ。／When I was a college student, whenever I had time I used to drink and talk with my friends all night long.

（3）父 は東京 へ行 けば必 ずお土産 を買 ってきてくれた。／My father used to buy me a souvenir every time he went to Tokyo.

（4）20 年 ほど前 には、街 から少 し離 れれば、いくらでも自然 が残 っていた。／Twenty years ago, if you went just a little way out of the city, there were still plenty of places where the natural environment remained untouched.

This usage of the ba-form expresses a past habit of a definite subject, or a state/event that always took place under some particular circumstances in the past. Means “someone used to do/always did...in the past,” “if someone did A, then B was always the case.” Sometimes used with V-たものだ, which indicates recollection, as shown in (1) and (2).

In the pattern ...ば...V-た, the ba-form can also indicate a state or event contrary to the actual situation, as in (4). The difference between counter-factual ば and repetitive/habitual ば is that the latter states a fact that has actually been realized.

Like ば, たら can also be used to state a past fact. However, while ば expresses an action that was repeated in the past or a situation that was always realized under certain conditions, たら usually expresses a past event that took place one time only.

（例1）ビールを2本飲めば酔っぱらいました。／Whenever I drank two bottles of beer, I got drunk.

（例2）ビールを2本飲んだら酔っぱらいました。／When I drank two bottles of beer, I got drunk.

(1) above means “when I drank two bottles, I always/without exception got drunk.” This expresses an event that was repeated in the past. In contrast, (2) means “when I happened to drink two bottles, I got drunk” and expresses a past event that occurred once.

3. ...ば〈not-yet-realized condition〉

Expresses the relation “if X happens, Y will happen,” with respect to a particular thing or person. X can be something that either has or has not been realized, but Y is always something that has not yet been realized.

The generic conditional ば described in Usage 1 is used to talk about things or events in general and is always accompanied by the dictionary form of a predicate at the end of the sentence. On the other hand, the hypothetical conditional ば is used to apply a general condition to a particular situation and state a prediction. It can be combined with expressions such as だろう and かもしれない at the end of the sentence.

（例）〈一般条件〉食事を減らせば誰でもやせる。 ／〈generic condition〉If you reduce your food intake at meals, anyone can lose weight.

（例）〈仮定条件〉食事を減らせばあなたもやせるだろう。 ／〈not-yet-realized condition〉If you reduce your food intake at meals, you too will lose weight.

The slot for Y in this pattern may be filled by a statement describing an unrealized situation, an expression of intention or command, or some other expression that reveals the speaker’s thoughts/feelings or his/her desire to exert an influence on someone.

a. ...ば+未 実 現 のことがら

（1）もし私 が彼 の立場 なら、やっぱり同 じように考 えるだろう。／If I were in his shoes, I would think the same.

（2）もし天気 が悪 ければ、試合 は中止 になるかもしれない。／If the weather is bad, the match may be canceled.

（3）手術 をすれば助 かるでしょう。／If you have surgery, you will probably recover.

（4）こんなに安 ければ、きっとたくさん売 れると思 う。／If it is this inexpensive, I’m sure it will sell well.

（5）それだけ成績 がよければ、どの大学 にでも入学 できるはずです。／If your grades are that good, you should be able to get into any university.

（6）ふだん物静 かな夫 がめずらしく、一時間 も説教 していた。あれだけ叱 られれば、息子 も少 しは反省 するにちがいない。／Surprisingly, my usually quiet husband lectured our son for a whole hour. Having been given such a talking-to, surely our son will reflect on his conduct at least a little.

Used with respect to a specific person or thing and means “if X happens, of course Y will also happen.” Y refers to an unrealized situation or event and is often combined with an expression of supposition or prediction at the end of the sentence, such as だろう, にちがいない, はずだ, かもしれない, or 思う.

In (1)-(3), the speaker assumes X, which has not (yet) been realized, and makes supposition Y, which is something that should happen under condition X. (4)-(6) are cases in which X has already been realized. Here the ba-form expresses the notion that “if a situation like this has actually occurred, then Y should naturally occur as well.”

When the speaker is quite certain that Y will be realized, the non-past declarative form of a predicate can be used at the end of the sentence, as shown below.

（7）応募 人数 が多 ければ抽選 になります。／If there is a large number of applicants, the selection will be made by lottery.

（8）うっかりミスさえしなければ必 ず合格 できますよ。／If you just don’t make any careless mistakes, you will definitely pass.

（9）食事 の量 を減 らして運動 をすれば、2、3キロぐらいはすぐ減 りますよ。／If you reduce your food intake and get some exercise, you will soon lose two or three kilograms.

（10）A:気 分 が悪 くなってきたよ。／I’m starting to feel sick.

B:それだけ飲 めば、気分 も悪 くなるよ。／If you’ve drunk that much, you will feel bad.

ば is often used to say that X is a necessary and sufficient condition for the realization of Y. In (8), it takes the pattern Xさえ...ばY and expresses the meaning “in order to realize Y, it is sufficient to realize X.” In (9), it is used to state what must be done in order to obtain a desired result, and in (10) it means “when you’ve drunk so much, it’s no surprise that you feel bad.”

All of these are ultimately examples of the generic condition “if X, then definitely Y” being applied to specific cases. For instance, in (10), the generic condition “anyone who drinks too much will start to feel bad” is applied to a particular addressee’s case, in order to convey the message “if you too drink so much, it’s only natural that you feel sick.”

b. ...ば+意 志 ・希 望

（1）安 ければ買 うつもりです。／If it is inexpensive, I intend to buy it.

（2）A:こんどの日曜日 、天気 がよければハイキングに行 こうよ。／If the weather is nice, let’s go hiking next Sunday.

B:いいね。すこしぐらい天気 が悪 くても行 こうよ。／Sounds good. Even if the weather isn’t quite perfect, let’s go.

（3）A:なにか飲 む？／Do you want something to drink?

B:そうだな、ビールがあれば飲 みたいな。／Well, if you have beer, I’d like some.

（4）レポートを提出 しなければ、合格点 はあげません。／If you don’t submit a paper, I won’t give you a passing grade.

（5）田中 さんが行 かなければ、私 も行 かない。／If Tanaka-san isn’t going, I won’t go either.

（6）田中 さんが行 けば、私 も行 く。／If Tanaka-san is going, I’ll go too.

（7）掃除 を手伝 ってくれればおこづかいをあげる。／If you help me with the cleaning, I’ll give you some spending money.

（8）お電話 くださればお迎 えに上 がります。／If you telephone me, I will come to meet you.

（9）もし、今学期 中 にこの本 を読 み終 われば、次 にこの本 を読 みます。／If I can finish reading this book this term, I’ll read that book next.

（10）もし雨 が降 れば中止 しよう。／If it rains, let’s cancel it.

ば is used in the pattern Xば...しよう／したい, where Y expresses the speaker’s intention or desire, and the range of predicates that can appear in X is restricted. The general tendency is that there is no difficulty if the predicate in X is stative, but use of a verb that expresses an action or change of state often sounds unnatural.

(1)-(5) contain stative predicates, including i-adjectives, ある, and V-ない, so ば can be used with no problem. In (6)-(10), X expresses an action or change of state, but it is still possible to use ば. This has to do with the fact that (6) expresses the same action on the part of both the listener and the speaker, and (7) and (8), which mean “if you do X, I will do Y in return,” are cases of the speaker making a promise to the listener in exchange for something. The ば clause in (9) means “I don’t know whether I can finish reading it or not, but.../I may not be able to finish reading it, but if I can...,” and the one in (10) means “supposing it were to rain.” These expressions are used when the speaker has doubts about whether or not X will definitely occur, or when s/he takes into account the possibility that X will not occur.

So, in cases like (6)-(10), ば can be used even though X expresses an action or change of state. However, when X expresses a future plan which involves a sequence of actions that progress over time, ば cannot be used. For example, if (9) is intended to mean “after I finish reading this book, then I’ll read the next,” たら must be used instead of ば.

（×）この本を読めば次にこの本を読みます。／If I read this book, I’ll read that book next.

（○）この本を読んだら次にこの本を読みます。／After I read this book, I’ll read that book next.

c. ...ば+働 きかけ

（1）そう思 いたければ勝手 に思 え。／If that’s what you want to think, go right ahead!

（2）やりたくなければやるな。／Don’t do it if you don’t want to.

（3）宿題 をすませなければ遊 びに行 ってはいけない。／Unless you finish your homework, you can’t go out to play.

（4）飲 みたくなければ飲 まなくてもいい。／If you don’t want to drink, you don’t have to.

（5）お時間 があれば、もう少 しゆっくりしていってくださいよ。／If you have time, please stay for a little while longer.

（6）明日 、天気 がよければ海 に行 きませんか。／If the weather is nice tomorrow, shall we go to the beach?

（7）7時 までに仕事 が終 われば、来 てください。／If you’re finished work by seven, please come.

ば is followed by an expression that requires the listener to perform an action, such as a command, prohibition, permission, invitation, or request. In general, when an “exertion-of-influence” expression like one of these appears at the end of the sentence, it is unlikely that an action or change-of-state verb can be used in X, and the range of verbs that can be used is even more restricted than when Y is an expression of intention or desire.

ば can be used when it is followed by a stative predicate such as V-たい, Vない, or ある, as is the case in examples (1)-(6). In (7), the change-of-state verb 終わる is used with ば and followed by an expression of request. This sentence conveys the meaning “you might not finish, but supposing you are able to...” and indicates that the speaker has doubts or a negative feeling about the possibility that the listener will finish. In cases like this, ば may sometimes be used.

However, in general, when X expresses an action or change, and the speaker instructs the listener to perform a second action (after the first action/change has taken place) or prohibits that action, ば cannot be used. たら should be used instead.

（×）駅に着けば迎えに来てください。／If you arrive at the station, please come to pick me up.

（○）駅に着いたら迎えに来てください。／When you arrive at the station, please come to pick me up.

（×）お酒を飲めば運転するな。／If you drink, don’t drive.

（○）お酒を飲んだら運転するな。／When you drink, don’t drive.

d. ...ば+問 いかけ

（1）A:学生 ならば、料金 は安 くなりますか。／If you’re a student, is the charge lower?

B:大人 料金 の2割引 になります。／It will be twenty percent off the adult price.

（2）この病気 は手術 をすれば治 りますか。／Will this illness be cured if I have an operation?

（3）あやまれば許 してくれるでしょうか。／If I apologize, will she forgive me?

（4）A:どうすれば機嫌 を直 してくれるかしら。／What can I do to restore his good humor?

B:何 か贈 り物 をして丁寧 にあやまるのが一番 ね。／The best thing you can do is give him some kind of gift and apologize politely.

（5）A:どのぐらい入院 すればよくなるでしょうか。／How long will I have to stay in the hospital to recover?

B:2週間 ぐらいですね。／About two weeks.

（6）A:どこに行 けばその本 を見 つけることができるでしょうか。／I wonder where I can go to find that book.

B:神田 の古本屋 を探 せば、一冊 ぐらいはあるかもしれませんね。／If you go to the used bookstores in Kanda, you may be able to find a copy.

The pattern XばYか expresses a question seeking an answer from the listener. (1)-(3) are yes-no interrogative sentences, and (4)-(6) are interrogative sentences with question words such as どう (how) and どこ (where). In the latter case, ば is often used in the form どうすればYか, to ask about the means or method X that can be used in order to achieve the good result Y. On the other hand, when the speaker is asking what to do when X has occurred, it is more natural to use たら, and using ば often results in an unnatural or anomalous expression.

（×）雨が降ればどうしますか。／What will you do if it rains?

（○）雨が降ったらどうしますか。／What will you do if it rains?

e. 疑 問 詞 +V-ば...のか

（1）いったいどういうふうに説明 すれば分 かってもらえるのか。／How in the world should I explain it, to make him understand?

（2）何年 勉強 すればあんなに上手 に英語 がしゃべれるようになるのだろう。／I wonder how many years I should study English in order to be able to speak as fluently as that.

（3）どれだけ待 てば、手紙 は来 るのか。／How long should I wait for the letter to come?

（4）人間 、一体 何度 同 じ過 ちを繰 り返 せば、気 がすむのであろうか。／How many times do human beings have to repeat the same mistake until they are satisfied?

This is a rhetorical expression that consists of a question word such as 何 (what), どれだけ (how much), or どんなに (how/however) followed by the ba-form of a verb. It means “no matter how much I do..., things don’t go the way I want them to,” and it expresses the speaker’s sense of exasperation or desperation regarding a certain situation. Expressions like のか, のだ, and のだろう(か) are used at the end of the sentence. V-ば can be replaced by V-たら.

4. ...ば〈counter-factual〉

A statement of something contrary to fact comes before ば, and after ば comes a description of something that should (have) happen(ed) if the situation were the opposite. Used to talk about an undesirable situation that has already been realized, or about a situation that is obviously impossible to realize.

When this pattern is used to say that a desired situation has not been realized, it conveys a feeling of regret or disappointment. On the other hand, when it is used to say that an undesirable situation has been avoided, it implies the speaker’s feeling of relief, as in “it’s a good thing such-and-such didn’t happen.”

In many cases, it is impossible to distinguish a counter-factual use from a factual one on the basis of form alone. However, the patterns below are often used in counter-factual conditional sentences. Also, this usage of ば can always be substituted with たら.

a. ...ば　...のに／...のだが

（1）宿題 がなければ夏休 みはもっと楽 しいのに。（残念 なことに宿題 がある。）／If there were no assignments, my summer holiday would be more enjoyable. (Unfortunately, I do have assignments.)

（2）お金 があれば買 うんだけどなあ。（お金 が無 いから買 えない。）／If I had the money, I would buy it. (Because I don’t have the money, I can’t buy it.)

（3）お金 があれば買 えたんだが。（お金 がなかったので買 えなかった。）／If I had had the money, I could have bought it. (Because I didn’t have the money, I couldn’t buy it.)

（4）A:試験 うまくいった？／Did your exam go well?

B:うまくいっていれば、こんな不機嫌 な顔 はしていないさ。（試験 に失敗 したから、こんな不機嫌 な顔 をしている。）／If it had gone well, I wouldn’t look this crabby. (Because I failed the exam, I look this crabby.)

The pattern XばYのに／のだが／のだけれど is a counter-factual conditional sentence. The predicate in Y takes either the dictionary form or the ta-form. (1) and (2) are examples of the former. These express that the speaker desires something that is different from the present situation, regrets this situation, etc. In (3) the speaker uses the ta-form to hypothesize a past situation that is different from what actually happened and to state that, if the hypothetical situation had been realized, the result would have been different. (4) illustrates the pattern V-ていればV-ている, which is used to state a hypothesis, with regard to a situation that has already been realized, that if things had been different the present situation would not have arisen.

As shown in (1)-(3), when an expression like のに, のだが, or のだけれど appears at the end of the sentence, it is clear that the sentence is a counter-factual conditional. However, such expressions are not always used, as seen in (4).

b. ...ば　...だろう／...はずだ

（1）地震 の起 こるのがあと1時間 遅 ければ被害 はずっと大 きかっただろう。／If the earthquake had happened one hour later, the damage would have been far more extensive.

（2）気 をつけていれば、あんな事故 は起 きなかったはずだ。／If she’d been more careful, an accident like that wouldn’t have happened.

（3）発見 がもう少 し遅 ければ助 からなかったかもしれない。／If he had been found a little later, he might not have been saved.

（4）あの時 すぐに手術 をしていれば、助 かったにちがいない。／If she had had an operation right away at that time, she would certainly have recovered.

（5）彼 が止 めに入 らなければ、ひどい喧嘩 になっていたと思 う。／I think it would have turned into a terrible fight, if he had not stepped in to stop it.

（6）あの時 、あの飛行機 に乗 っていれば、私 は今 ここにいないはずだ。／If I had taken that flight then, I would not be here now.

Used to speculate about a situation or event that could have happened, if things had been different. An expression of prediction or conjecture, such as だろう, はずだ, かもしれない, にちがいない, or と思う, is used at the end of the sentence.

When the expression of prediction or conjecture is preceded by the ta-form of a predicate, as in (1)-(5), it means that the actual past situation differs from the one expressed by the predicate. When the dictionary form is used, as in (6), it means that the present situation differs from the one expressed by the predicate.

c. ...ば...ところだ（った）

（1）もう少 し若 ければ、私 が自分 で行 くところだ。／If I were a little younger, I would be ready to go myself.

（2）あのとき、あの飛行機 に乗 っていれば私 も事故 に巻 き込 まれていたところだ。／If I had taken that flight then, I would have been caught up in the accident too.

（3）今日 の授業 は突然 休講 になったらしい。田中 が電話 をしてくれなければ、もう少 しで学校 に行 くところだった。／Apparently today’s class was canceled without notice. If Tanaka hadn’t called me, I would have been on my way to school in a little while.

（4）電車 がもう少 し早 く来 ていれば大惨事 になるところだった。／If the train had arrived a little earlier, it would have been a terrible disaster.

（5）注意 していただかなければ忘 れていたところでした。／If you hadn’t reminded me, I would have forgotten.

In this pattern, ば is followed at the end of the sentence by an expression like V-るところだった, V-ていたところだ, or V-ていたところだった.

...ばV-るところだ is used to hypothesize an unrealized situation or event Y, which would likely be realized if the situation were different from X. (1) is such an example; it means “I’m not actually young so I can’t go, but I am almost inclined to do so.”

...ばV-ていたところだ means “if the situation had been different, I would have done such-and-such/such-and-such would have happened.” Expresses a potential situation in the past, as exemplified in (2).

...ばV-るところだった, shown in (3) and (4), is used when an event that would have happened under different circumstances was avoided just before it takes place. Used when the speaker feels relieved that it was possible to avoid an unfavorable outcome.

忘れていたところだった in (5) can be rephrased as 忘れているところだった. However, the former expresses a past situation, with the sense of “I managed not to forget,” while the latter expresses a present situation, with the sense of “I’ve managed to remember.”

→【ところだ】2

d. ...ば　V-た／V-ていた

（1）安 ければ買 った。／If it had been inexpensive, I would have bought it.

（2）もっと早 く来 れば間 に合 った。／If I had come earlier, I would have been in time.

（3）手当 てが早 ければ、彼 は助 かっていた。／If he had been treated sooner, he would have been saved.

（4）きちんとした説明 があれば、私 も反対 しなかった。／If a proper explanation had been given, I wouldn’t have objected either.

In this pattern, ば takes the ta-form of a verb at the end of the sentence and expresses a counter-factual situation or event. Used with respect to a past situation, to hypothesize an action that was not actually performed or a state that differs from reality, and to express a situation or event that would have occurred under the hypothetical circumstances. (2), for instance, means “if I had come earlier, I would have been in time; however, since I actually came late, I was not in time.”

In general, counter-factual conditional sentences often end with expressions like のに／のだが／のだけれど, or だろう／かもしれない／はずだ／にちがいない／と思う, or ところだ(った), as shown in patterns (a)-(c) above. However, there are cases in which no such expression is used, as shown in this pattern (d). Note that when the ta-form is used in sentence-final position, in particular, conditional sentences with ば and たら may express different meanings.

（例1）ボタンを押したら爆発した。／When I pressed the button, it exploded.

（例2）ボタンを押せば爆発した。／If I had pressed the button, it would have exploded.

Example 1, which means “I pressed the button. Then it exploded,” expresses an event that actually took place. On the other hand, example 2 is a counter-factual conditional sentence that means “If I had pressed the button, it would have exploded, but I didn’t actually press the button, so it didn’t explode.”

5. ...ば〈already-realized condition〉

（1）彼 は変 わり者 だという評判 だったが、会 ってみれば、うわさほどのことはなかった。／He had the reputation of being quite a strange character, but when I met him, he was not half as strange as was rumored.

（2）言 われてみればそれももっともな気 がする。／Now that you say so, I think that’s a good point too.

（3）始 める前 は心配 だったが、すべてが終 わってみれば、それほど大 したことではなかったと思 う。／I was worried before I started, but now that it’s all over, I don’t think it was such a big deal.

The pattern XばY is used to express that the speaker realized Y at the time X occurred. For this usage, たら and と are more usual, and the use of ば is restricted to somewhat old-fashioned literary expressions such as those found in poetry and novels. When this pattern is used in spoken Japanese, it usually takes the form V-てみれば and expresses the speaker’s understanding or acceptance after learning the truth about something, with the sense of “that is quite right” or “of course, it stands to reason.”

In (1)-(3), ば can be replaced by たら, but when たら is used, it means “as a result of taking such-and-such an action, I realized something.” For example, when ば in (1) is replaced by たら to say 会ってみたら、うわさほどのことはなかったよ, the たら sentence means “as a result of meeting him, I found out that he was not as (strange) as was rumored.” Thus, when a speaker is describing a new realization just the way it happened, s/he usually uses たら or と; if ば is used, it often sounds unnatural.

（×）昨日、台所で変な音がするので泥棒かと思って行ってみれば、弟がラーメンを作っていた。／Yesterday I heard a strange noise in the kitchen so I thought it might be a thief, but if I went to see, my brother was making raamen noodle soup.

（○）昨日、台所で変な音がするので泥棒かと思って｛行ってみたら／行ってみると｝、弟がラーメンを作っていた。／Yesterday I heard a strange noise in the kitchen so I thought it might be a thief, but when I went to see, my brother was making raamen noodle soup.

（×）朝起きれば、雨が降っていた。／If I got up in the morning, it was raining.

（○）朝｛起きたら／起きると｝、雨が降っていた。／When I got up in the morning, it was raining.

When talking about one person who performs two actions in succession, one time only, と should be used, not ば or たら. See the example below.

（×）次郎は家に｛帰れば／帰ったら｝、テレビを見た。／If Jiro came home, he watched TV.

（○）次郎は家に帰ると、テレビを見た。／When Jiro came home, he watched TV.

6. ...ば...で

［A-ければ A-いで］

［V-ば V-たで］

（1）自動車 がないとさぞ不便 だろうと思 っていたが、なければないでやっていけるものだ。／I thought it would be very inconvenient to live without a car, but I can actually manage without one.

（2）父 は暑 さに弱 い。それでは冬 が好 きかというとそうではない。寒 ければ寒 いで文句 ばかり言 っている。／My father can’t take the heat. But that doesn’t mean he likes winter. Once it gets cold, he does nothing but complain about it.

（3）金 などというものは、無 ければ困 るが、あればあったでやっかいなものだ。／Money is something that is trouble if you don’t have any, but a nuisance if you do have some.

（4）子供 が小 さい間 は、病気 をしないだろうかちゃんと育 つだろうかと心配 ばかりしていたが、大 きくなれば大 きくなったで、受験 やら就職 やら心配 の種 はなくならない。／When my children were little, I fretted over whether they would get sick or grow up the right way. Now that they’re getting older, there is no end to worries about entrance exams and job-hunting and so forth.

The same verb or adjective is repeated in this pattern, which is used to say that situations that should contrast with each other are essentially the same. For instance, (1) means “if I had a car, it would be convenient, but even without a car, I don’t have as much trouble as I’d expected,” (2) means “My father complains, regardless of whether it is hot or cold,” (3) means “Money is always troublesome, whether you have it or not,” and (4) means “Children make us worry while they’re small and also after they’ve grown up.” In (4), it is possible to omit the second use of 大きく and say 大きくなればなったで instead. ...たら...で is a synonymous expression.

7. ...ば〈introductory utterance〉

This pattern is used to indicate in advance the conditions under which the following statement will be made, or to give advance warning or explanation of something. It includes idiomatic expressions that are rather fixed. In most cases, ば can be replaced by たら.

a. ...ば+request, recommendation

（1）もし、お差 し支 えなければ、ご住所 とお名前 をお聞 かせください。／If you wouldn’t mind, please tell me your name and address.

（2）A:今日 の説明会 はもう終 わったんでしょうか。／Has today’s briefing already finished?

B:はい、3時 に終了 いたしました。よろしければ、来週 の火曜 にも説明会 がございますが。／Yes, it was over at three. If it’s convenient for you, there will be another briefing next Tuesday.

（3）よろしければ、もう一杯 いかがですか。／If it suits you, would you care for another glass?

The expressions above in ba-form are idiomatic expressions used to make requests, recommendations, or suggestions. They show the speaker’s consideration for the listener’s situation or feelings. They mean “as long as it is not contrary to your convenience or intentions.” These are polite expressions that convey the speaker’s reservation—that is, the attitude that it is not necessary for the listener to act on the request, suggestion, etc., if it is inconvenient for him/her or if s/he does not want to do it.

b. ...ば〈viewpoint〉

（1）A:本当 に行 くのかい。／Are you really going?

B:うん。でも正直 言 えば、本当 は行 きたくないんだ。／Yeah. But to be honest, I really don’t want to.

（2）50 年 前 と比 べれば、日本人 もずいぶん背 が高 くなったと言 える。／Compared with fifty years ago, we can say that Japanese people too have gotten quite a bit taller.

（3）今 は円高 なので、国内 旅行 よりも海外旅行 の方 が安 くつくらしい。考 えてみればおかしな話 だ。／I’ve heard that because the yen is strong now, traveling abroad is less expensive than traveling in Japan. If you think about it, that’s really strange.

（4）思 えば、事業 が成功 するまでのこの 10 年 は長 い年月 だった。／Looking back, these past ten years—until the project succeeded—were really long ones.

Verbs of utterance, thought, or comparison, such as 言う (say/speak), 思う (think), and 比べる (compare), are used in the ba-form to give advance warning or explanation of the perspective or standpoint from which the statement or judgment that follows will be made.

The ba-form expressions in (1) and (2) can be rephrased as 正直言って／言うと／言ったら and 比べて／比べると／比べたら, respectively. (3) can be rephrased as 考えてみると／みたら. The expression 思えば in (4), which means “when I think about it once again,” is used to take an emotional look back at the past. It cannot be rephrased with the te-form, たら, or と.

As noted above, this usage of the ba-form consists mostly of idiomatic expressions that are rather fixed. Additional examples include はっきり言えば (frankly speaking/to put it bluntly), 極端に言えば (to put it in extreme terms), からみれば (from the viewpoint of), からすれば (from the standpoint of), and so on.

8. V-ば〈suggestion, recommendation〉

（1）《服 売 り場 で》／《at a clothing store》

A:これなんかどうかなあ。／What about this one?

B:着 てみれば。／Why don’t you try it on?

（2）A:ゆうべから、すごく頭 が痛 いんだ。／I’ve had a terrible headache since yesterday evening.

B:そんなに痛 いの？　会社 休 めば。／That bad, huh? Why don’t you take a day off?

（3）A:あ、これ間違 ってる。／Oh, this is wrong.

B:教 えてあげれば。／Why don’t you tell him?

V-ば is pronounced with rising intonation and used to suggest that the listener take a particular action. When the speaker ends a sentence with V-ば, it often sounds like s/he is unconcerned or has only passing interest in the matter at hand. Can be substituted with V-たらor V-たらどう. Used in casual spoken Japanese.

9. ...も...ば...も

（1）彼 は心臓 が悪 いくせに酒 も飲 めばたばこも吸 う。／Even though he has a bad heart, he not only drinks but also smokes.

（2）彼 は器用 な男 で料理 もできれば裁縫 もできる。／He is good with his hands, and he not only cooks but also sews.

（3）勲章 なんかもらっても、うれしくもなければ、名誉 だとも思 わない。／Even if I were given a medal, I wouldn’t feel pleased or honored.

（4）動物 が好 きな人 もいれば、嫌 いな人 もいる。／Some people like animals, but some don’t.

（5）人 の一生 にはいい時 もあれば悪 い時 もある。／We have both good and bad times in our lives.

This pattern is used to list similar items for emphasis, as shown in (1)-(3), or to list contrasting items in order to express that there is a variety of cases, as shown in (4) and (5). These examples can be paraphrased using ...し, as in 酒も飲むしたばこも吸う (he drinks and moreover he smokes). Also, the first instance of も can be changed to が, as in 動物の好きな人がいれば嫌いな人もいる (some people like animals, but others don’t).

10. おもえば→【おもえば】

11. ...かとおもえば→【かとおもえば】

12. ...からいえば→【からいう】1

13. ...からすれば→【からする】1

14. ...からみれば→【からみる】1

15. さえ...ば→【さえ】2

16. ってば

（1）お父 さんってば、早 く来 てよ。／Oh Dad, hurry up and come!

（2）絶対 に私 が正 しいんだってば。／I’m telling you, I’m definitely right!

→【ってば】

17. ...といえば→【といえば】

18. ...とすれば→【とすれば1】、【とすれば2】

19. ...となれば→【となれば】

20. ...ともなれば→【ともなれば】

21. ...ならば→【なら1】、【なら2】、【なら3】

22. ...にいわせれば→【にいわせれば】

23. ...にしてみれば→【にしてみれば】

24. ...ば...ほど

（1）考 えれば考 えるほど分 からなくなる。／The more I think, the more confused I get.

（2）食 べれば食 べるほど太 る。／The more I eat, the more I gain weight.

→【ほど】4b

25. ...も...ば

（1）その部品 なら 1000 円 も出 せば買 えるよ。／You can buy this part for only 1,000 yen.

（2）こんな作業 は5分 もあれば終 わる。／It would take only five minutes to finish a job like this.

→【も】4d

26. ...も...あれば...もある→【も】10

<< 【はい】 | Home | 【はいざしらず】 >>

【ばいい】

［N／Na　なら（ば）いい］

［A-ければいい］

［V-ばいい］

An idiomatic expression that consists of the ba-form of a conjugated predicate combined with いい. ばよい and ばよろしい are slightly more formal expressions.

→【たらいい】、【といい】

1. V-ばいい〈suggestion, recommendation〉

（1）休 みたければ休 めばいい。／If you want to take a rest, then you should take a rest.

（2）お金 がないのなら、お父 さんに借 りればいいじゃない。／If you don’t have any money, why not borrow some from your father?

（3）A:どうすればやせられるでしょうか。／What can I do to lose weight?

B:食 べる量 を減 らして、たくさん運動 すればいいんじゃないですか。／You could reduce the amount of food you eat and do a lot of exercise, couldn’t you?

（4）A:何時 ごろ行 きましょうか。／Around what time should I come?

B:10 時 までに来 てくれればいい。／It would be good if you could be here by ten.

An expression used to recommend or suggest that the addressee take a certain action. Used to give or seek advice regarding what kind of measures or means should be taken in order to achieve a particular desired result. Synonymous with たらいい and can usually be rephrased as such. However, ばいい conveys a strong sense that “doing this alone is necessary and sufficient.” Depending on the context, ばいい may sometimes express a lack of interest on the part of the speaker or show that s/he is pointedly wondering why the addressee does not understand even such a simple matter. When ばいい is used to seek advice, it may be used in the form of a question that specifies a purpose, as shown in (3A) どうすればやせられるか (what can I do to lose weight?), or it may just be used in the interrogative form どうすればいいか (what can I do?).

2. ...ばいい〈wish, desire〉

（1）この子 が男 の子 ならいいのに。／If only she were a boy.

（2）もうすこし暇 ならいいのに。／I wish I had a little more free time.

（3）もう少 し給料 が高 ければいいのだが。／I wish my salary were a bit higher.

（4）もっと家 が広 ければいいのになあ。／How I wish my house were more spacious!

（5）明日 、雨 が晴 れればいいなあ。／I really hope it’ll clear up tomorrow.

（6）父 が生 きていればなあ。／If only my father were still alive.

（7）順子 さんもパーティに出席 してくれればいいなあ。／I hope Junko-san will come to the party too.

Expresses the speaker’s hope or desire that something will happen. Often followed by an expression like のだが, のに, or (のに)なあ at the end of the sentence. When the current situation differs from the one that is desired, or when the desired situation is impossible, ばいい expresses a feeling of regret, like “I’m sorry that it isn’t so.” As shown in (6), the form ...ばなあ, which leaves out いい, is also used often. In almost all cases, ばいい can be replaced by たらいい.

3. ...ばよかった

（1）親 がもっと金持 ちならばよかったのに。／I wish my parents had been richer.

（2）体 がもっと丈夫 ならばよかったのに。／If only I were healthier and stronger.

（3）もう 10 センチ背 が高 ければよかったのに。／I wish I could have been ten centimeters taller.

（4）あんな映画 、見 に行 かなければよかった。／I shouldn’t have gone to see a movie like that.

（5）A:スキー旅行 楽 しかったよ。君 も来 ればよかった。／The ski trip was fun. You should have come too.

B:僕 も行 ければよかったと思 うよ。残念 だった。／I wish I could have gone along too. It was too bad.

Expresses criticism of the addressee or a sense of regret when something did not actually happen or the current situation is contrary to what the speaker had hoped for. When the negative form なければよかった is used, as in (4), it means that the speaker regrets something that s/he actually did. ばよかった may be followed at the end of the sentence by のに, のだが, or のだけれど. たらよかった is a synonymous expression. With this usage, it is not impossible to say とよかった. However, たらよかった and ばよかった are more common. のに is not usually used when the speaker is talking about his/her own actions.

（×）僕も行ければよかったのに。／I wish I could have gone too.

（○）僕も行ければよかったんだが。／I wish I could have gone too.

<< 【ばかり】 | Home | 【ばかりでなく...も】 >>

【ばかりか】

A formal expression with the tone of written language.

1. ...ばかりか　...も／...まで

［Nばかりか　...も／...まで］

［Na なばかりか　...も／...まで］

［A／V　ばかりか　...も／...まで］

（1）彼女 は、現代語 ばかりか古典 も読 める。／She can read not only modern works but also the classics.

（2）会社 の同僚 ばかりか家族 までが私 を馬鹿 にしている。／Not only my colleagues at work but also my family treat me like a fool.

（3）そのニュースが放送 されると、日本 国内 ばかりか遠 く海外 からも激励 の手紙 がよせられた。／When the news was broadcast, letters of encouragement were sent to them not only from within Japan but also from abroad.

（4）手術 をしても歩 けるようにはならないかもしれないと言 われていたが、手術後 の回復 はめざましく、歩 けるようになったばかりか軽 い運動 もこなせるようになった。／Although he was told that he might not be able to walk even after surgery, his recovery has been remarkable; not only has he started to be able to walk, he can even do some light exercise.

（5）最近 では、東京 や大阪 のような大都市 ばかりか、中 小都市 でも道路 の渋滞 がひどくなってきているらしい。／Recently, traffic congestion seems to be getting much worse, not only in big cities such as Tokyo and Osaka, but even in small and medium-sized cities.

Means “not only...but also....” Used to make a statement about something of a lesser degree and then indicate that this also extends to something else at a higher degree.

For example, (1) means “she can read not only modern works but also the classics, which are much more difficult.” (2) means “not only my colleagues, but even my family (who should have the most faith in me) are treating me like a fool.”

When this expression is used in the form V-ないばかりか, it tends to be used to refer to something unfavorable.

（例）彼は自分の失敗を認めないばかりか、相手が悪いなどと言い出す始末だ。／He not only ignores his own mistakes, he tops things off by saying that the other party is to blame.

（例）親切に忠告してやったのに、彼は、まじめに聞かないばかりかしまいには怒りだした。／Even though I gave him a piece of advice out of kindness, he not only refused to listen seriously, he also ended up getting angry.

（例）薬を飲んだが、全然きかないばかりか、かえって気分が悪くなってきた。／Although I took some medicine, it didn’t work for me at all; instead, it made me feel sick.

2. そればかりか

（1）上田 さんは英語 が話 せる。そればかりか韓国語 もインドネシア語 も話 せる。／Ueda-san can speak English. In addition, he can also speak Korean and Indonesian.

（2）彼 はその男 に着 る物 を与 えた。そればかりか、いくらかの金 まで持 たせてやった。／He gave some clothes to the man. What is more, he also let him have some money.

（3）日本 の私立 高校 には、たいてい制服 がある。そればかりか靴 やカバンまで決 まっているという学校 が多 い。／Students at private high schools in Japan usually wear a school uniform. Moreover, many schools even have designated shoes and school bags.

Used the same way as Usage 1 (above). The first sentence describes something of a relatively lower degree, and the second one indicates that this extends to another thing at a higher degree.

<< 【ばかりでなく...も】 | Home | 【はじめ】 >>

【ばこそ】

［N／Na　であればこそ］

［A-ければこそ］

［V-ばこそ］

（1）すぐれた教師 であればこそ、学生 からあれほど慕 われるのです。／It is because she is such an excellent teacher that she is so adored by her students.

（2）体 が健康 であればこそ、つらい仕事 もやれるのだ。／It is only because you are healthy that you can do the hard work, too.

（3）問題 に対 する関心 が深 ければこそ、こんなに長 く研究 を続 けてこられたのだ。／It is because you are deeply interested in this problem that you have been able to continue your research for such a long time.

（4）あなたを信頼 していればこそ、お願 いするのですよ。／It is because I trust you that I am asking you.

（5）家族 を愛 すればこそ、自分 が犠牲 になることなどはおそれない。／It’s precisely because I love my family that I’m not afraid of sacrificing myself.

Formed by attaching こそ to ば. A slightly old-fashioned expression used to emphasize the reason for something. Means “for this very reason.” Often followed by のだ at the end of the sentence. In most cases, から (because) can be used instead. However, with から the emphasis on the reason is lost.

（例）すぐれた教師だから、学生からあれほど慕われるのです。／She is an excellent teacher, so she is really adored by her students.

からこそ is similar to ばこそ. However, からこそ can be used with a cause or reason that has either positive or negative meaning, whereas ばこそ is unlikely to be used in the case of a negative cause/reason.

（×）体が弱ければこそ嫌いなものも無理して食べなければならない。／It is because you are weak that you should force yourself to eat things you don’t like.

（○）体が弱いからこそ嫌いなものも無理して食べなければならない。／It is because you are weak that you should force yourself to eat things you don’t like.

Has the tone of written language. Used in written texts and formal spoken language.

→【からこそ】

<< 【はじめて】 | Home | 【はずみ】 >>

【はず】

［Nのはず］

［Na なはず］

［A／V　はず］

1. ...はずだ〈speaker’s judgment〉

（1）A:山田 さんも明日 の会議 には出席 するんですか。／Will Yamada-san attend the meeting tomorrow, too?

B:いや、今週 は東京 に行 くと言 っていたから、明日 の会議 には来 ないはずだよ。／No, she said she was going to be in Tokyo this week, so she won’t be at the meeting tomorrow.

（2）あれから4年 たったのだから、今年 はあの子 も卒業 のはずだ。／It’s been four years since then, so he must be graduating this year too.

（3）今 はにぎやかなこの辺 りも、昔 は静 かだったはずだ。／It must have been quiet around here a long time ago, even though it’s bustling these days.

（4）A:本当 にこのボタンを押 せばいいのかい？　押 しても動 かないよ。／Are you sure we’re supposed to push this button? I did, but nothing happened.

B:説明書 によるとそれでいいはずなんだけど。変 だなあ。／According to the instructions, that’s how it should work. How strange!

（5）A:あそこにいるの、下田 さんじゃありませんか。／Isn’t that Shimoda-san over there?

B:おかしいな。下田 さんは昨日 ニューヨークに発 ったはずだよ。／That’s funny. Shimoda-san was supposed to have left for New York yesterday.

（6）A:会議 は一 時 からですか。／Does the meeting start at one o’clock?

B:ええ、そのはずです。／Yes, it’s supposed to.

Used to state something that the speaker thinks is a natural or logical judgment, based on some kind of evidence. This judgment must be based on a logical train of thought. Thus, はず cannot be used in cases such as the one below.

（×）めがねが見つからない。またどこかに置き忘れたはずだ。／I can’t find my glasses. I should have left them somewhere again.

（○）めがねが見つからない。またどこかに置き忘れたんだ。／I can’t find my glasses. I’ve left them somewhere again.

As shown in (4) and (5), when reality does not conform to the speaker’s judgment, はず expresses a sense of surprise or suspicion.

はず can be used with respect to a third party’s plans, as in 彼は来年帰国するはずです (he should be returning to his country next year). However, it cannot be used with respect to the speaker’s own actions. In that case, つもり (intend to), V-ようと思う (be going to do...), or ...予定だ (plan to...) are used instead.

（×）私は来年帰国するはずです。／I should be returning to my country next year.

（○）私は来年帰国する予定です。／I plan to return to my country next year.

However, はず can be used with respect to the speaker’s own actions when an outcome can’t be determined according to his/her own will or when it differs from his/her intended actions, as shown below.

（○）マニュアルを何回も読んだからできるはずなんだけど、どうしてもコンピューターが起動しない。／I’ve read the manual over and over again, so I should be able to do this, but the computer won’t boot up no matter what.

（○）その旅行には、私も行くはずでしたが、結局行けませんでした。／I was supposed to go along on the trip, but in the end I couldn’t.

2. ...はずだ〈understanding〉

［Na なはずだ］

［A／V　はずだ］

（1）この部屋 、寒 いねえ。（窓 が開 いているのを見 つけて）寒 いはずだ。窓 が開 いているよ。／This room is cold, isn’t it? (realizing that the window is open) No wonder it’s cold. The window is open!

（2）《作品 を見 ながら》彼 が自慢 するはずだ。本当 にすばらしいできだ。／《looking at a work of art》No wonder he was boasting about this. It really is a magnificent piece.

（3）さっきから道 が妙 にすいていると思 っていたが、すいているはずだ。今日 は日曜日 だ。／I was just thinking how strange it is that the roads are so empty, but they ought to be. Today is Sunday.

Expresses the speaker’s feeling of being convinced, after discovering a fact that adequately explains something s/he was previously suspicious of or didn’t fully understand.

3. V-たはず

（1）おかしなことに、閉 めたはずの金庫 のカギが開 いていた。／Strangely, the safe—which I thought I had locked—was open.

（2）A:書類 、間違 っていたよ。／There was a mistake on the document.

B:えっ、よく確 かめたはずなんですけど。すみません。／Really? I thought I had checked it carefully. I’m sorry.

（3）ちゃんとかばんに入 れたはずなのに、家 に帰 ってみると財布 がない。／I thought I had put my wallet in my bag, but when I returned home I couldn’t find it.

Used when there is a discrepancy between what the speaker expected to be true and the actual situation. Expresses a feeling of regret or suspicion on the part of the speaker.

4. ...はずがない〈negation of possibility〉

（1）あの温厚 な人 がそんなひどいことをするはずがない。／A good-natured person like him can’t have done such a terrible thing.

（2）かぎがない？　そんなはずはない。さっき机 の上 に置 いたんだから。／You can’t find the key? That’s impossible. I just left it on the desk a minute ago.

（3）これは君 の部屋 にあったんだよ。君 が知 らないはずはない。／We found this in your room. So you can’t say you don’t know anything about it.

Used in the form はずがない or はずはない. Means “inconceivable,” “impossible,” or “strange.” Expresses strong doubt on the part of the speaker.

For instance, (3) means “It doesn’t make sense that you don’t know. Surely you must know.”

The expression ...ないはずだ, which is an instance of Usage 1 (above), is used when the speaker thinks that something is “probably not” the case. For example, if (1) were rephrased as そんなひどいことはしないはずだ, it would mean “he isn’t likely to have done such a terrible thing,” which is a weaker assertion than the one expressed by ...はずがない.

5. ...はずだった

（1）彼 も来 るはずだったが、急用 ができて来 られないそうだ。／He was supposed to come too, but I heard that he can’t because something urgent came up.

（2）理論上 はうまくいくはずだったが、実際 にやってみると、うまくいかなかった。／In theory it should have worked fine, but in practice it didn’t.

（3）初 めの計画 では、道路 はもっと北側 を通 るはずだったのに、いつの間 にか変更 されてしまった。／According to the original plan, the road was supposed to be constructed farther north, but that changed without any notice.

Means that the speaker “had thought that naturally something would happen.” Used to express that the actual result is different from the one the speaker expected. Often implies the speaker’s surprise, disappointment, or regret. Also, often used in adversative constructions such as はずだったが／のに／けれど (should have...but.../although...was supposed to...).

6. ...はずではなかった

（1）こんなはずではなかった。もっとうまくいくと思 っていたのに。／This is not what was supposed to happen. I thought it would work out much better.

（2）こんなはずじゃなかったのに。／It really wasn’t meant to turn out like this.

（3）彼 が来 るはずではなかったのに。／He wasn’t supposed to come.

Often used in the expression こんなはずではなかった (see above). Indicates the speaker’s disappointment or regret with respect to the actual situation, which differs from what s/he had expected. Often used in the pattern ...はずではなかったのに.

<< 【ひとつ】 | Home | 【ひととおり】 >>

【ひとつまちがえば】

（1）出産 というのは大変 な仕事 で、医学 の進 んだ現在 でもひとつまちがえば命 にかかわる。／Giving birth is a huge undertaking, and even with the high standard of modern medicine, one slightest mistake can make a difference of life or death.

（2）政治家 の不用意 な発言 が続 いている。ひとつ間違 えば外交 問題 にも発展 しかねない。／Politicians have been making a series of verbal blunders. One careless utterance could escalate into a diplomatic incident.

（3）カーレースは、ひとつまちがえば、大事故 につながることもある危険 な競技 である。／Car racing is a dangerous pursuit in which a small error can lead to a major accident.

（4）ひとつ間違 えば大惨事 になるところだった。／At that point, one mistake could have turned it into a disaster.

（5）乗 る予定 だった飛行機 が墜落 した。ひとつ間違 えば、私 もあの事故 で死 んでいたと思 うとぞっとする。／The airplane I was supposed to catch crashed. It chills me to think that I came so close to dying in that accident.

Means “by a very small margin.”

Shows that there is a high probability of something disastrous happening, and whether this materializes or not is determined by something very small and marginal. Often used in the form of ひとつまちがえば...こともある／かねない (if it went the wrong way...it could result in ...).

In the cases of (4) and (5), disastrous situations have been narrowly avoided. In particular, ひとつ間違えば...ところだった indicates that “although it didn’t happen, it was very close.”

<< 【ぶり】 | Home | 【ぶん】 >>

【ぶる】

［N／Na　ぶる］

（1）彼 は、通 ぶってフランスの上等 なワインしか飲 まない。／He pretends to be a connoisseur by drinking only expensive French wine.

（2）父 は学者 ぶって解説 を始 めた。／My father started explaining as though he were an expert.

（3）あの人 は上品 ぶってはいるが、たいした家柄 の出 ではない。／She tries to look posh, but in fact she isn’t from a family of any consequence.

（4）彼 はもったいぶってなかなか教 えてくれない。／He is so pompous that he wouldn’t part with the information readily.

（5）三年生 になった長女 は、先輩 ぶって一年生 の妹 にいろいろ教 えたりしている。／The eldest daughter is now in the third grade and helps her little first grade sister like a true upperclassman.

Means that someone behaves in a manner that is typical of the role the person is emulating. Often used in the context of いかにもたいした...である (behaving as if the person is a “real someone/something”). As in the cases of (1) - (3), it often shows the speaker’s negative evaluation of someone who “behaves as though he is X” or who is pretentious and makes a fuss over something minor. In (4), もったいぶって is an idiomatic phrase that means “affected, putting on airs” and is used in conjunction with phrases such as なかなか教えない／言わない. It has limited usage.

<< 【ぶん】 | Home | 【べからず】 >>

【べからざる】

［V-るべからざる］

（1）川端 康成 は日本 の文学史 上 、欠 くべからざる作家 だ。／Kawabata Yasunari is a writer who could not be omitted in any history of Japanese literature.

（2）大臣 の地位 を利用 して、企業 から多額 の金 を受 け取 るなどは、政治家 として許 すべからざる犯罪 行為 である。／It is an unforgivable criminal act for a politician to use his or her position as a government minister to receive large sums of money from companies.

（3）いかなる理由 があったにせよ、警官 が一般 市民 に暴行 を加 えるなど、あり得 べからざる異常事態 だ。／Whatever the reason, it is beyond belief that a policeman should use physical violence on an ordinary citizen.

Used in the form of べからざるN. It is the classical written language version of べきでないN. It indicates that the action or the state is not right or undesirable and means ...ことができないN or ...てはいけないN (N that cannot do something or N that should not do something).

(1) means that the person cannot be omitted or must not be forgotten. (2) means that the criminal act is so terrible that it should be stopped. (3) refers to an incident that would not/should not take place.

A limited number of verbs can take this form. As in the cases of (1)-(3), it is often used in idiomatic phrases such as 欠くべからざる人物, 許すべからざる行為, あり得べからざる事態. Note that in the case of 得る in (3), べからざる is attached to 得, forming 得べからざる. It is a formal written language style. Also note that the pronunciation of 得 in 得べからざる is u rather than e.

<< 【べからず】 | Home | 【べく】 >>

【べき】

［N／Na　であるべき］

［A-くあるべき］

［V-るべき］

This is a conjugation of the literary auxiliary verb べし. It attaches to the dictionary form of verbs in modern usage. する becomes either するべき or すべき in form.

1. ...べきだ

（1）学生 は勉強 す（る）べきだ。／Students ought to study.

（2）他人 の私生活 に干渉 す（る）べきではない。／You should not interfere with someone else’s private life.

（3）近頃 は小学生 まで塾 に通 っているそうだが、子供 はもっと自由 に遊 ばせるべきだ。／I hear nowadays even primary school children attend cram schools, but I think children should have greater freedom just to play.

（4）女性 は常 に化粧 をして美 しくあるべきだなどという考 えには賛成 できない。／I cannot agree with the idea that women should always be made up and look pretty.

（5）地球的 規模 で自然破壊 が進 んでいる。人間 は自然 に対 してもっと謙虚 であるべきだ。／Ecological destruction is progressing on a global scale. People ought to be more thoughtful about nature.

（6）教師 : 君 、成績 が良 くないね。もっと勉強 するべきだね。／Teacher: Your academic record is not good. You ought to study harder.

学生 : すみません。／Student: Sorry.

（7）A:海外 研修 に行 くかどうか迷 っているんだ。／I am debating whether I should go on an overseas study tour.

B:そりゃ、行 くべきだよ。いいチャンスじゃないか。／You should go! It is a good opportunity, isn’t it?

（8）この仕事 はきみがやるべきだ。／You should do this job.

（9）会社 の電話 で私用 の電話 をするべきじゃないね。／You shouldn’t be making personal calls on the company telephone, you know.

Means that “it should be done,” “it is proper to do ...,” or “... must be done.” The negative form is べきではない meaning “it is not good to do ...” or “doing ... is not appropriate” or “must not do ....”

In (1)-(5), the speaker is expressing his view on general matters. If used in relation to the actions of another, it becomes advice for or against doing something, prohibition, or an order. This expression is used in both spoken and written language.

2. ...べき　だった／ではなかった

［V-る／V-ておく　べきだった］

（1）あの時 買 っておくべきだった。／I should have bought it then.

（2）あんなひどいことを言 うべきではなかった。／I shouldn’t have said such a nasty thing!

（3）君 はやっぱりあのときに留学 しておくべきだったんだよ。／In hindsight, you should have gone abroad to study then.

Indicates one’s regrets over an action one took or didn’t take and means “I wish I had done ...” or “I wish I hadn’t done ....”

(1) means that the speaker wished he had bought it then but he did not. (2) means that the speaker wished he had not said something unkind but in reality, he did. In (3), the speaker is saying to his friend that he should have gone abroad to study. When the speaker talks about himself, it shows his regrets or remorse. This expression is often used in both everyday written and spoken language.

3. ...べきN

（1）外交 政策 について、議論 すべきことは多 い。／With regard to the diplomatic policies, there are many issues that need to be discussed.

（2）エジプトのピラミッドは、永遠 に残 すべき人類 の遺産 である。／The pyramids of Egypt are a world legacy that should be protected for future generations forever.

（3）エイズは恐 るべき速 さで世界中 に広 がっている。／AIDS is spreading around the world at a fearful speed.

（4）人 は皆 死 すべき運命 を背負 っている。／Everyone is fated to die.

Means “something that has to be done” or “the inevitable consequence.”

(1) indicates what has to be discussed as an important issue. (2) means that a world heritage should be maintained as a matter of course and should be passed on to the future generations. (3) and (4) are idiomatic phrases each meaning “incredible speed” and “unavoidable eventual death” respectively.

A formal expression that is often used in written language.

<< 【べき】 | Home | 【べし】 >>

【べく】

［V-るべく］

The verb stem of an auxiliary verb べし that is used in classical written language. It is used in modern Japanese as an expression that is formal and is in the style of written language.

1. ...べくV-た

（1）大学 に進 むべく上京 した。／They went to Tokyo in order to go to university.

（2）速 やかに解決 すべく努力 致 します。／We will do our best to resolve the issue promptly.

（3）しかるべく処置 されたい。／Please deal with the matter appropriately.

Means “in order to do ...” or “so that ... can be done.” (3) is asking for an appropriate action to be taken. Used in formal expressions in the style of written language.

2. V...べくしてV-た

（1）この機械 の危険性 は以前 から何度 も指摘 されていた。この事故 は起 こるべくして起 こったといえる。／The danger of this machinery has been pointed out on numerous occasions. It could be said that this accident was waiting to happen.

（2）彼 が勝 ったのは偶然 ではない。練習 につぐ練習 を重 ねて、彼 は勝 つべくして勝 ったのだ。／His victory was not coincidental. Practice after practice brought about his well-deserved victory.

Means something has happened as it has been anticipated as a matter of course when the verb is repeated.

(1) means that people had been worried that an accident might take place and indeed, an accident did happen. (2) means that it is no wonder he won because he had worked for it so hard, and it is not because of luck or coincidence.

A formal expression in the style of written language.

3. ...べくもない

（1）多勢 に無勢 では勝 つべくもない。／Being so outnumbered by our opponents, we have no chance of winning.

（2）優勝 は望 むべくもない。／There is no hope of coming in first.

（3）突然 の母 の死 を、遠 く海外 にいた彼 は知 るべくもなかった。／Being so far away overseas, there was no way for him to learn of his mother’s sudden death.

Means that something is not achievable, cannot be done, or something cannot happen. It is a formal expression in the style of written language, and it is not used very often in modern Japanese.

<< 【べく】 | Home | 【へた】 >>

【べし】

［V-るべし］

（1）学生 はすべからく勉強 に励 むべし。／Students should apply themselves to their studies.

（2）後生 おそるべし。／The next generation carries our hopes.

（3）今度 の試験 は、よほど難 しかったらしく、クラスで一番 良 くできる生徒 でも 60 点 しかとれなかった。後 は推 して知 るべしだ。／The recent examination must have been very difficult because even the brightest student in the class got only sixty points. You can imagine how the rest of the class did.

An expression used in the classical written language, rarely used in modern language except in idioms. Expresses a command with the meaning of “ought to do ... as a matter of course” or “it is appropriate to do ....”

(1) takes the form of すべからく...べし and in this context it means, “It’s a matter of course that students must study, so study!”

(2) is an idiom meaning, “Young people have great potential and therefore they should be nurtured.”

(3) is an idiomatic phrase meaning, “if one thinks about it, it will become apparent.” In the context of this example, it means that it goes without saying that all the rest of the students got poorer marks.

<< 【ほとんど】 | Home | 【まえ】 >>

【まい】

Structurally, まい is placed after a Group 1 verb in dictionary form, or a Group 2 verb in either verb stem or dictionary form. As for the Group 3 verbs 来る and する, there are two possibilities each of くるまい／こまい and するまい／すまい, respectively. Of the two, くるまい and するまい are more common in both verbs.

When used with non-verbs, ない becomes あるまい, Nではない becomes Nではあるまい, Naではない becomes Na ではあるまい, and A-くない becomes A-くあるまい.

Can also be attached to ます to form ますまい.

1. ...まい

a. V-まい〈volition〉

（1）酒 はもう二度 と飲 むまい。／I shall not drink sake ever again.

（2）あいつにはもう二度 と会 うまい。／I shall not see her ever again.

（3）A:佐々木 とけんかしたんだって？／Is it true that you quarreled with Sasaki?

B:そうなんだよ。人 が親切 で言 ってるのに聞 こうともしないんだ。あいつにはもう何 も言 うまいと思 っているんだ。／Yes. He wouldn’t listen to me when I was advising him out of kindness. I have made up my mind that I won’t say anything to him anymore.

（4）二日 酔 いの間 はもう二度 と飲 みすぎるまいと思 うが、ついまた飲 み過 ぎてしまう。／When I have a hangover I always think that I won’t drink too much ever again, but then I can’t help indulging myself in drinking again.

（5）その時 、広子 は、二度 と田中 には会 うまいと固 く決心 した。／Just then, Hiroko firmly made up her mind that she would not see Tanaka ever again.

（6）母 を悲 しませまいと思 ってそのことは知 らせずにおいた。／I kept it secret from my mother so as not to upset her.

Expresses the speaker’s intention of not doing something. In spoken language, V-ないようにしよう and V-ないつもりだ are commonly used. To express someone else’s intention, as in the case of example (5), ...まいと決心する／思う／考える are used. Example (6) is in a formal style often found in written language, and it means that the speaker does not want to make his mother upset.

b. V-まいとする

（1）銃 を奪 われまいとして争 いになった。／It developed into a fight as both sides tried to keep the gun from being taken by the other.

（2）夏子 は泣 くまいとして歯 を食 いしばった。／Natsuko clenched her teeth to keep herself from crying.

（3）家族 の者 を心配 させまいとする気持 ちから、会社 をやめたことは言 わずにおいた。／From my desire not to worry my family, I said nothing about the fact that I had left my company.

Means “trying not to do something.” A formal expression often found in writing. When it is used in the form of ...まいとして, して is sometimes omitted.

（例）銃を奪われまいと争いになった。／It developed into a fight as both sides tried to keep the gun from being taken by the other.

2. ...まい〈supposition, conjecture〉

（1）このうれしさは他人 にはわかるまい。／I don’t suppose anyone else could understand how happy I feel now.

（2）税金 を減 らすのに反対 する人 はまずあるまい。／I don’t suppose there is anyone who opposes a decrease in taxation.

（3）山田 氏 の当選 はまず間違 いあるまい。／There’s no mistaking that Yamada-shi (Mr. Yamada) will win the election.

（4）年老 いた両親 も亡 くなって、ふるさとにはもうだれもいなくなってしまった。もう二度 と訪 れることもあるまい。／Now that both my elderly parents have died, there is nobody waiting for me in my hometown. I don’t think I will be visiting it again.

（5）こんな話 をしてもだれも信 じてはくれまいと思 って、今 まで黙 っていたのです。／Because I thought no one would believe me even if I tried to explain, I haven’t told anyone about this until now.

（6）顔 を見 るだけで他人 の過去 を当 てるなんて妙 な話 だが、これだけ証人 がいるのならまんざら嘘 でもあるまい。／Though it is very strange that anyone can tell someone else’s past by just looking at his or her face, with so many attesting to this fact, there could be some truth to it.

（7）他 ならぬ松下 さんの御依頼 ですから、父 もまさかいやとは言 いますまい。／Since it is a request from none other than Matsushita-san, I would never have thought that my father would refuse it.

（8）子供 が初 めて下宿 した時 には、かぜをひいてはいまいか、一人 でさびしがっていはしまいかと心配 でならなかった。／When my child first started living in a boarding house, I was so worried over whether she might catch a cold or feel lonely.

Means that someone will likely not do something. Expresses the speaker’s conjecture. Rarely used in spoken language, as in the case of example (7). 言わないだろう or 言わないでしょう is more common. However, it may be used in spoken language when it is used in quotations accompanying と思って or と考えて, as in example (5).

3. ...でもあるまい

a. Nでもあるまい

（1）仕事 を紹介 して下 さる人 もあるが、私 ももう 70 だ。この歳 になって、いまさら会社勤 めでもあるまい。／Some people want to find work for me, but I am already seventy. At this age, I can’t see starting to work for a company.

（2）自分 から家 を出 ておきながら、今 ごろになって、同居 でもあるまい。／He left home on his own a long time ago, so at this point we can hardly expect him to live with his family again.

Indicates that something or an action is not appropriate or befitting the situation. Often used in the form of いまさら／いまごろ、...でもあるまい, indicating that time has passed and it is no longer appropriate for a certain event to take place or to take a certain action.

b. Nでもあるまいし

（1）子供 でもあるまいし、自分 のことは自分 でしなさい。／You are no longer a child, so take charge of your own things yourself.

（2）学生 でもあるまいし、アルバイトはやめて、きちんと勤 めなさい。／You are not a student, so stop working part-time and get a real job.

（3）17 や 18 の小娘 でもあるまいし、男 に振 られたぐらいで、いつまでもくよくよするのはやめなさい。／You are no longer a girl of seventeen or eighteen, so stop moping on and on just for being dumped by a guy.

Means “because something/someone is not N” or “because something/someone is not supposed to be N.” Often used in conjunction with a prohibitive or imperative form and is often used in scolding or criticizing someone. The form では／じゃあるまいし is also found.

c. V-ることもあるまい

（1）あんなにひどい言 い方 をすることもあるまいに。／There wasn’t any need for saying it so harshly, was there?

（2）あの程度 のことで、大 の大人 が泣 くこともあるまい。／There is no need for a fully grown adult to cry over something so trivial as that.

（3）電話 か手紙 で用 は足 りるのだから、わざわざ行 くほどのこともあるまい。／Since the matter can be dealt with by telephone or letter, there is hardly any need for anyone to go there in person.

Used in order to convey the opinion that a certain action is inappropriate or unnecessary. A formal expression often used in written language. In spoken language, V-ることもないだろう is used more often.

4. まいか

a. ...ではあるまいか

［N／Na　（なの）ではあるまいか］

［A／V　のではあるまいか］

（1）彼 は若 くみえるが、本当 はかなりの年輩 なのではあるまいか。／Though he looks young, I wonder if he is in fact quite old.

（2）佐藤 さんは知 らないふりをしているが、全部 わかっているのではあるまいか。／Though Sato-san is pretending not to know anything, she may in fact know everything.

（3）児童 の自殺 があいついだのには、現在 の教育 制度 に、何 か問題 があるのではあるまいか。／I wonder if there aren’t some problems in the current system of education that have caused this outbreak of children’s suicides.

（4）他人 への無関心 が、このような事件 を引 き起 こす一因 となったのではあるまいか。／Indifference towards other people may have been one of the factors that caused this incident.

（5）知識 のみを偏重 してきたことは、現在 の入試 制度 の大 きな欠陥 ではあるまいか。／Putting too much emphasis on book-learning alone may be considered as a major defect in the current entrance examination system.

（6）会社 や組織 のためにのみ働 き続 ける生活 は、誰 よりも本人 が一番 苦 しいのではあるまいか。／For a life that is spent working continuously for a company or organization, it is the person him/herself who probably suffers more than anyone else.

Indicates the speaker’s conjecture ...ではないだろうか (I wonder if it isn’t a case of ...).

When used in conjunction with a noun or na-adjective, takes either of the two forms: N/Naではあるまいか or N/Naなのではあるまいか.

As in the cases (3) through (6), often used in introducing the discussion point or in presenting the speaker’s assertion by taking the form of a question to the listener. A formal expression used mainly in written language.

b. V-てくれまいか

V-てもらえまいか

（1）忙 しいからと一度 は断 わったのだが、なんとかやってもらえまいかと何度 も頼 まれてしかたなく引 き受 けた。／I had refused to do it once by saying that I was too busy, but then I gave in and agreed to do it since I was begged so many times.

（2）A:例 のニューヨーク支店 の件 だが、支店長 として、まず君 に行 ってもらえまいか。／About the New York store... I wonder if you would go there first of all as the store manager.

B:かしこまりました。／Yes, I will.

Indicates a request. A masculine, formal expression. In spoken language, either V-てくれ or V-てもらえないだろうか is more common. As in (1), often used for quoting another person with the forms ...と頼まれた／言われた.

5. V-ようがV-まいが→【よう2】4c

6. V-ようとV-まいと→【よう2】6c

<< 【まじき】 | Home | 【まず】 >>

【まして】

1. まして（や）

（1）日本語 の勉強 を始 めて3年 になるが、まだ新聞 を読 むのも難 しい。まして古典 などはとても読 めない。／It has been three years since I started learning Japanese, but it is hard enough reading newspapers, let alone the classics.

（2）この辺 りは昼 でも人通 りが少 ない。まして夜 ともなると、怖 くて一人 では歩 けない。／There are very few people who pass through this area even during the day. It goes without saying that at night I would be too scared to walk about on my own.

（3）僕 にでもできた仕事 だ。まして君 のような優秀 な人間 にできないはずはない。／Even I could have done this job. There is no reason why such an able person as you can’t do it.

（4）家族 の死 は常 に悲 しい。まして、子供 の死 ともなれば、残 された者 の嘆 きは、いかばかりであろうか。／A death in the family is always sad. And when it is the death of a child, how absolutely devastating it must be for the surviving family.

Often used in the patterns Xは...ましてYは... or Xでも...ましてYは.... Comparing X with Y, which possesses the quality used to describe X to an even greater extent, it means “as even X is (descriptive expression), Y is of course even more so.” ましてや is a rather formal expression that has the tone of written language.

2. Nにもまして

（1）日本 の夏 は暑 い。しかし、暑 さにもまして耐 えがたいのは、湿度 の高 さだ。／Japanese summers are hot. However, what’s even harder to bear than the heat is the high level of humidity.

（2）本当 にいい映画 だった。映像 の美 しさはもちろんだが、それにもまして音楽 がすばらしかった。／It really was a good movie. The images were beautiful, of course, but the music was even more wonderful.

（3）彼 はもともとまじめでよく働 く人間 だが、子 どもが生 まれてからというもの、以前 にもましてよく働 くようになった。／By nature he’s a hardworking person, but since his children were born, he works even harder than before.

（4）何 にもましてうれしかったのは、友人 の加藤 君 と 10 年 ぶりに再会 できたことだった。／What made me happier than anything else was meeting my friend Kato-kun again for the first time in ten years.

Used in the patterns Xにもまして...なのはYだ, XにもましてYが... etc., means “X is of course (descriptive expression) but Y is more so.” By comparing Y to X, the expression emphasizes the high degree to which Y possesses the quality discussed. As in the case of (3), when used in the form 前にもまして or 以前にもまして it means “still (even) more than before.” As in the case of (4), 何にもまして means “more than anything,” “the most.”

<< 【まで】 | Home | 【まま】 >>

【までに】

［Nまでに］

［V-るまでに］

（1）レポートは来週 の木曜日 までに提出 して下 さい。／Please submit your report by Thursday of next week.

（2）何時 までに伺 えばよろしいですか。／What time should I be there by?

（3）明日 までにこの仕事 を済 ませてしまいたい。／I want to get this job finished by tomorrow.

（4）夏休 みが終 わるまでにこの本 を読 んでしまいたい。／I want to finish reading this book by the end of summer vacation.

Attached to nouns of time or clauses which show events, expresses the time frame or deadline of an action. When an expression which shows an action or function comes after this phrase, it shows that the action or function will take place at a point in time before the given time period or deadline.

...まで...する shows that an action or situation continues until a certain point in time, but ...までに...する does not denote continuity and demonstrates the occurrence of a certain event. Therefore, phrases expressing continuity cannot be used after ...までに.

（×）5時までにここで待っています。／I will be waiting here until five o’clock.

（○）5時までここで待っています。／I will be waiting here until five o’clock.

Apart from demonstrating time frames, there is an idiom 参考までに that is used in letters, etc. Here it means “for reference” or “for your information.”

（例）ご参考までに資料をお送りします。／I will send the documents for your reference.

<< 【みせる】 | Home | 【みだりに】 >>

【みたいだ】

［N／Na／A／V　みたいだ］

A casual expression mainly used in speaking. In formal sentences or situations ようだ is used more commonly. It is unusual to replace ようだ in idiomatic expressions with みたいだ.

1. ...みたい〈simile〉

Used to show a condition, nature, form, or behavior of things by giving something similar as an example. It is the same as よう. まるで／ちょうど...みたい can be used to emphasize extreme similarity. As あたかも, いかにも, and さながら are formal written expressions, they cannot be used with みたい.

a. NみたいなN

（1）この薬 は、チョコレートみたいな味 がする。／This medicine tastes like chocolate.

（2）竹 下 さんって、あの学生 みたいな人 でしょ？／Takeshita-san is that guy who looks like a student, right?

（3）いい年 をして、子供 みたいな服 を着 ないでほしいな。／At your age, I wish you wouldn’t wear such childish clothes.

（4）飛行機 みたいな形 の雲 が浮 かんでいる。／There’s a cloud there that looks like an airplane.

When used in the form N1みたいなN2, N2 is described by giving an example of something (N1) to which it bears some resemblance.

Can be rephrased using N1のようなN2. Not to be confused with NらしいN, where N1=N2. N1みたいなN2 only gives something which resembles N2 as an example and so N2 is not actually the thing denoted by N1. For example, 男みたいな人 means that the person appears like a man but, in reality, is not a man. In contrast to this, 男らしい人 means that the person is very manly, or that masculine characteristics are prominent in that person, and it is used in reference to males.

b. ...みたいだ

［N／V　みたいだ］

（1）すごい風 だ。まるで台風 みたいだ。／What a wind! It’s just like a typhoon.

（2）君 ってまるで子供 みたいだね。／You’re just like a child.

（3）その地方 の方言 に慣 れるまでは、まるで外国語 を聞 いているみたいだった。／Until I got used to the dialect of that area, it was just like listening to a foreign language.

（4）私 が合格 するなんてうそみたい。／That I have passed (the exam) seems unbelievable.

What the speaker felt about the condition, nature, form, or behavior of things is expressed by giving an easy-to-comprehend example of something which bears some resemblance to them. It can be replaced with ...ようだ. Many women omit the sentence-final だ in everyday conversation, as in example (4). うそみたいだ means “(it’s) unbelievable” or “(I’m) very surprised.”

c. ...みたいに

［N／A／V　みたいに］

（1）もう9月 も半 ばなのに、真夏 みたいに暑 い。／Even though it’s the middle of September, it’s hot like midsummer.

（2）この服 は、買 って何年 にもなるが、新品 みたいにきれいだ。／It’s many years since I bought these clothes, but they look as good as new.

（3）子供 みたいにすねるのはやめろよ。／Stop sulking like a child.

（4）こんなにうまいコーヒーが、一杯 100 円 だなんて、ただみたいに安 いね。／Having coffee this good for only 100 yen a cup—it’s so cheap it seems free.

（5）私 ばかりが悪 いみたいに言 わないでよ。あなただって悪 いんだから。／Don’t speak as if only I was bad! You were bad, too!

（6）A:学校 ではあまり会 わないね。／We don’t see you much at school.

B:おいおい、そんな言 い方 をしたら、僕 が授業 をさぼってばかりいるみたいに聞 こえるじゃないか。／Hey, when you talk like that, it sounds like I’m always skipping classes.

Used to show the condition, nature, form, or behavior of things by giving something similar as an example. Examples (5) and (6) imply “even though (that) is not the case....”

d. ...みたいなものだ

［Nみたいなものだ］

［V-たみたいなものだ］

（1）僕 の給料 なんか、会社 の儲 けに比 べたら、ただみたいなものさ。／When it comes to my salary, compared to the company’s profits, it’s like I’m working for free.

（2）《野球 をみながら》こんなに点差 があけば、もう勝 ったみたいなものだ。／《while watching baseball》With this kind of point spread, it’s like they’ve already won.

（3）A:中田 さん、店 、売 ったんだって？／Is it true that Nakata-san sold his shop?

B:売 ったというか、まあ、取 られたみたいなものだ。借金 の抵当 にはいってたんだそうだよ。／Sold? Well, more like it was taken. Apparently it was used as collateral against a loan.

Means “(it) has still not actually happened but (it) is almost sure to” or “the situation is almost the same as....” In speech, もんだ is often used in place of ものだ.

2. ...みたいだ〈supposition, conjecture〉

（1）誰 も彼女 の本名 を知 らないみたいだ。／It seems that nobody knows her real name.

（2）田中 さんは甘 いものが嫌 いみたいだ。／It seems that Tanaka-san dislikes sweet things.

（3）どうもかぜをひいたみたいだ。／I might have caught a cold.

（4）今度 発売 された辞書 は、すごくいいみたいだよ。／The dictionary being launched now seems really good.

（5）何 か焦 げているみたいだ。へんな匂 いがする。／Something seems to be burning. There is a strange smell.

（6）A:あの人 誰 ？／Who is that?

B:誰 だろう。近所 の人 じゃないみたいだね。／Hmm, I wonder. He doesn’t look like someone from around here.

（7）A:試験 はいつあるんだい。／When’s your exam?

B:来週 みたいだよ。／It looks like next week.

（8）A:あの人 会社 をやめたの？／Has that person quit the company?

B:みたいだね。／It would seem so.

（9）A:小林 さんはもうアメリカに行 ったのかな？／Kobayashi-san has already gone to America, hasn’t she?

B:ええ、きのう出発 したみたいですよ。／Yeah, it seems she left yesterday.

（10）A:山本 さん怒 っていたでしょう？／Yamamoto-san was angry, wasn’t he?

B:うん、すごく怒 ってるみたいだった。／Yeah, he seemed very angry.

（11）そのときの佐々木 さんはなんだか怖 くて、いつもの彼 ではないみたいだった。／Sasaki-san was kind of scary at that time. He didn’t seem like his usual self.

Shows the speaker’s supposition. Means “(I) can’t be certain but (I) think it is so.” Expresses the speaker’s inference based on what they themselves have experienced, something they have seen, heard, or sensed.

In contrast to this, when expressing a supposition based on information gained indirectly, such as something heard from another person, らしい is used. When reporting something as it was heard from another, そうだ is used.

（例）山下さんは今日は来ないみたいですね（もう、時間も遅いし）。／It looks like Yamashita-san is not coming today (because the time is already late).

（例）山下さんは今日は来ないらしいですよ（直接きいたわけではないが、他の人がそう言っていた）。／It looks like Yamashita-san is not coming today (I haven’t heard this directly but somebody else was saying so).

（例）山下さんは今日は来ないそうです（山下さんから「行かない」という伝言があった）。／It looks like Yamashita-san is not coming today (I had a message from Yamashita-san saying she is not coming).

...みたいだ and ...みたいだった are both often used, but their meanings are different. As in the next example, V-たみたいだ concerns a thing which occurred in the past and shows the inferred outcome at the time of speaking.

（例）A:田中さんはいつ来たのかな？／I wonder when Tanaka-san arrived.

B:午前中は見かけなかったから、昼から来たみたいですよ。／I didn’t see him this morning and so he must have come after noon.

V-たみたいだった shows that the speaker thought something to be the case at a certain point in the past.

（例）昨日の夜は妙だった。誰か来たみたいだったから、ドアをあけてみたが、だれもいなかった。そんなことが何度もあった。／Last night was strange. Because I thought someone had come, I opened the door, but there was nobody there. That kind of thing has happened many times.

Also, when describing a situation as it is seen, for example, when there is a cake before your eyes, このケーキはおいしいみたいだ is not used. In such a case このケーキはおいしそうだ is used.

（例）A:これ、新しく買ったスマートフォンです。／This is my new smartphone.

（○）B：便利そうですね。／B：It looks handy.

（×）B：便利みたいですね。／B：It looks handy.

The そう that is used in such cases is different from the そう used to express hearsay and so care must be taken. When expressing hearsay we use おいしいそうだ(they say it is tasty) and 便利だそうだ (they say it is handy/convenient).

3. ...みたい〈example〉

［NみたいなN］

［Nみたいに］

（1）東京 や大阪 みたいな大都会 には住 みたくない。／I don’t want to live in a big city like Tokyo or Osaka.

（2）A:三分 間 写真 の機械 って、どんなところにある？／What kind of place will have an instant photo booth?

B:さあ、デパートみたいなところにはあるんじゃないかな。／Well, won’t they have them in places like department stores?

（3）何 か細 くて長 い棒 みたいな物 はありませんか。／Do you have something long and thin like a pole?

（4）佐藤 さんみたいに英語 が上手 になりたい。／I want to become good at English like Sato-san.

（5）今年 みたいに暑 いと、働 くのが本当 にいやになる。／When it’s as hot as this year, work really becomes a pain.

（6）君 みたいなあわて者 、見 たことがないよ。／I’ve never seen anyone as discombobulated as you.

（7）彼 みたいに勝手 なことばかりしていると、そのうち誰 も相手 にしなくなる。／If he keeps on doing selfish things like he is now, eventually nobody will want to have anything to do with him.

Used to give examples. Example (1) means “big cities such as Tokyo and Osaka, for example,” while (2) means “large shops like department stores, for example.”

Examples (5), (6), and (7) take the form of exemplifications but, in reality, they can be thought to mean the same as “because this summer was really hot, I didn’t like to work,” “you really are disorganized,” and “because he always does selfish things, eventually nobody will want anything to do with him.” In polite speech ...のような／ように is used.

<< 【めく】 | Home | 【めったに】 >>

【めぐって】

［Nをめぐって］

（1）憲法 の改正 をめぐって国会 で激 しい論議 が闘 わされている。／Fierce debates are being fought in the Diet surrounding the revision of the constitution.

（2）彼 の自殺 をめぐって様々 なうわさや憶測 が乱 れとんだ。／There are various rumors and speculation surrounding his suicide.

（3）人事 をめぐって、社内 は険悪 な雰囲気 となった。／An ugly atmosphere has developed within the company concerning personnel.

Means “relating to...” or “concerning....” Used to include the peripheral circumstances of a thing and to take them as the subject. Unlike ...について, there are many verbs with which it cannot be used.

（×）日本の経済をめぐって研究しています。／I am researching the Japanese economy.

（○）日本の経済について研究しています。／I am researching the Japanese economy.

Only verbs such as 議論する (to argue), 議論を闘わす (to have a heated debate), うわさが流れる (to be rumored) and 紛糾する (to become complicated) can be used with めぐる, and the nouns must be something that various people can argue about or discuss. をめぐり is often used in writing. When it is used to modify a noun, the form becomes NをめぐるN or NをめぐってのN.

（例）政治献金をめぐる疑惑がマスコミに大きくとりあげられている。／Suspicions surrounding political donations have been widely reported by the mass media.

（例）父親の遺産をめぐっての争いは、日増しにひどくなっていった。／The quarrels over their father’s inheritance were getting worse by the day.

<< 【めぐって】 | Home | 【も】 >>

【めったに】

1. めったに...ない

（1）私 は酒 はめったに飲 まない。／I seldom drink alcohol.

（2）うちの子 は丈夫 でめったに病気 もしない。／Our child is in good health and rarely gets sick.

（3）人混 みは好 きではないので、東京 や大阪 などの大都市 にはめったに行 かない。／I don’t like crowds of people and so I rarely go to big cities like Tokyo or Osaka.

（4）この頃 の機械 は優秀 で故障 はめったにない。／Appliances these days are well-made and so rarely break down.

（5）わが家 はずいぶん田舎 にあるので、お客 がやって来 ることはめったにない。／Our house is in a pretty rural area, so we rarely have guests dropping by.

（6）学生 時代 の友人 とも遠 く離 れてしまって、めったに会 うこともない。／I rarely meet friends from my university days because we live so far apart.

（7）近頃 は町中 で野生 の小動物 を見 かけるようなこともめったになくなった。／Nowadays you rarely catch sight of small wild animals in town anymore.

Expresses that the frequency with which something is done is extremely low. Often used in the form めったにV-ない, as in examples (1) - (3), or in the form ...はめったにない, as in examples (4) and (5).

たまに also expresses low frequency, but the point of emphasis is different. For example, both (1) and (2) below mean “alcohol is consumed very infrequently” but the めったに...ない in example (1) emphasizes the low frequency. In contrast, たまに in example (2) expresses that, although the frequency is low, it does take place.

（例1）私は酒はめったに飲みません。／I rarely drink alcohol.

（例2）私は酒は嫌いですが、友だちに誘われたときなど、たまには飲むこともあります。／I don’t like alcohol but, when I am invited by a friend, for example, I occasionally do drink it.

For these phrases, frequency decreases in this order: あまり...ない > ほとんど／めったに...ない > ぜんぜん／まったく...ない.

2. めったな

（1）めったなことで驚 かない私 も、そのときばかりはさすがにうろたえてしまった。／I am usually not surprised by things, but even so, I lost my cool just at that moment.

（2）A:山下 さんが盗 ったんじゃない？／Didn’t Yamashita-san steal it?

B:しっ。証拠 もないのに、めったなことを言 うもんじゃないよ。／Shh! There’s no evidence of that, so don’t say such things.

（3）この機械 は丈夫 ですから、めったなことでは故障 しません。／This appliance is so durable it hardly ever breaks down.

（4）このことは、めったな人 に話 してはいけない。／You shouldn’t talk of this to just anyone.

An idiomatic expression. Used in the form of めったなことで（は）...ない, it expresses that “unless there is a set of extreme circumstance/conditions, the event/action in question does not take place.” Example (1) means “generally not surprised, can take most things calmly” and (2) means “it is wrong to say irresponsible/imprudent things.”

Use of the form めったなN, as in example (4), is becoming rare. Means “it is wrong to talk (of this) to people other than a select (few/group).”

<< 【もさることながら】 | Home | 【もしかしたら】 >>

【もし】

With a conditional phrase following it, this expression conveys the speaker’s attitude in establishing his/her assumptions about a thing. It is often used at the beginning of a sentence. Synonyms are かりに and もしも. For the differences between this and もしも, see the entry for もしも.

1. もし...たら

（1）もし雨 が降 ってきたら、洗濯物 を取 り込 んでおいてね。／If it starts to rain, bring the washing in, will you?

（2）もしよろしければ、週末 、家 にいらっしゃいませんか。／If it’s all right with you, would you come to my home this weekend?

（3）もしお暇 なら、いっしょにドライブに行 きませんか。／If you have time, will you come for a drive with me?

（4）もし気 が付 くのが1秒 でも遅 かったら大惨事 になっていただろう。／If you had noticed just one second later, it would have been a huge disaster.

Phrases such as ...は／...なら can be used in place of たら. Accompanying a hypothetical situation where what follows is a result of that situation, means “supposing... then....” As in examples (1) to (3), it is used to predict or imagine an event, the truth of which is pending or not yet known, and, as in (4), it is used to anticipate or imagine an event which is inconsistent with reality.

This is similar to かりに, but かりに is used to suppose something which does not actually exist, while もし can be used whether or not something actually exists, but the speaker desires to make a supposition. For this reason, it can be used both in (1), where something is likely to happen, and in (4), which is contrary to the truth.

（×）かりに雨が降ってきたら、洗濯物を取り込んでおいてね。／Supposing that it should start to rain, bring the washing in, will you?

2. もし　...ても／...としても

（1）天気 予報 では曇 りですが、もし雨 でも遠足 は決行 します。／The weather forecast says it will be cloudy, but even if it rains, we’ll go on the field trip.

（2）薬 で治 りそうですが、もし手術 をすることになっても、簡単 に済 みます。／It seems that it will get better with medicine, but, even if surgery is necessary, it’s a simple procedure.

（3）もし泥棒 に入 られたとしたって、たいして金目 になるものはない。／Even if a burglar breaks in, there is nothing of monetary value.

（4）もし入社 試験 に合格 しても、本人 に入社 の意志 がないのなら辞退 すべきだ。／Even if one passes the company entrance test, if the person has no intention of joining the company, he or she ought to turn the offer down.

Used with conditional clauses such as ても, としても, and としたって, expresses the meaning “even if such a situation should come into being.” Often carries the implication that “there is little possibility, but....” Generally かりに can be used in its place.

<< 【もしくは】 | Home | 【もちまして】 >>

【もしも】

Used to further express the word もし, this means “supposing such were the case.”

1. もしも...たら

（1）もしも家 が買 えるなら、海辺 の洋館 がいい。／If I could buy a house, a western-style one near the beach would be nice.

（2）もしも僕 が君 の立場 だったら、違 う行動 をとると思 う。／If I were in your situation, I think I would behave differently.

（3）もしも私 が君 ぐらい若 ければ世界中 を飛 びまわっているだろう。／If I were as young as you, I think I would be travelling extensively around the world.

（4）もしも地震 が起 こるのがあと30 分 遅 ければ、被害 は甚大 なものになっていただろう。／If the earthquake had happened thirty minutes later, the damage would probably have been enormous.

Used with conditional expressions such as たら／ば／なら, this expresses the assumption that “if such were the case,” in reference to things which may or may not become reality or which are inconsistent with the facts.

2. もしものN

（1）父 にもしものことがあったらどうしよう。／If something happened to Father, what would we do?

（2）もしもの場合 にはすぐ連絡 してください。／If something should happen, please contact me right away.

（3）大地震 はそんなにちょくちょく起 こるわけではないが、もしもの時 のために準備 をしておいた方 がよい。／It’s not that major earthquakes happen so frequently, but it’s better to be prepared for such a time.

Nouns such as 時, 場合, こと come after もしも and express the meaning that “if by some chance, such a situation should be the case....” This is used in reference to such things as death, critical conditions, major disasters, and undesirable serious situations. Example (1) is a euphemistic way of talking about death. 万一 carries roughly the same meaning and can be used in this way also. もし cannot be used in this way.

<< 【ものなら】 | Home | 【ものを】 >>

【ものの】

1. ...ものの

（1）輸入 果物 は、高 いもののめずらしいらしく、人気 があってよく売 れている。／Imported fruit is expensive, but perhaps because people seem to find it unusual, it is popular and sells well.

（2）新 しい登山靴 を買 ったものの、忙 しくてまだ一度 も山 へ行 っていない。／I bought new hiking boots, but I’ve been busy and have yet to go to the mountains even once.

（3）今日 中 にこの仕事 をやりますと言 ったものの、とてもできそうにない。／I said I would finish this work by the end of today, but it doesn’t look at all possible.

（4）自然 の多 い郊外 に家 を買 ったものの、休 みの日 は寝 てばかりだ。／I bought a house in the suburbs with lots of undisturbed nature (close by), but on my days off I just sleep.

（5）次 の企画 を始 めるお金 はあるものの、アイデアがなくて困 っている。／I have the money to start the next project, but I just can’t come up with any ideas for it.

（6）招待状 は出 したものの、まだほかの準備 は全 くできていない。／I have sent out the written invitations, but I still haven’t been able to do any other preparations at all.

（7）先月 仕事 で久 しぶりに東京 へ行 った。大学 時代 の友人 に電話 でもかけてみようとは思 ったものの、忙 しさにまぎれて、つい、そのままにしてしまった。／Last month I went to Tokyo for the first time in a long time on business. I wanted to give one of my college friends a call or something, but I ended up being so busy that it ultimately never happened.

Mentioning a past event or a current situation, used to continue the sentence and means “but/however....” Afterwards, the sentence usually continues with a statement that what was expected to occur did not or does not look likely to occur.

Example (1) means “they are expensive and, therefore, not likely to sell well and yet they do.” With phrases such as やるといったのにむずかしい in example (3), phrases which express that “(the speaker) has no confidence in the situation that is to follow” or “it is difficult” often continue the sentence and relate to a thing they have said, or done, or to a particular circumstance.

2. ...とはいうものの

（1）四月 とはいうものの風 がつめたく、桜 もまだだ。／Although it is April, the wind is cold and the cherry blossoms are late.

（2）相手 は子供 とはいうものの、なかなか手 ごわい。／Although just a child, the opponent is pretty tough.

（3）「石 の上 にも三年 」とは言 うものの、こんなに訓練 がきびしくてはやめたくなる。／They say “perseverance prevails” (lit. three years on a (cold) stone (will make the stone warm)), but training like this is hard and makes me think about quitting.

（4）人間 は平等 だとはいうものの、この世 は不平等 なことばかりだ。／All people are equal, but this world is full of inequalities.

This means that something which is generally thought does not apply. Example (1) means that “usually in April it is warm and cherry blossoms bloom, but this year that is not the case.” As in example (3), it is often used in proverbs or maxims.

3. とはいうものの

（1）大学 時代 は英文学 専攻 だった。とはいうものの、英語 はほとんどしゃべれない。／I majored in English literature in college. Having said that, I can barely speak English.

（2）車庫 付 きの家 も買 ったし、すっかり結婚 の準備 は整 っている。とはいうものの、肝心 の結婚 相手 がまだ見 つかっていないのが悩 みだ。／I have bought a house with a garage and all the preparations for marriage are in order. Be that as it may, the crux of the problem is that I still haven’t found someone to marry.

Expresses that the situation is different than what would be expected as a result of the previous statement. Means “that may be so but” or “however.”

<< 【やたらに】 | Home | 【やなんぞ】 >>

【やっと】

1. やっと〈realization of expectations〉

（1）三回 試験 を受 けて、やっと合格 した。／On my third attempt, I finally passed the exam.

（2）テストもやっと終 わった。／The tests are also finally over.

（3）何日 も練習 してやっとできるようになった。／I practiced for days and finally became able to do it.

（4）やっと、退院 できるところまで快復 した。／At last I recovered enough to leave the hospital.

（5）1995 年 にトンネルはやっと完成 した。／The tunnel was finally completed in 1995.

（6）きびしく注意 したので、孫 もやっといたずらをしなくなった。／Because he was harshly scolded, my grandchild finally stopped making mischief.

（7）明日 でやっと試験 も終 わる。／Tomorrow I will finally finish the exams.

（8）貯金 もかなりできた。これでやっと独立 できる。／I have some savings. With them I will finally stand on my own two feet.

（9）娘 も来年 はやっと卒業 だ。／My daughter will also finally graduate next year.

Expresses a situation in which, after hard work or after a difficult time, the thing the speaker had been hoping for has been realized. Often used in the form やっとV-た. It shows the speaker’s feelings of relief or pleasure and that something took time or was difficult.

ようやく, とうとう, and ついに are similar expressions. とうとう and ついに can be used in relation to things the speaker either desires or does not desire. However, やっと can only be used in relation to something the speaker has been hoping for.

（例）長い間入院していた祖父が｛とうとう／ついに｝亡くなった。／After being in the hospital for a long time, my grandfather finally passed away.

In the above example, if やっと is used it means that the speaker has been waiting a long time for their grandfather to die. If とうとう or ついに is used, it bears no relation to whether the speaker wished for it or not but rather is a neutral expression meaning that, after a long time or journey, the final stage has been reached.

Furthermore, as they are used in cases in which the thing the speaker had been anticipating has materialized, やっと and ようやく cannot be used when something the speaker had hoped for has not materialized in the end.

（×）彼は、｛やっと／ようやく｝来なかった。／In the end he didn’t come.

（○）彼は、｛とうとう／ついに｝来なかった。／In the end he didn’t come.

2. やっと〈barely manage (to do something)〉

Can be used in both speaking and writing. どうにか, なんとか, かろうじて, and からくも are similar expressions. どうにか and なんとか are spoken expressions and かろうじて is a somewhat formal written expression. からくも is a formal written expression. For details of how this differs from かろうじて, refer to かろうじて (Usage 1).

a. やっとV-た

（1）タクシーをとばして、やっと約束 の時間 に間 に合 った。／Having raced there in a taxi, I just made my appointment on time.

（2）試合 は延長戦 にもつれこんだが、全力 を振 り絞 ってやっと勝 った。／The game went into extra innings, but mustering all their strength, they finally won.

（3）うちの子 は先月 やっと二才 になったばかりだ。／My child just turned two last month.

（4）彼 が出発 してから、まだやっと三日 しかたっていない。／Still only three days have passed since he left.

As in examples (1) and (2), used in cases where something was difficult, but through the application of effort or through the endurance of hardship, things came out well in the end. As in (3) and (4), when used with expressions of quantity, demonstrates that that quantity is the utmost, that there is no more than that, and that the quantity is small. Here, (3) means “to just reach the age of two (very young)” and (4) means “merely three days.”

b. やっとV-ている

（1）退職 してからは、国 から支払 われる年金 で、やっと生活 している。／I can just get by on the pension I get from the state after retiring.

（2）私 は太 りやすい体質 で、ダイエットをしてやっと現在 の体重 を維持 している。／I put on weight easily and have to diet just to maintain my current weight.

（3）人工 呼吸器 を使 って、やっと生 きている状態 だ。／The use of an artificial respirator is only just keeping him/her alive.

（4）一面 焼 け野原 で、焼 け残 った家 も、燃 え残 った柱 のおかげで、やっと立 っているというありさまだった。／In the burned-out ruins, the shell of the house was barely standing owing to the burnt remains of the pillars.

As in examples (1) and (2), can be used in cases where “(it) is not enough but, through hardship, the current situation can be maintained.” As in (3) and (4), also used in cases where the worst situation (death or ruin) is one step away but, somehow, the current situation is maintained.

c. やっとV-るN

（1）私 の家 は、家族 5人 がやっと暮 らせる広 さしかない。／In my house there is just barely the room for the five members of my family to manage to live.

（2）柿 の実 は、大人 が背伸 びをしてやっと届 くところにあった。／The persimmons were on high branches that an adult on tiptoe could just reach.

（3）何年 も英語 を勉強 しているが、やさしい本 がやっと読 める程度 で、新聞 なんかとても読 めない。／I’ve been studying English for many years and can just manage to read a simple book, but there is no way I could read something like a newspaper.

Indicates “N that is achievable to the degree of やっと／なんとか／どうにか...できる.” Shows that “(something) is difficult but can somehow just be done.” Used with expressions of possibility.

d. やっとNだ

（1）宿題 はなかなか終 わらない。まだやっと半分 だ。／It is taking a long time to finish my homework. I’ve still got half of it to do.

（2）この本 はすごく難 しくて、なかなか進 まない。三時間 かかって、やっと5ページだ。／This book is really difficult and I’m not making much progress with it. It’s taken me three hours to read just five pages.

（3）私 の収入 は、何 もかも全部 含 めても、やっと 10 万 円 だ。／If I put all my income together, it just comes to 100,000 yen.

（4）娘 は、まだやっと 18 才 だ。結婚 なんかとんでもない。／My daughter is still just eighteen years old. Things like marriage are unthinkable.

（5）うちの子 は、まだやっと幼稚園 だ。／My child is still only in kindergarten.

As in examples (1)-(3), used with expressions of quantity, shows that that quantity has been reached after tremendous efforts. Used in cases where the speaker thinks that the quantity is not proportionate to the effort put in. Also, used with expressions of age or school year as in (4) and (5), means “no more than...” or “very young/immature.”

e. やっとのN

（1）戦争中 は毎日 食 べていくのがやっとの生活 だった。／During the war, it was all one could do to eat every day.

（2）日常 会話 がやっとの語学力 では、大学 の授業 を受 けるのは難 しいだろう。／If everyday conversation is the limit of your language ability, it will probably be difficult for you to take university classes.

（3）やっとの思 いで、彼女 に秘密 を打 ち明 けた。／After agonizing over it, he told her his secret at last.

（4）やっとのことで、一戸建 ての家 を手 にいれた。／At long last I got my own house.

Used in the forms ...するのがやっとのN and NがやっとのN, means “doing something with all one’s might, there is no scope beyond that effort.” Also, the やっとの思いで and やっとのことで of (3) and (4) are idiomatic expressions meaning “after going to great trouble/putting in great effort.”

f. Nが／...のが　やっとだ

（1）家 の前 の道 は、車 一台 が通 るのがやっとだ。／Just a single car can pass along the road in front of my house (as the road is narrow).

（2）私 の給料 では、食 べていくのがやっとだ。／On my wages, all I can afford is to put food on the table every day.

（3）子供 の頃 は体力 がなくて、毎日 学校 に通 うのがやっとだった。／In my childhood I was physically weak and it was all I could do to get to school and back.

（4）この本 はすごく難 しくて、なかなか進 まない。一日 に5ページがやっとだ。／This book is very difficult and I’m making little progress. I can only read five pages a day.

Means “to do (something) with all one’s might with no scope beyond that.”

<< 【よう1】 | Home | 【ようするに】 >>

【よう2】

［V-よう］

One of the Japanese verb conjugation forms. Expresses the speaker’s will or conjecture. -よう attaches to the continuative form of Group 2 verbs, for example: 見よう((will) see) , 食べよう((will) eat). 来る(come) and する(do) become こよう((will) come) and しよう((will) do). In the case of Group 1 verbs, -う is added to the o-row, for example: 行こう((will) go), 読もう((will) read), 話そう((will) speak). In polite Japanese, the form is R-ましょう, as in 食べましょう, 行きましょう.

1. V-よう〈intention〉

Using verbs which demonstrate intentional acts, expresses the intent behind the speaker’s action. The rules of usage differ depending on the situation in which it is used, for example in a report, an invitation, or an indirect demand.

In polite Japanese, expressions such as ...しましょう／いたしましょう are used.

a. V-よう〈volition〉

（1）夏休 みには海 に行 こう。／Let’s go to the sea during summer vacation.

（2）来年 こそはよい成績 がとれるように頑張 ろう。／Let’s do our best to get good grades next year for sure.

（3）何 にもすることないから、テレビでも見 ようっと。／As there is nothing to do, I’ll watch television or something.

（4）はっきり申 しましょう。あなたにはこの仕事 は無理 です。／Let me be frank with you. For you, this job is impossible.

（5）A:今夜 一杯 いかがですか。／How about a drink this evening?

B:そうですねえ。今日 は遠慮 しておきましょう。／Hmm. I’m going to take it easy today.

Using verbs which demonstrate intentional acts expresses the speaker’s intention and assumption that the action will take place. Example (3) is an expression typical of someone speaking to themselves. Can also be pronounced in the shorter form V-よっと.

b. V-よう〈offer〉

（1）足 が痛 いのか。おぶってやろう。／Do your legs hurt? I’ll carry you.

（2）忙 しいのなら、手伝 ってあげよう。／If you’re busy, I’ll help you.

（3）その荷物 、お持 ちしましょう。／Let me carry that luggage (for you).

（4）切符 は私 が手配 いたしましょう。／I’ll arrange the tickets.

（5）駅 までお送 りしましょう。／I’ll take you to the station.

Used by the speaker to offer something they can do for another person. It is an action the speaker intends to do for the benefit of another. In humble speech, as in examples (3)-(5), it becomes ...いたしましょう or お...しましょう／いたしましょう.

c. V-よう〈invitation〉

（1）君 もいっしょに行 こうよ。／Why don’t you come with us?

（2）一度 ゆっくり話 し合 おう。／Let’s discuss it at our leisure some time.

（3）今夜 は飲 み明 かそうよ。／Let’s drink the night away tonight.

（4）お待 たせしました。では出 かけましょう。／Thank you for waiting. Right, let’s be going.

Used to invite the listener to act together with the speaker. In contrast to the meaning〈offer〉in b, where only the speaker is to undertake the action,〈invitation〉is used to invite the listener also to act together with the speaker.

d. V-よう〈appeal〉

（1）横断 する時 は左右 の車 に注意 しよう。／Watch out for cars from the left and right when crossing.

（2）飲酒 運転 は絶対 に避 けよう。／Let us make sure we will never drink and drive.

（3）食事 の前 には手 を洗 いましょう。／Please wash your hands before eating.

（4）動物 にいたずらしないようにしましょう。／Please don’t disturb the animals.

Used to appeal to a mass of people either to carry out or to refrain from carrying out a certain action. An expression often used on posters or bunting which is to be seen by many people and appeals to people to follow its instructions/advice.

e. もらおう／V-てもらおう

（1）ビールをもう一本 もらおう。／Get me another beer.

（2）あんたには死 んでもらおう。／You must die!

（3）ちょっと警察署 まで来 ていただきましょう。／We’d like you to come to the police station.

In the form (V-て)もらおう／いただこう, used to make an indirect demand of the listener. Similar to expressions used to make requests such as ビールをください(please give (me) beer), 死んでくれ(die!), and 来てください(please come) but (V-て)もらおう has the stronger nuance that the speaker is making a unilateral demand. From a social perspective, it is difficult to use this if one is not a person of higher social rank or in a position of higher authority in the workplace.

2. V-よう〈supposition, conjecture〉

Like だろう, this expresses the speaker’s conjecture but is somewhat more old-fashioned. Has the tone of written language. i-adjectives also have the same rules of usage as this (A-かろう) , as inよかろう／寒かろう.

a. V-よう

（1）場合 によっては延期 されることもあろう。／Depending on the situation, it may be postponed.

（2）この点 については次 のようなことが言 えよう。／Regarding this point, perhaps we can say the following.

（3）午後 からは全国的 に晴 れましょう。／It is likely to be sunny across the country from the afternoon.

（4）山沿 いでは雪 になりましょう。／There is likely to be snow in the mountains.

This shows the speaker’s conjecture. It is often used with phrases which express possibility but not will, such as ある and なる or 言える, できる, 考えられる and あり得る. The negative form is V-まい.

An old-fashioned, written expression. In speech, だろう is used. V-ましょうis the polite form of V-ようand was often used on weather forecasts in the past but nowadays でしょう is used.

b. V-ようか

（1）結論 としては、次 のようなことが言 えようか。／I wonder if we might conclude the following.

（2）こんなひどいことをする人間 がこの世 にあろうか。／Are there really people in this world who would do such a horrible thing?

（3）こんなに貧 しい人達 をどうして放 っておけようか。／How can we ignore such needy people?

（4）そんな馬鹿 げたことがありえましょうか。／Is such stupidity possible?

A way of saying だろうか in writing. Shows doubt or rhetorical negation. The irony in examples (2)-(4) can be interpreted as meaning “I wonder/no, that’s not the case.” Many use it in the direct style.

3. V-ようか〈intention〉

Makes a question of the volitional form of a verb and is used in cases where the speaker is expressing some doubt as to their own intentions or ideas and asks for the listener’s intent. The basic rules of usage are the same as V-よう but, through the addition of the か, the meaning changes to expressing uncertainty or asking a question.

a. V-ようか〈volition〉

（1）どうしようか。／What should we do?

（2）昼 ご飯 は何 にしようかな。／What should we have for lunch?

（3）行 こうか、それともやめておこうか。／Should I go or should I give it a miss?

（4）私 の考 えていること、白状 しちゃおうか。／Should I confess what I’m thinking?

（5）こんな仕事 やめてしまおうかしら。／Perhaps I ought to quit this kind of work?

（6）これからどうして暮 らしていこうか。／How am I going to live now?

Expresses that the speaker is in two minds over whether to conduct the act or not and has not decided. Apart from か, かな and かしら can also be attached. As かな and かしら are more in the style of someone speaking to themselves, it is difficult to use them with polite Japanese and ましょうかな／ましょうかしら and so on are not usually used.

b. V-ようか〈offer〉

（1）君 の代 わりに僕 がやろうか。／Shall I do it instead of you?

（2）荷物 、僕 が持 とうか。／Shall I carry your luggage?

（3）何 かお手伝 いしましょうか。／Can I help you with something?

（4）いいこと教 えてあげましょうか。／Shall I tell you something good?

Used with both rising and falling intonation but, when used with a rising intonation, the sense that a question is being asked is stronger.

c. V-ようか〈invitation〉

（1）結婚 しようか。／Shall we get married?

（2）何時 に待 ち合 わせしようか。／What time shall we meet?

（3）どこかで食事 しましょうか。／Shall we get a meal somewhere?

（4）いっしょに海外旅行 しましょうか。／Shall we take a trip abroad together?

Used to invite the listener to undertake an action together with the speaker. Often used with falling intonation but, when rising intonation is used, the sense that a question is being asked is stronger.

d. もらおうか／V-てもらおうか

（1）お茶 を一杯 もらおうか。／Could I have a cup of tea?

（2）これ、コピーしてもらおうか。／Copy this for me.

（3）君 には、しばらく席 をはずしていだだきましょうか。／Would you leave us for a moment?

（4）A:もうすぐ、帰 ると思 います。／I think she’ll return soon.

B:じゃ、ここで待 たせてもらいましょうか。／In that case, I will wait here.

Used to indirectly make a demand of the listener. The attachment of the か adds the sense that the speaker has only just arrived at that thought or that there is a feeling of hesitation and so this makes the request slightly softer than without it. From a social perspective, it is usually used by people of superior rank speaking to their subordinates.

4. V-ようが

A written version of V-ても and means “whatever kind of action is taken/whatever kind of situation occurs.” Phrases such as 自由だ／勝手だ(be free (to do)/be up to (someone)), which express that an event, a decision, or a demand will come to take place regardless of that action/situation come afterwards. There are many instances in which it can be rephrased as V-ようと but there are also cases in which it cannot be rephrased.

a. V-ようが

（1）どこで何 をしようが私 の勝手 でしょう。／What I do and where is up to me.

（2）人 になんと言 われようが、自分 の決 めたことは実行 する。／Whatever people say to you, do what you have decided to do.

（3）彼 がどうなろうが、私 の知 ったことではない。／Whatever happens to him is nothing to do with me.

Shows that the latter thing occurs without being restricted by the former. The latter part uses expressions such as 自由だ(be free(to do))／勝手だ(be up to (the person)) which demonstrate intention or determination.

b. V-ようがV-ようが

（1）出掛 けようが家 にいようが、あなたの自由 です。／Go out, stay in, it’s up to you.

（2）雨 が降 ろうがやりが降 ろうが、試合 は決行 します。／Whether drops or spears fall from the sky, the match shall take place.

（3）みんなに笑 われようがバカにされようが、気 にしない。／I don’t care whether I’m laughed at or made fun of by everyone.

Used to list things which are opposite or which are similar, this means “whatever happens/whatever (one) does.” The rules of usage are the same as for Usage 4a above.

c. V-ようがV-まいが

（1）あなたが出席 しようがしまいが、私 は出席 します。／Whether you attend or not, I will.

（2）勉強 をやろうがやるまいが私 の勝手 でしょう。／It’s up to me whether I study or not.

（3）パーティは参加 しようがしまいが、皆 さんの自由 です。／Whether they attend the party or not is up to everyone individually.

Using both the positive and the negative volitional form of the same verb, this means “whichever action (one) takes.” A formal way of saying ...してもしなくても.

5. V-ようじゃないか

（1）一緒 に飲 もうじゃないか。／We should go drinking together.

（2）みんなでがんばろうじゃないか。／Let’s do our best together.

（3）よし、そんなにおれと喧嘩 したいのなら、受 けて立 とうじゃないか。／Right, if you want to fight with me so much, I’ll take you on.

（4）今夜 は、語 り明 かそうではありませんか。／Let’s talk all night tonight.

Attached to verbs which express intention, this is a strong declaration of one’s intentions and is used to invite the listener to act together with the speaker. Mainly used by men and has a stronger sense of influence over the other person than V-ようか. Women usually use ...ましょう. The polite form is ...ようではありませんか／ないですか.

6. V-ようと

A written version of V-ても and means “whatever kind of action is taken/whatever kind of situation occurs.” Phrases such as 自由だ／勝手だ(be free (to do)/be up to (someone)), which express that a thing will come to take place regardless of that action/situation come afterwards. There are many instances in which it can be rephrased as V-ようが but there are also cases in which it cannot be rephrased as ても.

a. V-ようと

（1）なにをしようと私 の自由 でしょう。／What I do is up to me.

（2）どこへ行 こうとあなたの勝手 です。／Where you go is up to you.

（3）どんなに馬鹿 にされようと、腹 をたてるでもなく彼 はひたすら働 いている。／However much people make fun of him, he just carries on working without getting angry.

Expresses that the latter thing occurs without being restricted by the former. Phrases such as 勝手だ(up to (someone))／自由だ(free (to do)／関係ない(nothing to do with) come afterwards.

b. V-ようとV-ようと

（1）努力 しようと怠 けようと結果 がすべてだ。／Whether you work hard or are lazy, it’s the result that counts.

（2）あなたが泣 こうとわめこうと、僕 には関係 ない。／Whether you cry or shout, it’s nothing to do with me.

（3）行 こうとやめようと私 の勝手 だ。／Whether I go or not is up to me.

（4）遊 ぼうと勉強 しようとお好 きなようにしてください。／Whether you play or study, please do as you wish.

（5）煮 て食 おうと焼 いて食 おうとご自由 に。／Eat boiled or baked as you wish.

（6）駆 け落 ちしようと心中 しようと勝手 にしろ。／Elope or commit double (lovers’) suicide as you wish.

Used to list things which are opposite or which are similar, this means “it doesn’t matter what (you) do/it’s up to you” and that, whatever action one takes, regardless of that the latter thing will occur.

c. V-ようとV-まいと

（1）行 こうと行 くまいとあなたの自由 だ。／Whether you stay or go is up to you.

（2）たくさん食 べようと食 べまいと料金 は同 じだ。／Whether you eat a lot or not, the cost is the same.

（3）君 が彼女 に会 おうと会 うまいと僕 には関係 のないことだ。／Whether you meet her or not is nothing to do with me.

Means “whether one does... or not.”

d. V-ようとも

（1）皆 にどんなに反対 されようとも決 めたことは実行 する。／However much people oppose me, I’ll do what I’ve decided.

（2）たとえどんなことが起 ころうとも、彼 からは一生 離 れない。／Whatever happens, I’ll never leave him.

（3）どんなに脅 かされようとも、彼 は毅然 とした態度 をくずさなかった。／However much he was threatened, they didn’t break his resolve.

（4）いかに富 に恵 まれようとも、精神 が貧 しくては幸 せとは言 えない。／However much wealth you are blessed with, if you have no heart it cannot be called happiness.

Adding も to V-ようと, this is a written expression for V-ても. The meaning and rules of usage are the same as for instances without も but this carries a slightly more old-fashioned nuance. Often used with phrases such as (たとえ)どんなに／いかに.

7. V-ようとおもう

（1）お正月 には温泉 に行 こうと思 う。／I think I’ll go to a hot spring at New Year’s.

（2）来年 はもっと頑張 ろうと思 う。／I think I’ll try harder next year.

（3）今夜 は早 く寝 ようと思 っている。／I’m thinking of going to bed early this evening.

（4）今 の仕事 を辞 めようかと思 っている。／I’m wondering whether I should quit my job.

（5）外国 に住 もうとは思 わない。／I have no intention of living abroad.

（6）あなたは一生 この仕事 を続 けようと思 いますか。／Do you think you’ll do this job for life?

Taking verbs which demonstrate intention, this is used to express the speaker’s plans or intentions. In interrogative sentences it is used to ask the listener’s intentions. Also, the かと思う of example (4) demonstrates that the speaker’s indecisiveness or hesitancy. V-ようと(は)思わない means that the speaker has no such intention.

Similar to つもりだ but differs in that つもりだ can be used to express the will of a third person.

（○）山田さんは留学するつもりだ。／Yamada-san intends to study abroad.

（×）山田さんは留学しようと思う。／Yamada-san intends to study abroad.

Moreover, V-ると思う is used to express the speaker’s conjecture rather than will and cannot be used in cases where one wishes to express intention. In such cases V-ようと思う must be used.

（×）私は東京へ行くと思う。（意志の表現としては誤り）／I think I will go to Tokyo. (Incorrect as an expression of intention.)

（○）私は東京へ行こうと思う。／I think I will go to Tokyo.

8. V-ようとする

a. V-ようとする〈immediately before〉

（1）時計 は正午 を知 らせようとしている。／The clock is about to strike midday.

（2）長 かった夏休 みもじきに終 わろうとしている。／The long summer holiday is coming to an end.

（3）日 は地平線 の彼方 に沈 もうとしている。／The sun is setting over there on the horizon.

（4）上 り坂 にさしかかろうとする所 で車 がエンストを起 こしてしまった。／I stalled the car’s engine as I approached the ascent.

（5）お風呂 に入 ろうとしていたところに、電話 がかかってきた。／Just as I was about to get in the bath, the phone rang.

Means “just before/on the verge of” an action or change taking place. Typically used with non-volitional verbs such as 始まる(begin) and 終わる(end) but, when used in the form V-ようとするところ, it can also be used with volitional verbs. In instances in which non-volitional verbs are used, it is often a literary or poetic expression.

b. V-ようとする〈attempt〉

（1）息子 は東大 に入 ろうとしている。／My son is trying to get into Tokyo University.

（2）彼女 は 25 歳 になる前 に何 とか結婚 しようとしている。／She is trying to get married somehow before she turns 25.

（3）いくら思 い出 そうとしても、名前 が思 い出 せない。／However hard I try, I cannot remember his name.

（4）棚 の上 の花 びんをとろうとして、足 を踏 みはずしてしまった。／I lost my footing trying to get the vase from the shelf.

（5）本人 にやろうとする意欲 がなければ、いくら言 っても無駄 です。／If the person him/herself has no motivation, whatever you say is futile.

（6）寝 ようとすればするほど、目 がさえてきてしまった。／The more I tried to sleep, the more wide-awake I became.

Taking verbs which demonstrate intentional action, this expresses that attempts or efforts are made to realize that action.

c. V-ようと（も／は）しない

（1）うちの息子 はいくら言 っても勉強 をしようとしない。／Whatever I say, my son has no intention of studying.

（2）隣 の奥 さんは私 に会 っても挨拶 ひとつしようとしない。／Even when she sees me, the lady next door never greets me.

（3）その患者 は食 べ物 を一切 うけつけようとしない。／That patient won’t have any food.

（4）声 をかけても振 り向 こうともしない。／Even when I call out, he will not even turn to face me.

（5）彼女 はこの見合 い話 をおそらく承諾 しようとはしないだろう。／I don’t think she’ll consent to this arranged marriage.

Taking verbs which express intentional action, this expresses a lack of intention to carry out that action or deed. When も is inserted, as in V-ようともしない, it emphasizes a denial and means “have no intention even of ...ing.” As in example (5), は is also sometimes inserted.

9. V-ようとはおもわなかった

（1）こんなことになろうとは思 わなかった。／I had no idea this kind of thing would happen.

（2）被害 がこれほどまで広 がろうとは、専門家 も予想 しなかった。／Even the experts didn’t predict that the damage would be so widespread.

（3）息子 が、たった一度 の受験 で司法 試験 に合格 しようとは夢 にも思 わなかった。／I didn’t even dream that my son would pass the bar exam at just the first attempt.

（4）たったの五日 で論文 が完成 しようとは誰一人 想像 しなかった。／No one imagined that I would finish my thesis in just five days.

Taking non-volitional verbs such as なる, means “that such a thing would happen was not predicted.”合格しよう(will pass) and 完成しよう(will do) of examples (3) and (4) express that the thing happened naturally or spontaneously and, as such, like 合格／完成できる and 合格／完成することになる, they do not express the speaker’s intention. Apart from 思う, verbs which follow are those such as 予想／想像する(predict/imagine) and always take the form -なかった. It is a written expression.

10. V-ようにもV-られない

（1）頭 が痛 くて、起 きようにも起 きられない。／My head hurts and I couldn’t get up even if I wanted to.

（2）まわりがうるさくて、落 ち着 いて考 えようにも考 えられない。／It’s noisy around me and, even though I want to calm down and think, I can’t.

（3）風 が強 すぎて走 ろうにも走 れない。／The wind is so strong and I can’t run however much I try.

（4）雨 が降 っているので、外 で遊 ぼうにも遊 べない。／Because it’s raining, even though you want to play outside you can’t.

Attached to verbs which demonstrate intentional actions, means “even though one intends to... one can’t.” The same verb is repeated before and after. It is often used in cases where something cannot be done regardless of a strong wish to do it.

<< 【ようするに】 | Home | 【ようだ2】 >>

【ようだ1】

［Nのようだ］

［A／V　ようだ］

Conjugating na-adjectives, this becomes ように and ような in the continuative and attributive forms.

1. ...ようだ〈simile〉

a. ...ようだ

（1）この雪 はまるで綿 のようです。／This snow is just like cotton wool.

（2）彼女 の心 は氷 のように冷 たい。／Her heart is as cold as ice.

（3）男 は狂 ったように走 り続 けた。／He kept running like mad.

（4）赤 ん坊 は火 がついたように泣 き出 した。／The baby burst out crying as if she were on fire.

（5）あたりは、水 を打 ったように静 まりかえっている。／The area suddenly became completely silent.

（6）新製品 は面白 いようによく売 れた。／The new product sold like hot cakes.

（7）6月 が来 たばかりなのに真夏 のような暑 さだ。／Although June has just begun, it is hot like midsummer.

（8）会場 は割 れるような拍手 の渦 につつまれた。／The venue was engulfed by the tumultuous applause.

（9）身 を切 るような寒 さが続 いている。／The biting coldness continues.

Used to liken a situation, quality, form, or action to something which is essentially different. Not only used to liken a thing to something with similar properties but also to entirely distinct, fanciful, things. Often attached to nouns and verbs but, occasionally, as in example (6), also attached to i-adjectives. However, cannot be attached to na-adjectives. Also, sometimes used with accompanying adverbs which are used to express similes, such as あたかも, いかにも, さながら, まるで and ちょうど.

（例）町はすっかりさびれてしまって、まるで火が消えたようだ。／The town is in complete decline, just like a fire has gone out.

（例）家族が一堂に揃い、あたかも盆と正月がいっしょに来たようだ。／To have the family all together in one room is just like the Bon Festival and the New Year’s holiday have come at the same time. (= a very busy and happy time)

Often appears in customary, fixed expressions. Idiomatic expressions other than those which appear here are: 雲をつかむような話／竹を割ったような性格／血のにじむような努力／手が切れるような新札／飛ぶように売れる／目を皿のようにして探す (a vague story/a straightforward character/to sweat blood/a crisp new note/to sell like hot cakes/to search with wide eyes) .

In speech, みたいだ is often used. Furthermore, in writing ごとし can also be used.

b. V-る／V-た　かのようだ

（1）彼 はなにも知 らなかったかのように振 る舞 っていた。／He was acting as though he didn't know anything.

（2）父 はあらかじめ知 っていたかのように、平然 としていた。／My father was calm, as though he already knew.

（3）本当 は見 たこともないのに、いかにも自分 の目 で見 てきたかのように話 す。／You haven’t even seen (it) but you talk as though you have.

（4）極楽 にでもいるかのような幸 せな気分 だ。／I’m so happy I feel like I’m in paradise.

（5）犯人 は事件 のことを初 めて聞 いたかのような態度 をとった。／The criminal acted as though he was hearing about the incident for the first time.

（6）あたり一面 霧 に包 まれ、まるで別世界 にいるかのようだ。／The whole area is enveloped in mist; it is like I am in another world.

Taking the dictionary or ta-form of a verb, expresses that, although in reality (it) is not the case, one’s conduct or feeling is that it is. It is often used in cases which pick out things as examples which are inconsistent with reality or are imaginary.

2. ...ような／...ように

a. ...ように〈example〉

（1）あの人 のように英語 がペラペラ話 せたらいいのに。／I wish I could speak English as fluently as that person.

（2）ニューヨークのように世界中 の人々 が住 む都市 では、各国 の本格的 な料理 を味 わうことができる。／In cities like New York, where people from all around the world live, you can taste authentic food from many countries.

（3）母親 が美人 だったように、娘 たちもみな美人 ぞろいだ。／The daughters are all beauties like their mother was.

（4）私 が発音 するようにあとについて言 ってください。／Please pronounce it as I do, after me.

（5）先生 がおっしゃったようにお伝 えしておきました。／I told it as my teacher told it to me.

Taking the form XようにY, used to give a specific person or thing as an example of conformity/consistency in quality, content or method with Y. Example (4) means “to imitate an action” and (5) can be rephrased as とおりに.

In contrast to Usage 1 inようだ〈simile〉, an expression which compares an essentially different and distinct thing to X in the phrase まるでXのように, with this usage X is given as an example of a specific thing which shares a property or content with Y. However, it is not always possible to distinguish between these two usages.

b. ...ようなN〈example〉

（1）風邪 をひいたときは、みかんのようなビタミンC を多 く含 む果物 を食 べるといい。／When you catch a cold, it’s good to eat a lot of fruit like oranges which contain a lot of vitamin C.

（2）あなたのようなご親切 な方 にはなかなか出会 えません。／It’s not very often we meet people as kind as you.

（3）これはどこにでもあるようなものではない。／This is not the kind of thing you find everywhere.

（4）彼 はあなたが思 っているような人 ではない。／He is not the kind of person you think he is.

（5）このまま放 っておくと、取 り返 しがつかないようなことになりかねない。／If you leave it as it is, it’s quite possible that you won’t be able to sort it out.

（6）これを食 べても死 ぬようなことはありません。安心 してください。／You won’t die if you eat this. Please rest assured.

（7）薬 を飲 んでもよくならないような場合 は医者 に相談 してください。／In cases where you do not recover after taking medicine, please consult your doctor.

Used to give a concrete example of the noun which follows it. For example, in みかんのような果物(a fruit like an orange), the latter noun represents a higher concept than the former. When continued after a clause, the sentence can be valid without ような but there will be some difference in the meaning if it is included or not. For example, if ような is removed from (7) as 薬を飲んでもよくならない場合 it refers to a specific situation where “the condition does not improve after taking the medicine,” but in case of 薬を飲んでもよくならないような場合 then it means “cases like when you take the medicine but the condition does not improve” indicating that there are many other similar situations.

c. ...ように〈introductory utterance〉

（1）ご存 じのように、日本 は人口密度 の高 い国 です。／As you know, Japan is a country with a high density of population.

（2）あなたがおっしゃっていたように、彼 は本当 に素敵 な方 ですね。／As you were saying, he’s a really lovely man.

（3）すでに述 べたようにアフリカの食糧 不足 は深刻 な状況 にある。／As has already been mentioned, Africa’s food shortage is serious.

（4）ことわざにもあるように、外国 に行 ったらその国 の習慣 に従 って暮 らすのが一番 である。／As the maxim says, when you go abroad, it’s best to live by the customs of that country.

（5）あのにこにこした表情 が表 しているように、彼 はとても明 るい性格 の人 です。／As his smiling expression shows, he has a very cheerful character.

Shows that what is about to be said is consistent with what has been stated previously or is a well-known fact. Used to give notice that further explanation is about to be given. Can be replaced with とおり.

d. つぎのように／いかのように

（1）結果 は次 のようにまとめることができる。／The results can be summarized in the following manner.

（2）中 には以下 のような意見 もあった。／Among them there were the following kinds of opinion.

（3）本稿 の結論 をまとめれば、次 のようになる。／We can summarize the article’s conclusions as follows.

（4）以下 で示 すように、我 が国 の出生率 は下 がる一方 である。／As seen below, the birthrate of our country is declining.

Used to announce that concrete detail is to follow. In vertical text compositions, 右のように and 左のように are also used.

<< 【ように2】 | Home | 【ようやく】 >>

【ように3】

1. V-る／V-ない　よう（に）〈purpose〉

（1）後 ろの席 の人 にも聞 こえるように大 きな声 で話 した。／I said it in a loud enough voice so that even the people in the seats behind could hear it.

（2）子供 にも読 めるよう名前 にふりがなをつけた。／I put my name in furigana so that even children would be able to read it.

（3）赤 ん坊 を起 こさないようにそっと布団 を出 た。／I got out of the futon softly, so as not to wake the baby.

（4）忘 れないようにノートにメモしておこう。／I will make a note of this so I won’t forget.

Using a verb before and after, this means “do... so as to make such a circumstance or situation occur/do... so as not to....”に is sometimes omitted. Before ように, verbs which show non-volitional actions, such as なる and できる, or verbs which show possibility in the form V-れる are often used, as are the negative forms of verbs and expressions which show the state or condition of a thing. The clause which follows ように is a verb which demonstrates the speaker’s intentional act. The subject may differ before and after, as in examples (1)-(3), or it may be the same, as in (4).

Furthermore, in cases where the subject is the same before and after, and where the first verb demonstrates an intentional action, it is usual to use ために.

（×）息子が家で仕事ができるために父親は家を改築した。（異主語･非意志的）／So that his son could work from home, the father renovated the house. (different subject, non-volitional)

（○）息子が家で仕事ができるように父親は家を改築した。（異主語･非意志的）／So that his son could work from home, the father renovated the house. (different subject, non-volitional)

（○）家で仕事をするために家を改築した。（同一主語・意志的）／He renovated the house so he could work from home. (same subject, volitional)

2. V-る／V-ない　よう（に）〈admonition〉

（1）忘 れ物 をしないようにしてください。／Don’t leave anything behind.

（2）時間内 に終了 するようお願 いします。／Please finish within the time (allowed).

（3）風邪 をひかないようご注意 ください。／Please take care not to catch a cold.

（4）私語 は慎 むようにしなさい。／Please refrain from whispering amongst yourselves.

（5）集合 時間 は守 るように。／Keep to the appointed time.

（6）授業中 はおしゃべりしないように。／No chatting during class.

Used to give advice to or to remonstrate with the listener. Verbs such as しなさい／してください and お願いします are used in the latter half but are sometimes omitted, in which case the expression ends with ように. Also, it is possible to omit the に from ように but, where the sentence ends with ように, it is usual not to do so, as in examples (5) and (6). Used in the form V-ないように, this often expresses negative advice or recommendations.

3. V-る／V-ない　よう（に）〈prayer〉

（1）息子 が大学 に合格 できるよう神 に祈 った。／I prayed to God that my son would pass the university entrance exam.

（2）現状 がさらに改善 されるよう期待 している。／I hope that the present situation will improve again.

（3）《年賀状 》新 しい年 が幸 い多 き年 でありますよう祈 っております。／《New Year’s card》Wishing you a joyful new year.

（4）《病気 見舞 の手紙 》早 く全快 なさいますよう、祈念 いたしております。／《get-well card》I am praying for your swift and complete recovery.　

（5）どうか合格 できますように。／Wishing you success in the (e.g. entrance) exams.

（6）すべてがうまくいきますよう。／Hoping all goes well.

（7）あしたは雨 が降 りませんように。／Praying that it does not rain tomorrow.

Expresses one’s or another’s hopes, prayers and wishes. Verbs such as 祈る(pray), 祈念する(say a prayer), 念じる(pray silently), 望む(desire), 願う(wish), 希望する(hope) and 期待する(expect) are used after ように. As in examples (5) and (6), the expression can end with ように. In such cases the polite form is usually used before ように. It is often used to bring a speech or letter to a close.

4. V-る／V-ない　よう（に）いう

（1）すぐ家 に帰 るように言 われました。／I was told to go home at once.

（2）これからは遅刻 しないように注意 しておきました。／I warned them not to be late from now on.

（3）戻 りましたら、家 に電話 するようお伝 えください。／Please tell him to call me at home when he comes back (to the office).　

（4）隣 の人 に、ステレオの音量 を下 げてもらうように頼 んだ。／I asked my neighbor to turn the volume of her stereo down.

Using verbs of communication, such as 言う(say) and 伝える(convey) in the latter half, this is used to indirectly quote a request. Direct quotations take the following form: command/request+と+verb of communication.

（例）「すぐ帰れ」と言った。／She said, “Go home at once.”

（例）「ステレオの音量を下げてください」と頼んだ。／I asked, “Please would you turn down the volume of your stereo?”

5. V-る／V-ない　ようにする

（1）私 は肉 を小 さく切 って、こどもにも食 べられるようにした。／I cut the meat into small pieces so that even children could eat it.

（2）大 きな活字 を使 い、老人 にも読 みやすいようにする。／We use large print so that it’s easy for the elderly to read.

（3）できるだけ英会話 のテレビを見 るようにしている。／I’m watching as much English conversation program on TV as I possibly can.

（4）彼女 の機嫌 を損 ねることは言 わないようにした。／I tried not to say things that would hurt her feelings.

（5）試験日 には、目覚 まし時計 を2台 セットして寝坊 しないようにしよう。／On exams days I set two alarm clocks so that I don’t overlay.

（6）油 ものは食 べないようにしている。／I try not to eat fried foods.

Means to make efforts with the aim of/to aim to/to see to it that an action or situation occurs. As in examples (4)-(6), when the negative form is used, it means to aim for the action or situation not to occur....ようにしている of (3) and (6) means to do that thing customarily. A verb usually comes before ように but, as in example (2), V-やすい is also used. In this case 読みやすくする could also be used.

6. V-る／V-ない　ようになる

（1）日本語 が話 せるようになりました。／I have become able to speak Japanese.

（2）眼鏡 をかければ、黒板 の字 が見 えるようになります。／I can see the letters on the blackboard if I wear my glasses.

（3）赤 ちゃんはずいぶん活発 に動 くようになりました。／The baby has started moving very vigorously.

（4）隣 の子供 は最近 きちんとあいさつするようになった。／The neighbor’s child has recently begun to make the proper greetings.

（5）注意 したら文句 を言 わないようになった。／After I had a word, he stopped complaining.

Taking the dictionary form of verbs, expresses a change from a situation in which something is not possible to one in which it is, or, from one in which a thing cannot be realized to one in which it can. It is often used to express possibility in the form V-れる, as in example (1). In cases where the negative form is used, as in (5), it expresses a change to a situation in which a thing is not done. In this case 言わなくなった could also be said.

<< 【よもや】 | Home | 【よる】 >>

【より】

1. ...より（も／は）

［N／V　より（も／は）］

（1）今年 の冬 は昨年 よりも寒 い。／This winter is colder than last year’s.

（2）このシャツの方 がさっき見 たのより色 がきれいだ。／The color of this shirt is nicer than the one we saw before.

（3）休 みの日 は外 へ出 かけるよりうちでごろごろしている方 が好 きだ。／On holiday days I like to be idle at home rather than go outside.

（4）田中 さんの送別会 は予想 していたよりずっと多 くの人 が集 まってくれました。／Many more people than expected gathered for Tanaka-san’s farewell party.

（5）やらずに後悔 するよりは、無理 にでもやってみた方 がいい。／You would be better off having a go at it, however impossible it may seem, than regretting afterwards not having even tried.

（6）仕事 は思 ったよりも大変 だった。／The job was more difficult than I had thought.

（7）事件 の背景 は、私 が考 えていたよりも複雑 なようだ。／It seems that the circumstances of the incident are more complicated than I had thought.

In the forms XよりもYのほうがZ and YはXよりもZ, shows X as the standard for comparison. In casual conversation the forms such as the following can also be used: よりか, それよか.

（例）レストランよりか居酒屋の方がリラックスできていいんじゃないかな。／I think a bar is better than a restaurant because we can relax there.

（例）今から外食しに行くのもいいけど、それよか一緒に買い物に行ってうちで作って食べない？／We could eat out but, rather than do that, why don’t we go shopping together and then cook at home?

2. ...というより

（1）彼 は堅 実家 というよりけちだと言 う方 が当 たっている。／It’s closer to the mark to see him as stingy rather than prudent.

（2）彼女 はきれいというよりはむしろ個性的 なタイプで、独特 のファッション感覚 がある。／More than just being pretty, she is a unique type; she has her very own sense of fashion.

（3）彼 の書 いた英文 は、できが悪 いというより、むしろもう絶望的 だと言 った方 がいいくらいひどい。／His English composition wasn’t just bad; I’d rather say it was so horrible as to be hopeless.

（4）あいつは酒 を飲 むというより流 し込 むと言 った方 がいいような飲 み方 をする。／That guy’s way of drinking sake is not so much drinking as it is pouring it down.

（5）こんなパーティーは、楽 しいというよりも退屈 なだけで、一部 の人 のためのバカ騒 ぎとしか思 えない。／This kind of party is actually just boring rather than fun, and I can’t think of it as anything other than horseplay for a small group of people.

Used to compare ways of expressions about or ways of judging a certain thing. Means “You could say X, or see it X way but, in comparison Y is more appropriate.” As in examples (2) and (3), it is often used together with むしろ.

3. ...よりない

a. V-るよりない

（1）どうしても大学 に通 う気 が起 きないのなら、もう退学 するよりないだろう。／If you can’t bring yourself to attend lectures, there’s nothing to do but drop out of university.

（2）文句 を言 っても仕方 がない。とりあえず今 できることを一生懸命 やるよりない。／It’s no use complaining. For now, all we can do is give it our very best effort.

（3）こんな不景気 なら、どこでもいいから採用 してくれるところに就職 するよりなさそうだ。／It seems that, in this kind of recession, all we can do is look for work anywhere they will employ us.

Expresses that, in situations where there is a problem, there is no other way of resolving it. ...しかない and ...以外にない can also be used.

b. V-るよりほか（に／は）ない

（1）今 さらあれはうそだったとも言 えないし、隠 しとおすよりほかにない。／At this point we can’t say that it was a lie, so we have no choice but to cover it up.

（2）雪 はだんだん激 しくなってきたが、引 き返 すこともできないし、とにかく山小屋 まで歩 くよりほかはなかった。／The snow gradually became stronger, but as we couldn’t retrace our steps, we had no choice but to walk on to the mountain hut.

（3）放 っておけばあの地域 のリゾート開発 は進 む一方 だし、こうなったら反対 運動 を起 こすよりほかにないと思 った。／I thought that, if we ignored it, the development of the region’s resorts would proceed, so in that case, I had no choice but to start an opposition movement.

Expresses that, in situations in which there is a problem, there is no other way to resolve it. ...しかない and ...以外にない are also used.

c. ...よりほかに...ない

［Nよりほかに...ない］

［V-るよりほかに...ない］

（1）その部屋 は静 かで、時計 の音 よりほかに何 の物音 も聞 こえなかった。／The room was quiet and, apart from the ticking of the clock, you couldn’t hear a sound.

（2）田中 さんよりほかにこの仕事 を任 せられる人 はいない。／There’s nobody other than Tanaka-san to whom I can entrust this job.

（3）あなたよりほかに頼 れる人 がいないから、忙 しいのを承知 でお願 いしているのです。／There’s nobody but you I can depend on, so while I know that you’re busy, I’m asking you (this favor).

（4）せっかくのお休 みで天気 もいいのに、うちでテレビを見 るよりほかにすることはないのですか。／It’s finally the holidays and the weather is good, so don’t you have anything other to do than watch television inside?

Used with a negative expression coming afterwards to emphasize that “there is nothing other than that.” ...以外に...ない is also used.

d. V-るよりしかたがない

（1）お金 がないのなら、旅行 はあきらめるよりしかたがないね。／If you have no money, you have no choice but to give up your trip.

（2）自分 の失敗 は自分 で責任 を持 って始末 するよりしかたがない。／There is no other option but to deal with your failings by taking responsibility for them yourself.

（3）終電 が出 てしまったので、タクシーで帰 るよりしかたがなかった。／As the last train had left I had no other option but to go home by taxi.

（4）あさってからスキーに行 きたいのなら、さっさとレポートを書 いてしまうよりしかたがないでしょう。／If you want to go skiing after tomorrow, you have no choice but to hurry up and finish writing the report, you know.

Expresses that, although with reluctance, there is no other choice in order to resolve a situation. ...ほかしかたがない and ...以外にしかたがない are also used.

<< 【られたい】 | Home | 【られる2】 >>

【られる1】

This is the passive voice. In cases where the V in V-られる is a Group 1 verb, the dictionary form ending changes to the a-row and れる is added, as in 行く(go)→行かれる and 飲む(drink)→飲まれる. Where Group 2 verbs are used られる is added to the stem, as in 食べる(eat)→食べられる. 来る(come) becomes こられる and する(do) becomes される. V-られる conjugates in the same way as Group 2 verbs.

1. NがV-られる〈direct passive〉

（1）この地方 ではおもに赤 ワインが作 られている。／In this region red wine is primarily made.

（2）木曜日 の会議 は3時 から開 かれることになっている。／Thursday’s meeting will be started at three o’clock.

（3）この辞書 は昔 から使 われているいい辞書 だが、最近 の外来語 などはのっていない。／This is a good dictionary that has been used for a long time but it doesn’t contain recent loan words.

（4）昨夜 、駅前 のデパートで1億円 相当 のネックレスや指輪 が盗 まれた。／Last night, necklaces and rings worth 100 million yen were stolen from the department store in front of the station.

（5）来月 発売 される車 のカタログを手 に入 れた。／I got hold of a catalogue of cars to go on sale from next month.

This is used to give as the subject a thing which is acted upon or which is affected. Often used in factual descriptive sentences and in informative sentences. As the agent cannot be identified, it is usual for it not to appear in the sentence.

2. NがNにV-られる

a. NがNに（よって）V-られる〈direct passive〉

（1）漫画 週刊誌 は若 いサラリーマンによく読 まれている。／Weekly manga magazines are often read by young businessmen.

（2）その寺院 は7世紀 に中国 から渡来 した僧侶 によって建 てられた。／That temple was built by a priest who came over from China in the seventh century.

（3）このあたりの土地 はダイオキシンに汚染 されている。／The soil in this area is contaminated with dioxin.

（4）地震後 、その教会 は地域 の住民 によって再建 された。／After the earthquake, that church was rebuilt by the local residents.

（5）その展覧会 はフォード財団 によって支援 されている。／That exhibition is supported by the Ford Foundation.

Used to give as the subject a thing which is acted upon or which is affected. It is often used in factual descriptive sentences and in informative sentences. The agent is indicated by Nに or Nによって. In cases regarding the production of a thing (a work or building), and in formal speech, によって is primarily used.

b. NがN　に／から　V-られる〈direct passive〉

（1）おばあさんが犬 にかまれた。／An elderly lady was bitten by a dog.

（2）その子 は母親 にしかられて、泣 き出 した。／That child was scolded by his mother and burst out crying.

（3）彼女 は皆 にかわいがられて育 った。／She was raised being doted on by everyone.

（4）森 さんは知 らない人 から話 しかけられた。／Mori-san was spoken to by a stranger.

（5）彼 は正直 なので、だれからも信頼 されている。／Because he is honest, he is trusted by everyone.

（6）夜中 に騒 いだら、近所 の人 に注意 されてしまった。／When I made a lot of noise late at night, a neighbour admonished me.

Used to give as the subject a person who is acted upon or who is affected. A way of expressing a thing which occurs between two people from the viewpoint of someone other than the agent. The agent is indicated by Nに but when an action showing that a feeling, information or remark is given by the agent Nから is also used. When the speaker is affected by the action, the passive voice is often used to express the speaker’s viewpoint. Furthermore, it is usual for the sentence to convey the point of view of one person.

（×）夜中に騒いだら、近所の人が注意した。／I was noisy in the middle of the night and someone from the neighborhood admonished me.

（○）夜中に騒いだら、近所の人に注意された。／I was noisy in the middle of the night and was admonished by someone from the neighborhood.

c. NがNにV-られる〈indirect passive〉

（1）忙 しいときに客 に来 られて、仕事 ができなかった。／I had a visitor while I was busy and so I couldn’t do my work.

（2）A:日曜日 はいかがでしたか。／How was Sunday?

B:家族 でハイキングに行 ったんですが、途中 で雨 に降 られましてね。／I went hiking with my family but we were rained on while along the way.

A:それは大変 でしたね。／Oh, that was too bad.

（3）彼 は奥 さんに逃 げられて、すっかり元気 をなくしてしまった。／He was deserted by his wife and completely lost his will to live.

（4）子 どもに死 なれた親 ほどかわいそうなものはない。／There is nothing as sad as a parent who has a child die.

Used to relate the standpoint of a person adversely affected by something which has caused their situation. Corresponds with the respective active sentence which uses an intransitive verb such as 客が来る(visitors are coming) and 雨が降る(it rains). The agent is indicated by Nに but Nによって and Nから cannot be used.

3. NがNにNをV-られる

a. NがNにNをV-られる〈possessor passive〉

（1）森 さんは知 らない人 に名前 をよばれた。／Mori-san’s name was called by a stranger.

（2）わたしは今朝 、電車 の中 で足 をふまれた。／This morning my foot was trodden upon on the train.

（3）犯人 は警官 に頭 を撃 たれて重傷 を負 った。／The offender was injured after being struck over the head by a police officer.

（4）先生 に発音 をほめられて英語 が好 きになった。／I came to like English after my pronunciation was praised by my teacher.

Used to give as the subject the owner of the thing which is acted upon or affected. Used to show that, through an action which is done to a thing, the owner of that thing is troubled or perplexed. The thing possessed by the owner (such as their name, foot, or head) is indicated in the form Nを. If this possession is taken as the subject, the effect is often unnatural.

（×）私の足がふまれた。／My foot was trodden on.

（○）私は足をふまれた。／I had my foot trodden upon.

When the action is welcome from the point of view of the speaker, expressions which demonstrate gratitude such as V-てもらった are often used but, as in the ほめる of example (4), when a verb which essentially has a positive meaning is used in the passive voice, the development of feelings such as embarrassment or pride is implied.

b. NがNにNをV-られる〈indirect passive〉

（1）せまい部屋 でタバコを吸 われると気 分 が悪 くなる。／When someone smokes in a small room it makes me feel sick.

（2）夜遅 くまで会社 に残 って仕事 をされると、電気代 がかかって困 る。／If someone stays late working at the company, I worry that it costs electricity.

（3）次々 に料理 を出 されて、とても食 べきれなかった。／One dish after another was brought out and I just couldn’t eat it all.

（4）台所 のテーブルの上 に宿題 を広 げられると晩御飯 のしたくができないから、はやくどけなさい。／I want to prepare dinner but can’t if your homework is spread all over the table, so hurry up and move it.

（5）結婚 はおめでたいけど、今 あなたに会社 をやめられるのは痛手 だなあ。／Congratulations on your marriage, but it’s a blow to us that you’re leaving the company.

Used to express the standpoint of a person indirectly bothered by a thing which has happened to cause their situation. It corresponds with the respective active sentence which uses an transitive verb such as (だれかが)タバコを吸う and (だれかが)仕事をする and demonstrates that the speaker is troubled because of that. The agent is indicated by Nに but Nによって and Nから cannot be used. Often the agent is not indicated.

<< 【られる2】 | Home | 【れる2】 >>

【れる1】

Demonstrates potential. In cases where the V in V-れる is a Group 1 verb, the dictionary form ending changes to the e-row sound and る is added, as in 行く(go)→行ける and 飲む(drink)→飲める. Where Group 2 verbs are used, られる is added to the stem, as in 食べる(eat)→食べられる. 来る(come) becomes こられる or これる and する(do) becomes できる. V-れる conjugates in the same way as Group 2 verbs.

In cases where the V is a Group 1 verb, the potential aspect takes the different form V-れる from the passive voice V-られる (for example the form of possibility becomes 飲める, 書ける (can drink, can write) while the passive form becomes 飲まれる, 書かれる(be drunk (by someone), be written (by someone)). On the other hand, Group 2 verbs take the same form for both the potential and passive voices (both become 食べられる(can eat/be eaten (by someone)), 起きられる(can get up/be gotten up (by someone)), for example). However, in speech nowadays, the more people are omitting the ら from the possible V-れる and so it becomes 食べれる, 起きれる. Also, more people are using NをV-れる rather than NがV-れる.

1. NはNがV-れる

Generally NはNがV-れる is used but a person with an ability or potential is also sometimes indicated with Nに, as in NにNがV-れる.

a. NはNがV-れる〈ability〉

（1）リンさんはなっとうが食 べられますか。／Can Lyn-san eat nattoo?

（2）かれにできないスポーツはない。／There is no sport he cannot do.

（3）わたしにかれらの指導 ができるだろうか。／I wonder if I can coach them?

（4）読 めない漢字 があったら、そう言 ってください。／If there are kanji you cannot read, please say so.

（5）この本 は読 み出 したら、やめられない。／Once you start, you won’t be able to stop reading this book.

（6）どうしてもあの先生 の名前 が思 い出 せなくて冷 や汗 をかいた。／I couldn’t remember that teacher’s name no matter what and broke into a cold sweat.

（7）朝 6時 から練習 を開始 しますので、起 きられたら来 てください。／As practice will commence from six in the morning, please come if you can get up.

This expresses a possibility dependant on ability, skill, or willpower.

b. NはNがV-れる〈possibility〉

（1）あの店 ではいつも珍 しいものが食 べられる。／You can always eat unusual things in that shop.

（2）仕事場 の人 はだれでもそのファックスが使用 できる。／Everyone at the workplace can use that fax.

（3）この動物園 では、子供 は無料 でイルカのショーが見 られる。／At this zoo, children can watch the dolphin show for free.

（4）わたしが直接 話 せたらいいのですが、あいにく都合 が悪 いんです。／I would have liked to speak to them directly, but unfortunately it is not convenient.

（5）両親 に言 えないことでも、友達 になら言 える。／I can say things to my friends that I can’t even say to my parents.

（6）辞書 は図書館 で借 り出 せないので、ひまなときに調 べに行 くつもりだ。／As you can’t take the dictionaries out of the library, I intend to go and look (it) up when I am free.

（7）昨日 は答 えが聞 けなかったので、きょうもう一度 たずねてみます。／As I wasn’t able to get a response yesterday, I’ll pay a visit again today.

Expresses that there is a possibility which is dependent on the situation or on opportunity. 見られる(can see/can be seen) and 見える(can see) are similar expressions but the difference is that 見える is used in cases where a thing spontaneously comes into view while 見られる is used when the possibility of seeing a thing occurs because a particular situation or opportunity arises.

（○）昨夜のスポーツニュースはいそがしくて見られなかった。／I wasn’t able to see last night’s sports news as I was busy.

（×）昨夜のスポーツニュースはいそがしくて見えなかった。／I wasn’t able to see last night’s sports news as I was busy.

（○）ここから白い建物が見えます。／You can see a white building from here.

（×）ここから白い建物が見られます。／You can see a white building appear from here.

聞ける and 聞こえる are the same in the sense that 聞ける shows that a thing spontaneously comes into hearing while 聞こえる is used when the possibility of hearing a thing occurs because a particular situation or opportunity arises.

（○）携帯ラジオをもってきたので、どこでも天気予報が聞ける。／Because I brought a handheld radio, we can hear the weather forecast anywhere.

（×）携帯ラジオをもってきたので、どこでも天気予報が聞こえる。／Because I brought a handheld radio, we can hear the weather forecast anywhere.

（○）どこからか鳥の声が聞こえた。／I could hear the sound of a bird from somewhere.

（×）どこからか鳥の声が聞けた。／I could hear the sound of a bird from somewhere.

For eyesight and hearing 見える and 聞こえる are used.

（例）生まれたばかりの猫の子は目が見えない。／The eyes of a newborn kitten are blind.

（例）補聴器をつけたら、耳がよく聞こえるようになった。／Wearing a hearing aid I could hear much better.

2. Nは V-れる〈characteristic〉

（1）この野菜 はなまでは食 べられない。／This vegetable cannot be eaten raw.

（2）この泉 の水 は飲 めます。／This fountain’s water can be drunk.

（3）悲 しい映画 かと思 ったが、見 てみるとけっこう笑 える映画 だった。／I had thought it was a sad movie, but watching it, it was quite funny.

（4）この教室 は300 人 は楽 に入 れます。／This classroom can comfortably take 300 people.

Expresses possibility as a property of a thing.

<< 【わけがない】 | Home | 【わけではない】 >>

【わけだ】

1. ...わけだ〈monologue-type〉

［N　な／である　わけだ］

［Na なわけだ］

［A／V　わけだ］

States a logically-derived conclusion from a fact or situation showing a previous utterance or context. Used in cases where the speaker or writer is explaining or elucidating something.

a. ...わけだ〈conclusion〉

（1）イギリスとは時差 が8時間 あるから、日本 が 11 時 ならイギリスは3時 なわけだ。／As there is an eight hour time difference between the United Kingdom and Japan, if it is eleven o’clock in Japan, it will be three o’clock in the United Kingdom.

（2）体重 を測 ったら 52 キロになっていた。先週 は 49 キロだったから、一週間 で3キロも太 ってしまったわけだ。／When I weighed myself I weighed 52 kilograms. I weighed 49 kilograms last week and so it means that I’ve put on three kilograms in one week.

（3）最近 円高 が進 んで、輸入品 の値段 が下 がっている。だから洋書 も安 くなっているわけだ。／Recently the value of the yen has been increasing and so the price of imported goods is going down. This means Western books are also getting cheaper.

（4）彼女 は中国 で3年間 働 いていたので、中国 の事情 にかなり詳 しいわけである。／She worked in China for three years and so she’s quite knowledgeable about the Chinese situation.

（5）私 は昔 から機械類 をさわるのが苦手 です。だから未 だにコンピュータも使 えないわけです。／I’ve always been bad with machines and so, to this day, I can’t even use a computer.

Takes the form X。(だから)Yわけだ. Shows that Y is the natural course of development from X, or is an inevitable conclusion. It is often used together with phrases such as だから, から and ので.

b. ...わけだ〈restatement〉

（1）彼女 の父親 は私 の母 の弟 だ。つまり彼女 と私 はいとこ同士 なわけだ。／Her father is my mother’s younger brother. That is to say, we are cousins.

（2）彼女 はフランスの有名 なレストランで5年間 料理 の修行 をしたそうだ。つまりプロの料理人 であるわけだ。／I hear that she spent five years training in a famous French restaurant. In other words, she’s a professional chef.

（3）彼 は大学 へ行 っても部室 でギターの練習 ばかりしている。要 するに講義 にはほとんど出 ていないわけだが、それでもなぜか単位 はきちんと取 れているらしい。／Even though he goes to school, he just practices his guitar in his room all the time. In other words, he hardly ever goes to his lectures but, even so, somehow he seems to pick up the credits he needs.

（4）父 は 20 年 前 に運転 免許 を取 っていたが車 は持 っていなかった。つまり長 い間 ペーパードライバーだったわけだ。／My father got his driver’s license twenty years ago but didn’t have a car. That is, for a long time he was a driver only on paper.

（5）私 はおいしいものを食 べている時 が一番 幸 せである。言 いかえれば、まずいものを食 べることほどいやなことはないわけで、それが強制 されたものだとなおさらである。／I’m happiest when eating something delicious. In other words, there’s nothing I like less than eating something bad, and if I’m forced to, then it’s even worse.

Used in the form X。（つまり）Yわけだ, Shows that X and Y are the same thing and that X can be said in other words as Y.

c. ...わけだ〈reason〉

（1）今年 は米 のできが良 くなかった。冷夏 だったわけだ。／The quality of this year’s rice was poor. It’s because it was a cool summer.

（2）彼女 は猫 を3匹 と犬 を1匹 飼 っている。一人 暮 らしで寂 しいわけだ。／She keeps three cats and one dog. It’s because she is living alone and is lonely.

（3）姉 は休 みの度 に海外旅行 に出 かける。日常 の空間 から脱出 したいわけだ。／When there’s a holiday my older sister goes on a trip abroad. It’s because she wants to escape from her everyday life.

（4）山田 君 は就職難 を乗 り越 えて大企業 に就職 したのに、結局 3ヶ 月 でやめてしまった。本当 にやりたかった音楽 関係 の仕事 をめざすことにしたわけだが、音楽 業界 も就職 はむずかしそうなので、心配 している。／Even though Yamada-kun overcame the job shortage and was employed by a large company, in the end he quit after three months. He did it because he decided to try to find a music-related job he really wants to do, but it seems that finding work is difficult in the music field too and so he’s worried.

Takes the form X。Yわけだ. Means that Y is the cause of X.

d. ...わけだ〈claim of fact〉

（1）4人 とも車 で来 るわけだから、うちの前 にずらっと4台 路上 駐車 することになるね。／As four people are arriving by car, I suppose there will be four cars parked in a line on the street in front of my house.

（2）私 は古本屋 めぐりが好 きで、暇 があると古本屋 を回 っては掘 り出 し物 を探 しているわけですが、このごろはいい古本屋 が少 なくなってきたので残念 に思 っています。／I like to look around second hand bookstores, so when I have free time, I go looking for bargains in them, but unfortunately there are fewer good second hand bookstores nowadays.

（3）私 、国際 交流 関係 のボランティア活動 はすでに 10 年 近 くやってきているわけでして、自慢 じゃありませんが、みなさんよりもずっと経験 はあるわけです。そういう立場 の者 としてご提案 させていただいているわけです。／I have been doing international exchange-related volunteer work for already ten years. I don’t mean to boast, but it’s from that position of being by far the most experienced that I make this proposal.

（4）ねえ、聞 いてくれる。昨日 駅前 に自転車 置 いて買 い物 に行 ったんだけど、帰 ってきたらなくなってるわけ。あちこち見 てみたけど見 つからなくて、しょうがないから警察 に行 ったわけよ。そしたら「鍵 かけてなかったんじゃないの」なんて言 われちゃって...。／Hey, listen to this. Yesterday, I leave my bike in front of the station and go shopping, but when I come back, it’s gone. I look here and there but can’t find it and so the only thing I can do is to go to the police. And then, they tell me something like “Well, you probably didn’t lock it....”

Used to insist on or emphasize that what one is saying is a fact with a logical foundation. Often used in speech and, especially even in cases where there is no logical basis for what is being said, it is often used as a sentence-ending particle. Frequently used when attempting to persuade another person by telling him what your thinking is.

As in examples (2), (3) and (4), used even when the listener does not know the truth, and in such cases can seem pushy, meaning “I think you know it too but....”

2. ...わけだ〈dialogue-type〉

Used to state the logical conclusion after accepting another person’s utterance. There are two possible situations for this: one is for the speaker to confirm the conclusion with the other person and the other is for the speaker to accept the conclusion as a fact based on the logical substantiation of the discourse of the other person.

a. ...わけだ〈conclusion〉

［それなら...わけだ］

［それじゃ...わけだ］

［じゃ...わけだ］

（1）A:森 さんは8年 もフィンランドに留学 していたそうですよ。／I hear that Mori-san has been to Finland to study for eight years.

B:へえ、そうなんですか。それならフィンランド語 は得意 なわけですね。／Wow, really? If that’s the case, she must be really good at Finnish.

（2）A:明日 から2泊 3日 で熱海 の温泉 に行 くの。／From tomorrow, I’m going to a hot spring in Atami for two nights, three days.

B:へえ、いいわね。じゃ、その間 仕事 のストレスからは解放 されるわけね。／Wow, that’s great. While you’re there you should get relief from your work stress.

Used in the form それなら／それじゃ／じゃ...わけだ, taking what the other person says, this shows the inevitable conclusion.

b. ...わけだ〈restatement〉

［つまり...わけだ］

［ようするに...わけだ］

（1）A:この間 書 いた小説 、文学賞 がもらえたよ。／The other day, I received a literary prize for the novel which I wrote.

B:あなたもようやく実力 が認 められたわけね。／At last, your real ability has been acknowledged.

（2）A:田中 くん、富士山 登山 に行 くのやめるんだって。帰 った次 の日 がゼミの発表 だから準備 しなくちゃいけないらしいよ。／Apparently, Tanaka-kun has decided not to climb Fuji-san (Mount Fuji). It seems that he has to prepare for a seminar presentation the next day.

B:ふうん。要 するに体力 に自信 がないわけね。／Humph. In other words, he has no confidence in his physical strength.

Takes the form つまり／要するに...わけだ. Used to rephrase something another person has just said.

c. ...わけだ〈reason〉

（1）A:川本 さん、車 大 きいのに買 いかえたらしいよ。／Kawamoto-san seems to have bought a new car even though the old one was so big.

B:へえ。子供 が生 まれて前 のが小 さくなったわけだな。／Really? The one he had before his child was born must have gotten too small.

A:いや、そうじゃなくて、単 に新車 がほしくなっただけのことらしいけど。／No, that’s not it. It seems he just wanted a new car.

（2）A:ぼく、今度 一軒家 に引 っ越 すことにしたんですよ。／I’ve decided to move to a detached house this time.

B:いいですね。でも家賃 高 いんでしょう。ってことは、お給料 、けっこうたくさんもらってるわけですね。／That’s good. But the rent must be high. So that means you must get a pretty high salary.

A:いや、それほどでもないですけどね。／No, not so much.

Expresses the reason for or cause of what the other person says.

d. ...わけだ〈understanding〉

［だから...わけだ］

［それで...わけだ］

［なるほど...わけだ］

［どうりで...わけだ］

（1）A:山本 さん、結婚 したらしいですよ。／It seems that Yamamoto-san has gotten married.

B:ああ、そうだったんですか。それで最近 いつもきげんがいいわけだな。／Oh, is that so? So that’s why she’s always in a good mood lately.

（2）A:彼女 は3年 もアフリカにフィールドワークに行 っていたそうですよ。／I hear that she went to do fieldwork in Africa for three years.

B:そうですか。道理 で日本 の状況 がよくわかっていないわけですね。／Really? It’s no wonder that she doesn’t know much about what’s going on in Japan.

（3）A:隣 の鈴木 さん、退職 したらしいよ。／It seems that Suzuki-san from next door has retired.

B:そうか。だから平日 の昼間 でも家 にいるわけだ。／Oh. So that’s why he’s at home during the day even on weekdays.

（4）あ、鍵 が違 うじゃないか。なんだ。これじゃ、いくらがんばっても開 かないわけだ。／Oh! This must be the wrong key. What’s up with it? No wonder I couldn’t open it however much I tried.

（5）田中 さん、一 か月 で4キロやせようと思 ってるんだって。なるほど、毎日 昼 ご飯 を抜 いているわけだわ。／They say Tanaka-san is trying to lose four kilograms in one month. That’s why he’s skipping lunch every day.

Often used in the form だから／それで／なるほど／どうりで...わけだ. Used in the form X。(だから)Yわけだdemonstrates that, although the speaker thought the reason for Y was mysterious, they have accepted that Y is so because of X after hearing information from another person which acts as the cause or reason.

Since the speaker comes to his/her own conclusion about the situation it is not necessary to use such phrases as ね afterwards but, in the polite form ...わけです, phrases such as ね and な are appended.

In example (1), the situation is that Yamamoto-san has always been in a good mood lately but the reason for that is not known. It shows that, on hearing the information from A that “It seems Yamamoto-san has got married,” B comes to understand that as the reason for Yamamoto-san’s being in a good mood of late. The situation in (4) is that one person, speaking to him/herself, does not understand why the door will not open and, discovering that he has the wrong key, comes to understand that as the reason for why the door will not open. As in (4) and (5), this is used by persons to detail something they have discovered for themselves or information they have heard from another. Combining that with facts already known, it is also used to show the speaker’s understanding of the situation.

3. ...わけだから

a. ...わけだから...はとうぜんだ

（1）小池 さんは何年 もインドネシア駐在員 だったわけだから、インドネシア語 が話 せるのは当然 です。／As Koike-san was located in Indonesia for some years, he naturally can speak Indonesian.

（2）あの議員 は履歴 を偽 って国民 をだましていたわけだから、辞職 は当然 のことだ。／As that member of the Diet lied about her background and deceived the people, it’s natural that she should resign.

（3）A:あの人 、クビになったんだってよ。／I heard that person was fired.

B:当然 よ。会社 のお金 、何百万 も使 い込 んでるのがばれたわけだから。／Of course. It’s because he was caught embezzling millions of the company’s money.

In the form XわけだからYは当然だ, takes X, a reliable fact, as the foundation for asserting that, as X is a fact, Y is the natural outcome.

b. ...わけだから...てもとうぜんだ

（1）彼女 は大学 を出 てからもう8年 も経 っているわけだから、結婚 していても当然 だろう。／As it’s already been eight years since she left university, she’s probably married by now.

（2）彼 は大学 を卒業 しているわけだからパソコンが使 えても当然 なのに、まったく使 えないらしい。／As he graduated from university, you would think he would be able to use a computer, but it seems he can’t use one at all.

（3）これだけ利用者 が増 えているわけだからもっと安 くしても当然 なのに、電車 やバスの運賃 は値上 がりする一方 だ。／Because the number of users is increasing, bus and train fares should get cheaper, but they just keep rising.

Takes the form XわけだからYても当然だ. Means “when one accepts X as a reliable fact, it would not be strange if Y were also true.” As in examples (2) and (3), it is often used in cases where, in reality, the opposite situation to Y has occurred and runs counter to expectations.

4. というわけだ／ってわけだ

（1）イギリスとは時差 が8時間 あるから、日本 が 11 時 ならイギリスは3時 （だ）というわけだ。／As there is an eight hour time difference with the United Kingdom, when it is eleven o’clock in Japan, that means it is three o’clock in the United Kingdom.

（2）彼女 の父親 は私 の母 の弟 だ。つまり彼女 と私 はいとこ同士 （だ）というわけだ。／Her father is my mother’s younger brother. In other words, that means we are cousins.

（3）A:あしたから温泉 に行 くんだ。／I’m going to a hot spring from tomorrow.

B:へえ、いいね。じゃ、仕事 のことを忘 れて命 の洗濯 ができるというわけだ。／Wow, that’s great. It means you can kick back and forget all about work.

（4）A:川本 さん、車 買 いかえたらしいよ。／It seems that Kawamoto-san has changed his car.

B:あ、そう。子供 が生 まれて前 のが小 さくなったってわけか。／Oh, really? Had the previous one gotten too small after his child was born?

This form is related to the〈conclusion〉,〈restatement〉and〈reason〉uses of Usage 1 and 2 in わけだ.

<< 【わけだ】 | Home | 【わけても】 >>

【わけではない】

1. ...わけではない

（1）このレストランはいつも客 がいっぱいだが、だからといって特別 においしいわけではない。／This restaurant is always full of customers but that fact doesn’t necessarily mean that the food is particularly good.

（2）私 はふだんあんまり料理 をしないが、料理 が嫌 いなわけではない。忙 しくてやる暇 がないだけなのだ。／The reason I don’t often cook is not that I dislike it. It’s just that I’m busy and don’t have the time to do it.

（3）私 の部屋 は本 で埋 まっているが、全部 を読 んだわけではなく、買 ってはみたものの開 いたことさえないというものも多 い。／My room is full of books but that doesn’t mean I have read them all. There are many which I haven’t even opened since I bought them.

（4）来月 から英会話 を習 うことにした。全然 話 せないわけではないのだが、日頃 英語 をしゃべる機会 がないので、いざというとき口 から出 てこないのだ。／I’ve decided to learn English conversation from next month. It’s not that I can’t speak it at all but, as I don’t have a regular chance to speak English, when it comes to the crunch it won’t come out of my mouth.

（5）娘 の外泊 をただ黙 って見 のがしているわけではないが、下手 に注意 したらかえって反発 するので、どうしたものかと考 えあぐねている。／I don’t just silently overlook my daughter staying out overnight but clumsily caution her and, as she responds by rebelling all the more, I am at a loss as to what is to be done.

（6）弁解 をするわけではありませんが、昨日 は会議 が長引 いてどうしても抜 けられなかったのです。／It’s no excuse but yesterday’s meeting dragged on and I couldn’t escape no matter what.

（7）A:イギリスへ行 ってしまうんだそうですね。／I hear that you’re going to the UK.

B:ええ。でも別 に永住 するわけじゃありませんし、5年 たったらまた帰 ってきますよ。／Yes, but it’s not permanent; I’ll be back when five years have passed.

（8）A:今度 の日曜日 に映画 に行 きませんか。／Shall we go to see a movie next Sunday?

B:日曜 ですか。／Sunday?

A:予定 があるんですか。／Do you have plans?

B:いえ、予定 があるわけではないのですが、その日 はうちでゆっくりしたかったので...。／No, it’s not that I have plans but I wanted to spend that day relaxing at home....

Used to deny that which is thought to be naturally derived from what has just been said or from the current situation. It is often used together with phrases such as だからといって, 別に and 特に.

In example (1), it can generally be concluded from いつも客がいっぱいだ that “the food is delicious” but this is denied as not being the case. Meaning “It is a mistake to conclude that the food is delicious,” おいしいわけではない, in comparison to the directly negative 料理はおいしくない, becomes a euphemistic, indirectly negative expression. Therefore, as in (8), it can be used to make a more indirect refusal than 予定はありませんが. そういうわけではないのですが can also be said. Furthermore, as in (3) and (4), when used with words such as 全部・みんな and 全然・まったく, it becomes a partial denial, meaning for example, “I have read a few” or “I can speak it a little.”

2. というわけではない

ってわけではない

（1）このレストランはいつも満員 だが、だからといって特 においしいというわけではない。／This restaurant is always full but, be that as it may, it doesn’t mean the food is especially delicious.

（2）私 はふだんあまり料理 をしないが、料理 がきらい（だ）というわけではない。忙 しくてやる暇 がないだけだ。／I don’t cook very often but it doesn’t mean I hate cooking. It’s just that I’m busy and don’t have the time to do it.

（3）A:あした映画 に行 かない？／Coming to the movies tomorrow?

B:あした、か。うーん。／Tomorrow? I’m not sure....

A:私 とじゃいやだってこと？／You don’t want to go with me?

B:いや、いや（だ）ってわけじゃないんだけど…。／No, no, that’s not it....

（4）今日 は学校 へ行 く気 がしない。雨 だから行 きたくないというわけではない。ただ何 となく今日 は何 もする気 になれないのだ。／I don’t feel like going to school today. It’s not because it’s raining. It’s just that, for some reason, I don’t feel like doing anything today.

This form connects わけではない with という／って. As in the 雨だから行きたくない of example (4), in cases where the logic XだからY appears explicitly within the same sentence, it is usual to use というわけではない rather than わけではない.

<< 【わけても】 | Home | 【わざわざ】 >>

【わけにはいかない】

1. V-るわけに（は）いかない

（1）ちょっと熱 があるが、今日 は大事 な会議 があるので仕事 を休 むわけにはいかない。／I have a bit of a fever but there is an important meeting today and so I can’t take a holiday from work.

（2）カラオケに誘 われたが、明日 から試験 なので行 くわけにもいかない。／I was invited to karaoke but I have tests from tomorrow and so I cannot make it.

（3）体調 を崩 した仲間 を残 して行 くわけにもいかず、登山隊 はしかたなくそこから下山 することになった。／They couldn’t leave their unwell friend behind and so the mountaineering party had no choice but to descend the mountain from there.

（4）いくらお金 をもらっても、お宅 の息子 さんを不正 に入学 させるわけにはいきません。／However much money you give me, I can’t dishonestly allow your son to pass into this school.

（5）もう 30 近 い娘 をいつまでも甘 やかしておくわけにもいかないが、かと言 って自立 できる収入 もないのに出 て行 けと放 り出 すわけにもいかない。／I can’t keep spoiling my daughter who is almost thirty but, having said that, as she has no income by which she can be independent, neither can I just throw her out.

（6）A:うちで猫 を飼 っていること、大家 さんには内緒 にしてもらえませんか。／Will you keep it a secret from the landlord that we’re keeping a cat in the house?

B:いや、そういうわけにはいきませんよ。契約 ではだめなことになっているんですから。それにみんな猫 の鳴 き声 で迷惑 しているんですよ。／No, I can’t do that. It’s against the terms of the contract. Besides, everyone is annoyed by its cries.

Means “It is not possible to do so.” It does not simply mean “cannot do” but rather that “thinking from general knowledge, socially accepted ideas or past experience (something) cannot be done.”

私はお酒が飲めない shows that the speaker is constitutionally a weak drinker and, therefore “cannot drink.” However, お酒を飲むわけにはいかない does not mean that constitutionally they are a weak drinker, but rather that, for some reason (for example, they have come by car), they cannot drink. Also, as in the そういうわけにはいかない of example (6) where it refers to the inability to keep the secret, it can also be used in acknowledging the previous sentence.

2. V-ないわけに（は）いかない

（1）他 の人 ならともかく、あの上司 に飲 みに誘 われたら付 き合 わないわけにはいかない。断 ると後 でどんなめんどうな仕事 を押 しつけられるかわからないのだから。／If it’s somebody else it’s okay, but if that supervisor invites you to go drinking with him, you have to go. If you refuse, you don’t know what kind of drudging job you’ll be made to do.

（2）実際 にはもう彼 を採用 することに決 まっていたが、形式上 はめんどうでも試験 と面接 をしないわけにはいかなかった。／In reality we had already decided to employ him but, formally, even though it’s troublesome, we had to conduct an exam and interview.

（3）今日 は車 で来 ているのでアルコールを飲 むわけにはいかないが、もし先輩 に飲 めと言 われたら飲 まないわけにもいかないし、どうしたらいいのだろう。／As I’ve come by car today I can’t drink alcohol, but if my superior tells me to drink I’ll have to. What should I do?

（4）A:あんなハードな練習 、もうやりたくないよ。疲 れるだけじゃないか。／I don’t want to do that kind of hard exercise any more. It will just make me tired (without any benefit).

B:そういうわけにはいかないだろう。監督 に逆 らったらレギュラーから降 ろされるぞ。／That’s no excuse. If you go against the coach you’ll be dropped as a regular.

Connected to the negative form of a verb, this expresses the obligation that “It is not possible not to carry out that action,” in other words, “must do.” This also takes as its reason generally knowledge, socially accepted ideas or past experience. As in (4), it can also be used in the form そういうわけ or, in other words, やらないわけ.